<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Exanastasis, or, The saints rising out of the heap or mass of dead bodies contained in the globe of the earth and sea ... Rev. 20. 5 hereunto, by way of preface, is here prefixed the comprisal of the substance of our former parcels ... / by William Sherwin ...</title>
            <author>Sherwin, William, 1607-1687?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 248 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59933</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3401</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34222</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14150883</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14150883</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102108</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59933)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102108)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1070:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Exanastasis, or, The saints rising out of the heap or mass of dead bodies contained in the globe of the earth and sea ... Rev. 20. 5 hereunto, by way of preface, is here prefixed the comprisal of the substance of our former parcels ... / by William Sherwin ...</title>
                  <author>Sherwin, William, 1607-1687?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 83 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First word of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained and with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Revelation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Resurrection.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:102108:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:102108:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, OR The Saints Riſing Out of the Heap or Maſs of dead Bodies contained in the Globe of the Earth and Sea, at the firſt bleſſed Reſurrection Decy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phered by Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5.</p>
                  <p>Whereunto, by way of Preface, is here prefixed, The Compriſal of the Subſtance of our former Parcels: With further, and more evident Diſcoveries, which may fitly be called, <hi>The Marrow of Divine Revelation Myſteries.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Opened by that Key given By Chriſt himſelf for that uſe and purpoſe, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                     <p>If by any means I might attain unto the Reſurrection of the dead, <bibl>
                           <hi>Phil. 3.11.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                     <p>The reſt of the Dead lived not till the thouſand years were ended, <bibl>
                           <hi>Rev. 20.5.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now I ſay that Jeſus Christ was a Miniſter of the Circumciſion, for the truth of God, to confirm the Promiſes made unto the Fathers, <bibl>
                           <hi>Rom. 15.8.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>By <hi>William Sherwin,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed 1674.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="proofs">
                  <pb facs="tcp:102108:2"/>
                  <head>The firſt Bodily Reſurrection of the Saints a Thouſand Years before the reſt of the Dead, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Proved four wayes.
<list>
                           <item>1. From the Text, with its dependancy as a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, and compared with Chriſts Doctrine there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.35, 36.</item>
                           <item>2. From the Context, as an explication of <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſion of the ſame matter and time, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9, 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3. From many other Scriptures, Reaſons and Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (together with our whole Syſtem premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) proving the ſame.
<list>
                                 <item>1. Poſitively, that it is Bodyly.</item>
                                 <item>2. Negatively, that it is not ſpiritual, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>4. From ſundry Texts in the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſpeaking of the ſame thing of which this Revelation, <hi>ch.</hi> 20, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is a ſure Explication, with Anſwers to ſundry Objections.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Improved to divers u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.
<list>
                           <item>1. For Information, in nine particulars.</item>
                           <item>2. By Reference to Uſes of Terror and Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before.</item>
                           <item>3. For Admonition and Warning to all that profeſs Chriſtian Religion, now in the due ſeaſon to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove themſelves as Wiſe Virgins, both in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring and watching for the Bridegrooms coming, ſhortly approaching, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.15.</item>
                           <item>4. For Exhortation alſo, to all ſuch, to thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102108:2"/>
                  <head>The Compriſal of our whole work, and the Divine Myſteries therein explained and confirmed by many ſorts of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, deducted and drawn from the ſame Principles by way of Preface unto a following Tract on <hi>Rev. 20.5.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>DEar Chriſtians, whoſe part ſhall be in the firſt bleſſed Reſurrection, a thouſand years before the reſt of the Dead. We having been, by Gods ſpecial Grace, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly lead in the way of Diſcovery, as by many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uſeful diſtinctions contained in our <hi>Key,</hi> and applyed in our whole work, ſo particularly by our Diſtinctions, <hi>Aſſert.</hi> 6. of the ſame, of the ſeveral ſenſes of the comings of Chriſt, and more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially having firſt thereupon been led on in the compoſing of our Practical Tract upon <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.20. ſetting forth Chriſts ſecond Perſonal coming to deſtroy Antichriſt, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9, 11, 13, 14. many ways diſtinguiſhed from his deſcending a thouſand years after, at the laſt Trump and general Rapture, and glorious change of all the Saints, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.15, 16. &amp; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.51, 52. For at the former he brings all the Spirits of the deceaſed Saints that ſleep in Jeſus with him: at the latter, they, and all the reſt of the Saints, departed afterwards, ſhall in the twinkling of an eye be rapt up to meet him in the air. From the former Chriſt withdraws at the end of the thouſand years; after the latter, they ſhall ever be with him the Lord. In the former, he comes in the Clouds, that through them mortal eyes may then behold him: upon the latter, all Clouds will be aboliſhed, and Heaven and Earth will flee away before his face, and no plaee be found for them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.11. when the rapt Saints eyes and wicked mens then raiſed will be fitted to behold his glory on the great white Throne: at the former the wicked Quick will be judged with temporal deſtruction, <hi>viz. Turk</hi> and <hi>Pope,</hi> and ſuch as do offend and work iniquity will be taken out of his Kingdom, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.41. at the latter, the Saints will firſt be rapt up before the wicked riſe to be judged: at the former, the Saints will be judged with a judgment of reward in this world in the thouſand years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19. having before there ſuffered for Chriſt, they ſhall then reign with him, upon the firſt ſaid Reſurrection: at
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102108:3"/>the latter, they ſhall be joyned with Chriſt in judging the wicked: at the former he comes from the right hand of his Father, to make his foes his footſtoole; at the latter, he is ſaid to deſcend with a ſhout, and the voice of an Arch-angel and the Trump of God: at the firſt, he puts down all Rule, and all Authority, and Power that ſtood againſt him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24. at the latter, he deſtroys the laſt enemy, Death, <hi>v.</hi> 25. above a thouſand years after: at the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, <hi>Ezekiels</hi> Gog and Magog, <hi>ch.</hi> 38. 39. <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Pope</hi> will be deſtroyed. The <hi>Turk</hi> with a complication of Judgments, <hi>v.</hi> 22. the other, by the laſt Vial, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. &amp; <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. &amp; <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. 19. before the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> called <hi>Jehovah Shamma,</hi> ſhall be ſet up, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 40. to the end of that book, wherein <hi>Daniel</hi> agrees, <hi>ch.</hi> 11.45. and <hi>ch.</hi> 12.1, 2, 3. at the latter, the laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> ſhall be conſumed with fire from God out of Heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9. at the former will be the New Heavens, and the New Earth, being the time of the reſtitution of all things; at the latter, will be the end of the world, and the diſſolution of all things: at the former, only the Saints will be raiſed, at the firſt bodily Reſurrection which Chriſt brought with him; but at the latter, all the reſt of the dead, <hi>viz.</hi> Saints departed ſince that former coming, and all the wicked at the laſt Trump. Theſe, or the like we conſidered in the foreſaid Tract.</p>
                  <p>We alſo found from <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19, 20, 21. that God had ſpoken of things to be before in and after the ſaid thouſand years, as we have ſet down in 36. particulars in our firſt convincing Argument in the <hi>Word Written</hi>) by the mouth of all his holy Prophets ſince the world began, which we have in order made manifeſt from <hi>page</hi> 44. of our <hi>Irenic.</hi> but more eſpecially in <hi>ch.</hi> 5,6,7,8. of the ſame, which may deſerve your ſerious reading, and conſideration, as being ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Divine Foundation of the ſame Truths.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe upon the drawing up of thoſe 16 <hi>Divine Theſes,</hi> or <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, page</hi> 3, 4, 5, 6. of the <hi>Irenicon,</hi> in the 11 and 12th of them is contained that needful Diſtinction of the two fold Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſts execution of his three great Offices. 1. In reſpect of his Univerſal Church in the three great Periods of the world: as the work the Father gave him to do in all times of his Mediator<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. 2. In regard of the benefit always flowing from that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking to all Gods faithful people by the operation of the holy Spirit in their Souls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The former we have handled in our next Practical piece on <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. confirmed therein by Scripture, Reaſon, Experience, with many improvements made thereof in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102108:3"/>the ſaid Treatiſe, drawn up upon that ſaid account, which I wiſh may be well conſidered by all Chriſtians as another Foundation of them.</p>
                  <p>In the next place we have as it were in ſome ſort paſſed <hi>per ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> unto the 20th <hi>chap.</hi> of the <hi>Revelation:</hi> (many others having of late uſefully handled things in the firſt 19 Chapters) by our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgments thereof, of the order of the times of the ſeven Seals, Trumpets and Vials; and of the Seal Propheſie, and Book Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, and in the Scheme of the Contemporaries in both, all which we mentioned in our late account, which are almoſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, being all before the Date of the Man of Sin be expired: that we might ſo more ſpeedily come to the conſideration of the thouſand years, <hi>ch.</hi> 20. wherein Chriſt will reign with his raiſed Saints in the world, as is plainly aſſerted by the repreſentatives, <hi>Rev</hi> 5.10. which was our main drift, by Gods gracious aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, for the uſe of all his faithful people, whoſe concernment we are more and more aſſertained it will ſhortly more and more appear to be exceedingly above what is uſually by moſt Chriſtians appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended of it: And alſo by Abridgments of <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſions for the Diſcovery of the Series, and order of both thoſe Myſtical Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of <hi>Dan.</hi> and the <hi>Revel.</hi> and thereupon (as the 4th head of our method propounded <hi>ch.</hi> 1. of the <hi>Irenicon</hi>) we compoſed our Book of Parallels to manifeſt the <hi>Revelation</hi> to be a Divine Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Comment upon the ſealed, or ſhut up parts or ſhort hints in <hi>Daniels</hi> Propheſie; which our Saviour hath orderly (though My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtically) explained, as we have often ſaid, (and it is a great truth of this nature to be known) whereby many former miſtakes of many men are evidently diſcovered (as we hinted formerly, <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert.</hi> 5. of the <hi>Key</hi>) for he that once attains, but competently, to apprehend the ſubject, nature, order of times and ſcope of the book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> hath made a good progreſs in the ſtudy of that moſt excellent Divine book of Propheſie. I will thus for your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit a little here touch upon them.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt</hi> the Subject thereof are the Fates and State of the Church, and her Enemies in the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire from Chriſts Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention to his coming again, to <hi>ch.</hi> 20. where firſt of the <hi>Aſian</hi> Churches Declention, and the great Red Dragons 10 Perſecutions till <hi>Conſtantines</hi> time for above 300 years to the end of the 6th Seal, <hi>Rev.</hi> 6. And then come on Gods Judgments upon the Empire for perſecuting the Saints before, in ruining the Civil State thereof by the blaſts of the 7 Trumpets, proceeding out of the ſeventh Seal;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102108:4"/>the 4 firſt whereof being the milder (yet by the barbarous Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons deadly wounded the Weſtern part in the ſixth head of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, <hi>ch.</hi> 8.) and about <hi>An.</hi> 600, The firſt Woe Trumpet the <hi>Saracens, Rev.</hi> 9.1. fell upon a great part of the Eaſtern Empire, being the King of the South, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.40. and about 1100. the <hi>Turk</hi> began to overflow with his multitudes, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.40. being the King of the North, and the 2d Woe Trumpet, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.11. and the utter deſolation of the laſt head who healed the deadly wound given to the former head will be at Chriſts appearance and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> The nature of this book is a double Scheme of theſe things that concern the Civil State ond Eccleſiaſtical State, and accordingly twice running over the ſame times, in reſpect of each of them for about 1660. years and more. Firſt in the Seal Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, <hi>ch.</hi> 6, 7, 8, 9. And then again of the Eccleſiaſtick State in the little book, <hi>ch.</hi> 10. which begins <hi>ch.</hi> 12. with the ſaid primative per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions in the Battle with the Dragon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Churches time, times, and an half from her entering into her wilderneſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: wherein the Lords two Witneſſes feed her by their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry 1260. years, during Antichriſts perſecutions 42. months of years, (which are all the ſame time, <hi>ch.</hi> 13.) and as the true Church was nouriſhed by the ſaid Witneſſes along her Wilderneſs condition; ſo by their Preaching ſhall Antichriſt in the time of the ſeven Vials be conſumed thereby as by the breath of Chriſts mouth, <hi>ch.</hi> 14. which Vials are ſet down, <hi>ch.</hi> 15, 16. and explained and executed to <hi>ch.</hi> 20. about the time the laſt ſaid My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Trumpet will ſound, <hi>ch.</hi> 11.15. when the Kingdoms of the world ſhall become the Kingdoms of God, and of his Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Thirdly</hi> for the order and times thereof; <hi>See our ſeveral A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgments mentioned in our Account,</hi> p. 4. Inreference to the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel</hi> a <hi>Breviate</hi> of which ye may alſo obſerve afterwards in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering <hi>Davids</hi> ſure Mercies to be performed in Chriſt, after he as Gods Commiſſioner upon his receivlng the Book with ſeven Seals given to him by the Father, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.1. to open the Seals, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute the Contents of the ſame, until he ſit upon the Throne of his Father <hi>David, Luke</hi> 1.32. which will be <hi>Davids</hi> ſure Mercies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting his Kingdom for ever.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> as for the End, Drift and Scope of <hi>Revelation</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, we have of late ſpecially endeavoured to manifeſt it to be to ſhew to the Church of Chriſt what advantage and benefit ſhe ſhall have by means of her former ſufferings for Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102108:4"/>reign with him in his <hi>Davidical</hi> Kingdom in the world, which as it may be manifeſt by our 8 Convincing Arguments in the Word Written, and by our 12 Foundations of Faith: and our New Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem upon <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.17. and alſo from our Key and account, yet we having of late obtained, by the ſame grace of God, ſome farther Diſcoveries to this purpoſe, concerning this farther Aſſertion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the drift and ſcope of <hi>Revelation</hi> Propheſie, namely, That <hi>ch. Rev.</hi> 20. with the <hi>Jeruſalem State</hi> ſet forth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21, &amp; 22. are the great Key of all antient revealed and promiſed Mercies to the faithful Forefathers and their ſpiritual Seed, chiefly to be fulfilled in that ſtate and time of the ſaid 1000. years; which that they ſhall be in the world, may appear by our 15 Reaſons approved of by the Learned, in our <hi>New Jeruſalem, page</hi> 9, 10, 11. which excellent uſeful Key, as it is Divinely fitted by our great Prophet the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the faithful and true witneſs, to make a ſtrong, full and clear Diſcovery of the Wiſdom, Power and Juſtice of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his, and his Churches Enemies: ſo eſpecially of the Mercy, Truth and Faithfulneſs of God towards his faithful Servants, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing revealed, carried on, and to be perfected; and that in many particulars, chiefly in thoſe times which all true Chriſtians ſhould in theſe laſt times, wherein they draw on a pace to be fulfilled, know and be well inſtructed in, for their encouragement and comfort, at preſent, to glorifie God aforehand in reſpect of their Faith of them, that ſo they may be better fitted and prepared hereafter ſo to do, when they ſhall find in the enjoyment of them from what antient foundations of Faith, ſuch manifold great happineſs will be then derived unto them, in that world to come, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. in the renewed ſtate thereof; which I doubt not to manifeſt by the ſame Divine Aſſiſtance, very evidently to all ſerious unprejudiced and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Chriſtians, in the following Syſteme, of Gods moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Oeconomie or ordering his Houſhold the Church in the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, of ſuch revealed, promiſed, or convenanted Mercies, chiefly reſpecting thoſe times; but paſſing thence to eternal bleſſedneſs, for on ſuch, the ſecond Death ſhall have no power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now as the glory of Gods wonderful free Grace, firſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by himſelf to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve, Gen.</hi> 3.15. was by their faith applyed as to redound to all their faithful Poſterity; ſo hath God been graciouſly pleaſed to derive many rivolets of like grace from the ſame fountain head, running their ſeveral cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in their ſeveral times, but all falling in their fulleſt ſtreams (Divine Wiſdom and Goodneſs ſo ordering the ſame) as it were
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102108:5"/>into thoſe more narrow Seas or Streights of the ſaid 1000 years, and from thence paſſing into the vaſt Ocean of Eternity, whither they Saints ſhall all be conveighed in due time, order and manner from their happy enjoyments in that ſtate appointed for them; wherein in the mean time his Wiſdom, Mercy, Truth and Faithfulneſs will in ſuch reſpects ſhine out gloriouſly to them in ſo great enjoyments as they ſhall then obtain, and will be thereby many ways more fitted (with the bleſſed Angels) to glorifie God the Father, Son and Holy Spirit, in their rendering all due praiſe unto him for the ſame, both then, and for ever more: which they could never do if the raiſed Saints at the firſt ſaid Reſurrection of their bodies had not a part in all the happineſs of that tryumphant ſtate of Chriſts Church in the ſaid 1000. years; and in all the benefits and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges thereof, <hi>viz.</hi> of the ſaid revealed Promiſes and Covenants to the Fathers of old and their ſpiritual Seed, which we hope to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt in what follows, to be according to the word of Gods ſaid Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed Grace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And to that purpoſe we now proceed to the ſaid Syſteme of Gods declared Mercy at the fall of Man, and in all the ſucceeding <hi>Millenniums,</hi> or thouſands of years in order fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="system">
                  <head>The Syſtem of Gods declared Mercy at the Fall for a thouſand Generations, or ſeven thouſand Years, as by the Divine Guidance of his Word and Spirit (which we ſhall ever humb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and thankfully deſire to acknowledg to his Praiſe) he hath diſcovered to us, from the Fall of Man, to the end of the World: Eſpecially as is further diſcloſed by a double Key.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> of <hi>Daniels</hi> Sealed hints of Propheſie to <hi>ch.</hi> 20. of <hi>Rev. Secondly,</hi> of Gods moſt antient Revealed and Promiſed Mercies to the end of the <hi>Revelation.</hi> [Hinted alſo from <hi>Daniels</hi> Lot, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.12.]</p>
                  <div n="1" type="millenium">
                     <head>Of the order of the latter in the firſt Millen, or thouſand years.</head>
                     <p>WHen God in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing had finiſhed his great and good work of the Worlds Creation in ſix days, and made Man his Deputy Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler in it: and the Devil malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, by the Serpents ſubtilty,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102108:5"/>and upon the advantage of the womans weakneſs, had brought about the womans ſin and mans fall: The Trinune Diety of his own meer grace, was merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully pleaſed, to manifeſt his moſt glorious divine goodneſs, by a wonderful Declaration of his ſaid free, and infinite mercy towards loſt mankind, and by himſelf to publiſh that Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of all future happineſs (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining in the Womb of it) all future revealed and promiſed mercies and Covenants to his Church, and People in all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding times, by declaring that the ſeed of the Woman ſhall break the Serpents head, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. which Chriſt in his Mediator<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, from that time undertook and hath and doth, and will ſtill carry on, until he ſhall make his Foes his Footſtool, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.1. eminently at the beginning of the 1000 years, by deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>Pope,</hi> and taking out of his Kingdome all things that offend, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And by binding Satan for that time, and totally and finally deſtroy all his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies at the end, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. which is largely conſidered in our trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, upon that Text: And will not theſe things greatly concern, the raiſed &amp; living Saints too at that time? eſpecially to ſee the laſt moſt obſtinate and deſperate Enemies, both taken of, and taken away for ever: Oh how will then the Heavens rejoyce, and the Earth be glad: What Halelujahs will then be ſung by Angels and men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, When the old world was much heightened in wickedneſs: God alſo by <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch</hi> the 7th. <hi>Adam</hi> his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed tranſlation, as a worker of Righteouſneſs, excited men to well doing by Faith, and as a type of Chriſt, upon whoſe aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion all his Followers ſhall twice aſcend by Chriſt: Firſt, in this Souls by his powerful grace, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their natural Life: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, In Soul and Body both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, at the firſt bleſſed bodily Reſurrection of the juſt, and at the general Rapture of all the Saints at the laſt Trumpet, when the ſaid 1000 years ſhall be end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And may not real good Chriſtians, by their firſt aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into a ſtate of grace, by Chriſt, gueſs what degrees of joy and happineſs they ſhall riſe unto in Kingdom and Glory with Chriſt, at the Reſurrection and Rapture?</p>
                     <p>And alſo by <hi>Enochs</hi> Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Viſion, of Chriſts coming to Judgement in the firſt and ſecond Act thereof; recorded by <hi>Jude v.</hi> 14. <hi>Loe he cometh with</hi> 10000 <hi>of his Saints,</hi> to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Judgement, &amp;c. to warn all men to avoid evil; the firſt ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial Act thereof is ſet down, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. at the the beginning of the 1000 years, the ſecond <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.11. after the 1000
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102108:6"/>years are ended; and will not all the ſaid Saints magnifie Gods Holineſs. Power, Juſtice and Truth, in both his ſo reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and then executed Acts of Judgement <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="millenium">
                     <head>In the <hi>2d.</hi> millen or <hi>1000</hi> years.</head>
                     <p>GOd about an 1656. did alſo by <hi>Noah</hi> a Preacher of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, 1. Typifie, 2. Covenant, 3. Propheſie concerning theſe times, and things after he had warned the wicked world, then by his Preaching of Repentanae to them in the time of the Arks preparation 120. years, when their wickedneſs was arrived to the height; which Ark as it was for the ſaving of his own houſe then, or all ſuch penitent or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Sinners, that would then come into it, wherein ſafety then (as ſalvation at all times, is onely to be had in the Church of Chriſt.) So Chriſt will be the true and ſafe Ark of his Church, or Family, when the the world in part, or in whole ſhall periſh by Fire, at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning or end of the 1000 years; and will not the remembrance of <hi>Noah;</hi> Ark, illuſtrate Chriſts glory then being the Antitype thereof, in doing ſuch works for his Saints, how will he then be admired of them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. God alſo made a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with <hi>Noah,</hi> confirmed by the Rainbow, the Token there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of for the worlds preſervation, from drowning to the end, and alſo gave his bleſſings to men, and all ſorts of Creatures upon the Earth, to make them fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, <hi>Gen.</hi> 8, &amp; 9. whereby the world continues with its fruitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ever fince by Seed time and harveſt, as the great Stage for all Gods future actings, in Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies or Judgements, which his word teſtifieth have cheifly their fulfillings in the ſaid 1000 years, after which time it muſt continue the little ſpace of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans looſing, And as the world will ſo long be the Stage for ſuch actings of God, until the New Heavens and the New Earth ſhall ceaſe, ſo its fruitfulneſs was to be the accommodation for all ſuch purpoſes, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Earth in thoſe times, muſt power out its plenty in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance, for the Churches-ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation in that State, then ſaith the 67th. Pſal. <hi>The Earth ſhall yeild her increaſe of thoſe times,</hi> &amp;c. ſo Joel 3.18. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs in that day, that the Mountains ſhall drop down with new Wine, and the Hills ſhall flow with Milk: [ſee more in our Key of</hi> Noahs <hi>Covenant.</hi>]</p>
                     <p>And as the Saints grace, and Gods goodneſs in the Earths fruitfulneſs will be inlarged (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter its ſo many thouſand years bearing Fruit before) ſo it will be much more fruitful in thoſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102108:6"/>laſt times of its being, (yet in its renewed condition) whence al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the praiſes of the Saints will be inlarged, and their rejoyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings alſo in ſuch fulfillings, of ſuch promiſed Mercies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. For his propheſie when af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor the ſin of that curſed <hi>Cham,</hi> occaſioned by the hainous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of his Father <hi>Noah,</hi> (for the beſt Saints have need of their Saviour) yet when he through grace was awakened, by Repentance from his drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, God manifeſts his grace by him, in a like wonderful man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; not only to <hi>Shem</hi> at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, entitling him to himſelf to be the Lord his God: But alſo foreſhews his purpoſed mercy to come to the Gentiles, the poſterity of <hi>Japhet,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly his word gives wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to a twofold call which they were after to have to dwell in the Tents of <hi>Shem,</hi> as <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.27. the firſt was foretold by <hi>Hoſ. ch.</hi> 1.10.23. and applied by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 9.25, 26. upon the rejection of the <hi>Jews</hi> after Chriſts firſt coming, <hi>Acts.</hi> 13. which was the riches of the Gentiles, ſaith the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>ch.</hi> 11. which time of grace continues to the Gentiles, to Chriſts 2<hi>d</hi> coming; when upon the great Reſtauration of the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> the Gentiles will have their 2<hi>d</hi> call, when their great fulneſs will come in, which was foretold alſo by <hi>Moſes</hi> in his excellent ſong for peſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.43. <hi>Rejoyce ye Gentiles with his people:</hi> applyed alſo by the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. when Chriſt being the Miniſter of Circumſion, as he there ſtiles him, <hi>v.</hi> 8. for the truth of God to confirm the Promiſes made unto the fore, fathers (as he there plainly tells us with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Propheſies there, which ſhall alſo be thenfulfilled in the ſaid 1000 years: And will not the Saints then be greatly affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſeeing the accompliſhment of ſuch a mercy, and greatly praiſe God for it when his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious grace will ſhine out ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly to them therein, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="millenium">
                     <head>In the third Millen or <hi>1000</hi> Years.</head>
                     <p>WHen <hi>Lot</hi> about the year of the world 2440. had up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on worldly allurements choſen <hi>Sodom,</hi> and after thereupon was captivated by his Enemies, but delivered by faithful. <hi>Abraham,</hi> God ſent <hi>Melchiſcdeck</hi> to bleſs him who had the Promiſes, as a Type of Chriſts prevailing, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Prieſthoed to be of his order: to whom he then paid Tythes of all, as the payment of all due honor will be rendred unto Chriſt by all his Saints in the ſaid 100 years, and by all Creatures alſo, <hi>Rev</hi> 5. but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by all thoſe, whoſe great
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102108:7"/>High Prieſt he ſhall then appear to be (and probably will by a preſential interceſſion appear to be then) for ſuch as ſhall be in the natural life, <hi>viz.</hi> a Prieſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Throne, as <hi>Zach.</hi> 6.13. and alſo the raiſed Saints ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty then and for ever: And as this <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> Prieſt of the moſt high God was alſo King of <hi>Salem;</hi> ſo alſo Chriſt will then be the great King of the <hi>New Jeruſalem, Mat.</hi> 5.35. all the ſaid 1000 years: And as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was bleſſed by <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> after the ſlaughter of thoſe Kings; ſo <hi>Abraham</hi> and his faithful Seed will appear really bleſſed, when Chriſt maketh his own and their Enemies his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool; ſo the Saints will then find the mercies derived to them from many currents of long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyances, and ſtill more matter to them of praiſe and rejoycing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When <hi>Abraham</hi> that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, as by <hi>Eſay</hi> he is called, was ſent on his foot by Gods Divine Call, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. about the year of the World 2460. God was gracioufly pleaſed to make free Promiſes and Covenants, ſeven diſtinct times to and with <hi>Abrahans</hi> (as they are particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly ſet down in our <hi>Key</hi>) and after him to <hi>Iſaack</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> ſucceſſively, to give the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> perſonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to themſelves: which Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe the Apoſtle declares, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. they ſaw a far off by Faith, and died, not having received the ſame; wherefore as he alſo ſhewed they did not in their lives ſeek to poſſeſs it, but as men expecting to have the ſaid Promiſe of God made good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to themſelves at the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the juſt, they bought bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying places there to have their bodies interred (as alſo <hi>Joſephs</hi> bones after were) untill they ſhould all riſe again then to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs it in the renewed ſtate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: for they looked for an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly countrey, ſuch as then that ſtate will be, excellently fitted then by God for that their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. At firſt alſo the ſaid Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe was made to all <hi>Abrahams</hi> Seed, natural and ſpiritual, through that one Divine feed Chriſt (as the Apoſtle teacheth) to ſpring in time from <hi>Abrahams</hi> Loins according to the fleſh, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.16. by whom alſo all the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſeed by faith ſhould obtain their lot in that bleſſed ſtate by Promiſe, <hi>v.</hi> 29. concerning which two ſorts, the Scripture ſets forth many differences. The natural Seed was to inherit the Promiſed Land after <hi>Abrahams, Iſaacks,</hi> and <hi>Jacobs</hi> death, 430 years after the Promiſe was firſt made: but the ſpiritual will be joint heirs not only with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> but alſo with Chriſt in the ſaid renewed ſtate, when he ſhall ſit upon his own Throne as the Son of <hi>David.</hi> The former
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102108:7"/>were to be in Bondage long after the Promiſe, the ſpiritual are made free indeed by Chriſt the Son of God ſo ſoon as they are made the Sons of God by Adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Grace, beſides what will after appear they ſhall be when Chriſt ſhall appear, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.2. The former were compared to the duſt of the earth for mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, <hi>Gen.</hi> 13.16. but the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Seed was compared to the Stars of Heaven, not only for multitude, but excellency, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.5. explained by the Apoſtle, <hi>Pom.</hi> 4.17, 18. and <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. the whole Chapter. The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Seed entered into a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God in their own ſtrength and brake it; but as for the other God makes a new Covenant with them, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes the keeping thereof by them, that they ſhall not depart from him. The natural were delivered from an outward bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, which they were many ways liable to fall under again; the other are not liable to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaved again by their ſpiritual e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: the natural for their provocations, wandered in a worldly Wilderneſs long before they obtained the promiſed land: The other are in a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Wilderneſs, amongſt ſuch ſinners by whom they are perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted for well doing: The natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral had miraculous proviſion made for their bodies, yet through unbelief, that Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion came ſhort, and they died in the Wilderneſs; but the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual are fed by the Sackcloth witneſſes, who are appointed to feed the womans Seed in her wilderneſs condition: the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral were brought into the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> long after <hi>Abraham,</hi> by <hi>Joſhua</hi> the Son of <hi>Nun:</hi> The ſpiritual will be brought into its ſaid renewed ſtate by the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>type of <hi>Joſhua</hi> the true Jeſus and their great Meſſiah at his ſecond coming. The natural ſeed had a reſt that was afterward pollut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by their ſin, and therefore God foretold them that reſt ſhould caſt them out with a ſore deſtruction, <hi>Mich.</hi> 2.10. (as after it did) but the ſpiritual ſhall be brought into that reſt that remains for the people of God, <hi>viz.</hi> the Sabbatiſm of the worlds continuance when Chriſts reſt there will be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous all the ſaid time, and when God will ſet to his hand the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time to recover his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with many illuſtrations there and elſe where declared: for the natural a <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> and Pemple were built by men for typical worſhip: the ſpiritual ſhall have a <hi>New Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> whoſe maker and builder is God, where the Lamb will be the Temple of it: for the ſin of the natural ſeed the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens entered and defiled the typical Temple, but no <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite</hi> ſhall come into the New, or
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102108:8"/>any unclean thing enter into it: And though the laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> will wickedly, when Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan is looſed at the end of the 1000 years, attempt to beſiedge both the Holy City and the Camp of the Saints, yet they ſhall be deſtroyed by fire from God out of Heaven in that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt which will bring on the utter deſtruction of them all By theſe and the like differences may be diſcerned that what the natural Seed obtained, were but dark ſhadows of thoſe excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies which the ſpiritual Seed by Faith ſhall inherit in that world to come, as the Children of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham;</hi> for as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ye are all heirs according to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29. <hi>viz.</hi> of the land of <hi>Canaan</hi> renewed, or in the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate to come in the world, which will be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in eternal bleſſedneſs in Heaven: And therefore God made it his memorial through all generations, that he was the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaack</hi> and <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> in giving them perſonally that promiſed land in the ſaid renewed ſtate thereof, and to all their ſpiritual ſeed circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and uncircumciſed, to inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit then the ſame, together with them, which Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> manifeſts to be the ſcope of our Saviours Argument againſt the <hi>Saduces, Mat.</hi> 22.32. <hi>viz,</hi> that ſince he was the God of the living; they ſhall live again to inherit that promiſed land; and I doubt not but that theſe Divine Myſteries will then be found real verities; and how will the hearts of all thoſe Saints (then) be inlarged from the ſaid Covenants and Promiſes accompliſhed to them, with praiſes and rejoycings up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that account alſo, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Here alſo may be added <hi>Baa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lams</hi> Parable put into his mouth by God when be was hired by <hi>Balack</hi> King of <hi>Moah</hi> to Curſe <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> by turning his intended Curs into an eminent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telling of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>, of which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> but a ſhadow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> away (as was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>mb.</hi> 24.7, 8, 9. and <hi>v.</hi> 17. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the Star out of <hi>Jacoh</hi> and Scepter out of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that ſhall ſmite the corners of <hi>Moab,</hi> and deſtroy all the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Seth, v.</hi> 18, 19. and out of <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhall come he that ſhall have the Dominion, and <hi>v.</hi> 24. ſhe ſhews that the Ships of <hi>Chit, tim</hi> (the <hi>Roman</hi> Navy, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.40, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) ſhould afflict <hi>Aſhur</hi> and <hi>Eber,</hi> being the <hi>Jews</hi> laſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor, ſhould periſh for ever, or go into perdition, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. which will be fulfilled at Chriſts appearance in deſtroying that man of Sin, when that evil Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion ſhall ceaſe in the world. Much more might be here add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of Chriſts unwalling the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Seth</hi> as a prevailing King, when he ſhall be the Prince of the Kings of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102108:8"/>Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. and be that Star out of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and have the Dominion, <hi>v.</hi> 17.19. which will be eminently verified in his ſaid 1000 years Reign with his Saints, with other matters a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing to the Judgement of <hi>Jewiſh Rabbies,</hi> and pious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians reſpecting the ſame; but I ſtudy brevity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This may ſuffice: Now can we think that when the living and raiſed Saints; ſhall in the ſaid ſtate ſee theſe things fulfilled, from ſuch complicated evidences happily derived unto them, that they will not make ſuitable returns to God, for ſuch in-comes of his ancient declared goodneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Moſes</hi> alſo appears in his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of <hi>Judah, Deut.</hi> 33.7. to be directed by the Spirit of God, cheifly to reſpect Chriſt at that time, when God will bring him to his People to convert them, about his great appearance ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching, and that his hands ſhall be ſufficient for him, then to be the Lord, mighty in Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24. with many other expreſſions elſewhere; and that God would be an help to him againſt his Enemies, as <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.7. though ſome gradually applications hereof have in ſome ſort been not unfitly made yet the cheif appearance accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the tenour of Scripture, to be when he ſhall eminently make his Foes his Footſtool, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.1, <hi>v.</hi> 5, 6, 7. ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Potentates of the Earth, then found to oppoſe him, and eſpecially that head over diverſe Countries for the Original <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> is ſingular, not heads, but head, fitly expounded to be the Pope, who aſſumes himſelf an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal headſhip over divers Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries: So that hence it may be more and more manifeſt, that all ſuch ancient predictions till <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> Kingdom, and his ſure mercies, in reference to Chriſts ſaid Kingdom; all not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to that time and State, but then ſhall have their cheif ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fillings, when Chriſt ſhall then come to raign his and their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and reward his faithful Servants, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.9. and 22.12.</p>
                     <p>Come we now to conſider that which appears to be the laſt, anciently revealed or contented mercy of this nature, wherein all Saints then ſhall be interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and cheifly bears the Title of the Kingdom of Chriſt: For in the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they ſhall be interceſſed, as the faithful Spiritual Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but in their Reign with Chriſt, as the meek and upright ſpiritual Children of <hi>David, whoſe Soul was as a weaned Child,</hi> Pſal. 131. <hi>And ſuch then ſhall inherit the Earth, and delight themſelves in the abundance of Peace,</hi> Pſal. 37.11. which yet they have not obtained, but ſhall ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102108:9"/>
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 5.5. having in that State that Portion and Lot, in this ſure mercies of <hi>David, Iſa.</hi> 55.3.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="millenium">
                     <head>In the fourth Millen or <hi>1000</hi> Years.</head>
                     <p>TOwards the end of the third, and the beginning of the fourth Millen: We may place what concerns both <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> whoſe Buildings of the Temple is reckoned by <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> to be about the 3000th. year of the world, and about the middle of the time of the firſt 6000 years, (though (hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) the little ſpace of Satans looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, after the ſeventh Millen, may be allowed to make up ſome part of the ſixth before it,) yet there are ſome differences, by ſeveral learned Perſons diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered in Chronology, both under the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And therefore Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical Conjectures, ought to be in ſome probable Latitude, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Come we then in the next place to <hi>Davids</hi> Kingdom, not as it was given him as the Son of <hi>Jeſſe;</hi> ſpecially appointed thereunto by Gods peculiar de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignment, to be Anointed by <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel:</hi> But as by a new divine Character, it was by <hi>Nathans</hi> Meſſage confirmed for ever, through his one divine ſeed Chriſt, 2 <hi>Samuel</hi> 7.8, 9. to 17. and accordingly by <hi>Davids</hi> Faith, Thankfulneſs and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, afterwards improved from <hi>v.</hi> 16. to the end of the Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: (which we largely conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in our ſeventh Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Faith) which great and moſt excellent confirmation was, after <hi>Davids</hi> grievous fall in the matter of <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> and his Repentance, and his many Scourges ſuffered upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, for a long time; (for the freeneſs and ſeaſonableneſs of ſuch, Gods promiſed mercy to <hi>David,</hi> ought to be well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by us) as in all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſaid Examples, given from time to time) for the glory of Gods divine Wiſdom, Mercy, Truth and Faithfulneſs, to be then manifeſt throughout all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and Generations of the world until the Saints; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in thoſe times, when they ſhall ſee and enjoy all their greateſt accompliſhments, both praiſing Gods holy name for the ſame, and exceedingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing in them, in their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral conditions, of both ſuch ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and newly raiſed Saints: Therefore by <hi>Nathans</hi> ſaid Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to <hi>David,</hi> God took occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon <hi>Davids</hi> good puopoſe, to build God an houſe (when <hi>David</hi> injoyed peace after his former troubles, which God well accepted of as to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102108:9"/>intended, but yet for ſome Reaſons he aſſigned that work over to <hi>Solomon</hi> his Son; yet (I ſay) took occaſion thereupon to make to <hi>David</hi> the largeſt Charter, and to give the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt aſſurance of <hi>Davids</hi> ſure mercies, in reſpect of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral States of his Kingdom for ever; that was ever given to any mortal man, in many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects there obſervable, (as we ſhewed) the one was conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal for his immediate natural Seed, his Son <hi>Solomon</hi> (if he ſtood upright) who was to build that ſame glorious Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which after he did being therein a Type of Chriſt; yet afterwards did by his griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fall, alſo cut off that long intayl of his Kingdom (other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) to his natural race, which was ſoon after divided by the loſs of ten Tribes, in his Son <hi>Rehoboams</hi> time; being then engaged in Idolatry upon poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick accounts, the Cauſe of the miſery and ſpeedy captivity, which afterward was in both parts, by the ſucceeding provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of others, taken away from <hi>Iſrael</hi> firſt, and after from <hi>Judah</hi> alſo. But the ſecond was abſolute to <hi>Davids</hi> divine ſpiritual Seed Chriſt the Son of God, that was to become man, in an extraordinary way and moſt wonderful manner, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing born of that bleſſed Virgin, that was to come of <hi>Davids</hi> Race, who as the Angel told her at his birth, <hi>ſhould ſit on the Throne of his Father</hi> David, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.32. as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> had foretold, that there ſhould be no end of the encreaſe of his Government, and Peace upon the Throne of <hi>David</hi> and upon his Kingdom, to order it and to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh it, with Judgement and with Juſtice for ever; (as he had promiſed in the ſaid Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage by the Prophet <hi>Nathan</hi>) to the end of the World, or as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.29. <hi>That his ſaid Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Seed ſhall continue for ever, and his Throne as the days of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and that in the greateſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent over Sea and Land, with the higheſt Exaltation many ways illuſtrated, as for Gods firſt born higher then the Kings of the Earth, <hi>ver.</hi> 25, 27, &amp;c. and to be then the Prince of the Kings of the Earth, as he is ſtyled <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. And though for the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive great provocations of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo of <hi>Davids</hi> natural Seed, and eſpecially of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſeh</hi> and <hi>Zedekiah,</hi> from whom that Crown was then laſt taken away with a manifold Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods heavy diſpleaſure againſt him, the laſt of <hi>Davids</hi> ſaid natural Seed, as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane wicked Prince of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> ſaying by <hi>Ezekiel ch.</hi> 21. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the Diadem, take away the Crown, this ſhall not be, and I will overturn, overturn, overturn till hethat is Chriſt the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102108:10"/>ſpiritual Seed of <hi>David</hi>) come. Whereupon was that long inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim, or interruption of <hi>Davids</hi> Kingdom, in the four Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies following, revealed to <hi>Daniel</hi> twice, <hi>ch.</hi> 2. and <hi>ch.</hi> 7. (during the Gentiles Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all that time (probably) for the ſpace of 2300 years. <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.26. for which obſerve the Reaſons in our ſummary of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel;</hi> yet God did alſo there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare himſelf (even when the Tabernacle of <hi>David</hi> was fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) mindful of <hi>Davids</hi> ſure mercies, in and by his ſaid bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Seed [Chriſt] to come, (when all the ſaid four mettle Kingdomes, at once ſhall paſs away, as the chaffe of the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer threſhing floor, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.35.) ſaying, further by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ezekiel;</hi> (with whom all other Prophets, ſome wayes concur in the ſame matter,) when he whoſe right it is ſhall come, namely Chriſt, that he would give it him; who is now gone to Heaven to receive it, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. and when the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> long interim, of the ſaid four Monarchies is paſſed (of which now but little remains) he will return, and the fallen Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of <hi>David,</hi> ſhall in him be raiſed up again, as the Prophet <hi>James</hi> applyed, the Propheſie of <hi>Amos, ch.</hi> 9.11. at that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Counſel at <hi>Jeruſalem, Acts</hi> 15. with reference to the Gentiles great fulneſs under Chriſts ſaid Kingdom, then to come in alſo: By whoſe firſt coming to take mans nature in a Tabernacle of our Fleſh, for at that time, God according to his prediction, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.28. ſet up the ſpiritual Kingdom of the Stone, cut out of the Mountain without hands in the firſt State of it, in the time and height of the Roman Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being one and the laſt of the ſaid four Gentil Kingdoms, which by <hi>Daniel</hi> and Chriſts one Revelation, was thence to continue above ſixteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years; wherein Gods ſaid, ſpiritually powerful and prevailing Kingdom of the Stone; ſhould Divinely (in the ſaid time of the Dragon and Beaſt, after to come and continue, to act their parts ſo long) proceed powerfully by degrees, to bring on the ruine of that ſaid laſt, of the four Monarchies, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Romane</hi> and therewith all the broken parts of the three former which ſhall be certainly performed at Chriſts appearance and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declares. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.</p>
                     <p>And then all Satans <hi>Babiloniſn</hi> deſigns in all his three <hi>Babets</hi> will come to utter confuſion, <hi>viz.</hi> the confuſion of tongues and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions in the firſt, will then be diſſolved by oneneſs of language and unity: Tyranny and Cruelty, by Meekneſs and Peacefulneſs:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102108:10"/>and the great Myſtery <hi>Babylon</hi> fully be diſcovered, defeated, diſſolved when the Myſtery of God ſhall be finiſhed; which we largly conſidered <hi>chap.</hi> 5. of our <hi>Irenicon</hi> of the ſaid three <hi>Babels:</hi> The foundation of all which was laid by <hi>Nimrod</hi> in <hi>Aſſyria;</hi> which Title of the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> ſeems upon that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to be given to the <hi>Turk</hi> at his ruine, <hi>Mich.</hi> 5.5. This man [Chriſt] ſhall be our peace when the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> ſhall come into our land, and <hi>v.</hi> 6. Thus ſhall he deliver us from the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyrian,</hi> &amp;c. To which purpoſe</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="millenium">
                     <head>In the fifth Millen or <hi>1000</hi> years</head>
                     <p>GOd the Father in a glorious Viſion of the ſubſtance of Revelation Propheſie both for the order and end thereof, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. gives the book to the Lamb that had been ſlain and was alive again, to open the contents thereof under the ſeven Seals to that coming of Chriſt, and makes him alſo his Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (as we noted) impowering him alſo to execute the ſame, as being that Lamb that hath ſeven horns, and ſeven eyes, that is, hath perfect power, and perfect wiſdom, fully, by degrees in due order, to accompliſh the ſame, according to the double Scheme of Propheſie contained in the Book of <hi>Revelation.</hi> Firſt in the Seal-propheſie, for the ruine of the Civil State, which under the firſt five Seals, after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected the offers of Chriſt, and bloodily perſecuted his Saints in the time of the ten great Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, with others, by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans prevailing power amongſt them: who under the ſixth Seal, as a great Red Dragon, was by <hi>Conſtantine the Great,</hi> after 320 years caſt down from his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of Paganiſm-worſhip to the earth: ſince which time he hath ſought upon a new deſign to pervert Chriſtian Religion, and the Worſhip of the true God: Firſt by Errours and Hereſies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Father, Son, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, above an hundred years following: and after that to Paganize Chriſtian Religion it ſelf, by his new deſign then of two Beaſts, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. giving thereunto his great power and authority to contrive and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote a new Paganiſm, or Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, under a ſpecious Viſour of ſeeming and pretended Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; of which in the little Book <hi>ch.</hi> 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſeventh Seal proceed the ſeven Trumpets, ſounding out the wrath of God by degrees of Judgments againſt the Civil State of <hi>Rome;</hi> by the four firſt milder Trumpets to deſtroy it in the Weſt; in Empire, City, and Senate: And after in the Eaſt by the firſt Woe Trumpet
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102108:11"/>the <hi>Saracens</hi> to take away one half thereof, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.1. from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>An</hi> 600. and forward, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that King of the South, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.40. that in the time of the Holy Wars, ſo called, ſeemed to puſh at the <hi>Roman</hi> Armies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="millenium">
                     <head>And in the ſixth Millen or <hi>1000.</hi> years.</head>
                     <p>CHriſt hath ſince according to the Fathers ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion by that ſecond Woe Trumpet of the <hi>Turk.</hi> [who is therefore Chriſts Servant] as <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzar</hi> was ſaid to be Gods] from about <hi>An.</hi> 1300. hath taken away by his over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowings with his multitudes, the other part of the Eaſtern Empire, being that King of the North, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.40. deſcribed alſo in his actings, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.11, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who is to continue his day, and hour, and month, and year, to deſtroy the third part of men in the ſame 396 years of his Date, till that Empire ceaſe to be, <hi>v.</hi> 45. probably about <hi>An.</hi> 1700. with which the Beaſt was in great part to contemporate, with the Churches time, times, and half, in her wilderneſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and alſo the two ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth Witneſſes to feed the Church, and conſume the Beaſt by their Propheſie 1260 years, as by the breath of Chriſts mouth, till he at the end of the Beaſts 42 months (all being of the ſame time) ſhall deſtroy the Beaſt and the falſe Prophet at the appearance of his ſaid com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Kingdom, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.</p>
                     <p>To which purpoſe upon the <hi>Jews</hi> Captivity, and ſad fall of <hi>Davids</hi> ſaid Tabernacle, God did in that time by his contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary myſtical Prophets, <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> reveale the time of <hi>Iſraels</hi> Reſtauration, more darkly by <hi>Ezekiel, ch.</hi> 37. alſo ſhewing <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> muſt be removed, <hi>ch.</hi> 38, &amp; 39. before the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> ſhould be ſet up, called <hi>Jehova Shamma, ch.</hi> 40. to the end of the Book. But then to <hi>Daniel</hi> God was pleaſed more fully and clearly to ſet forth the [interim] or time of the four Monarchies. 1. Of <hi>Babylon.</hi> 2. <hi>Medo-Perſian.</hi> 3. <hi>Greece.</hi> 4. <hi>Rome,</hi> which were to paſs in the ſaid 2300. years before <hi>Davids</hi> Tabernacle ſhould be raiſed up again in Chriſt. But that the Kingdom of the Stone ſhould firſt be ſet up, as God foreſhewed, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.28. which was done above 1600 years paſt, in the time and height of the laſt, or <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, utterly (as was ſaid) to beat to duſt the ſaid four Mettle Kingdoms. And God ſhewed the ſame to <hi>Daniel</hi> in Viſion of the four Beaſts deſtroying each other, until the laſt ſhould be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102108:11"/>deſtroyed by Chriſt at his firſt act of Judgment againſt the Beaſt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.11. Whereupon he had the Viſion of Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Clouds of Heaven, when the Kingdom and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of all Nations ſhould be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to him, and that under the whole Heaven, <hi>v.</hi> 13, 14, 27. which will be <hi>Davids</hi> ſure mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies for his Kingdom and Throne to continue for ever upon that raiſing again of his Tabernacle fallen above 2000 years before, and will be alſo Chriſts <hi>Davidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Kingdom of his 1000 years Reign with his Saints, reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by himſelf, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by as was ſaid Gods wiſdom, power, mercy, truth and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, will gloriouſly ſhine out to all thoſe Saints in that reſpect (as in all the former before) both for his deſtroying the wicked then, as foretold, and ſo exalting his Saints to their great rejoycing and triumphant hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs in that excellent ſtate of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> and reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all things by Chriſt their great King, Saviour, and Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="millenium">
                     <head>In the ſeventh Millen or <hi>1000</hi> Years.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. SAtan is bound for 1000 years, but to be looſed again for a little ſeaſon when the 1000 years are ended, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.3.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Chriſt Reigns with his then raiſed Saints at the firſt bleſſed bodily Reſurrection the ſame 1000. years, <hi>v.</hi> 4, 5.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The ſaid raiſed Saints re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in the happy enjoyment of the Viſion of Chriſts glory, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. in his Kingdom given to him by God the Father in the <hi>New, Holy, Great,</hi> and <hi>Beloved Jeruſalem,</hi> enjoying then happy communion with Chriſt their head, and with one another in that ſtate, being ſo made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in one, as Chriſt prayed, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. and as his Spouſe or Bride one with himſelf, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.9. and with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels, all joyning with the inferiour Creatures in their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to praiſe God the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, for his great and glorious work of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and Redemption (as by that glimps of the end of <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> Propheſie <hi>ch.</hi> 4, 5. may be diſcerned) being all then in an undiſturbed, happy ſtate in their ſeveral degrees, whilſt Satan is bound and ſealed up in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs pit; that he may not tempt the nations any more till the 1000 years be ended, <hi>v.</hi> 3. all remaining in an happy peace, ſo long without being attempted againſt by any enemies.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Chriſts Servants, <hi>viz.</hi> the raiſed Saints, chiefly will then ſerve him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.3. as their buſineſs and happineſs ſo to do, <hi>ch.</hi> 7.15,</p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:102108:12"/>
                     <p n="5">5. Chriſt will be their light to them both, ſpiritual and viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and both glorious, in whoſe light, his Saints will then ſee light at the <hi>Revelation</hi> of all things, (probably) as to My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, Creatures and Providen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, when the myſtery of God is finiſhed, and the light of the Moon ſhall be as the light of the Sun, and the light of one day, as the light of ſeven days. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 30.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. The Nations of them that are then ſaved, will walk in the light of the ſaid great holy and beloved <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> come down from God out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, all the ſaid 1000 years, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Spirits of juſt men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore made perfect, to receive then from Chriſt their ſpiritual Bodies, alſo <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.24.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. <hi>The Kings of the Earth ſhall bring their Glory and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to it,</hi> in the ſame <hi>v.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="8">8. <hi>Alſo they ſhall bring the Glory and Honour of the Nations to it,</hi> v. 26.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. God will then dwell amongſt them, and all Tears ſhall be wiped from their Eyes, <hi>ch.</hi> 21.3, 4, <hi>&amp;</hi> 7, 16, 17.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. All the glorious Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the Paradiſe of God, of the Tree of Life, whoſe Leaves are for the healing of the Nations, and of the pure River, clear as Chryſtal, proceeding from the Throne of God, and of the Lamb, and all the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous excellencies aſſigned and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to it; which all thoſe happy raiſed Saints will then know by experience; how won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful, great and excellent they are in their Fruition thereof, the ſaid 1000 years.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. And though Satan when he is looſed will ſeduce his laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> to attempt to beſiedge the beloved City, and the Camp of the Saints; yet Chriſt hath afore hand reſolved them, that it ſhall onely be an attempt, and the Devil and all his Agents ſhall then be conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Fire from God, out of Heaven in the ſaid attempt, and the Fabrick of the world ſhall ſuddenly then be diſſolved, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſounding of the laſt Trumpet, and the general rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and change of all the Saints, to meet Chriſt in the Air, coming to ſit upon that great white Throne, at the laſt Judgement, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.11. <hi>From whoſe Face, the Earth and the Heaven ſhall fly away, and no place ſhall be found, for them,</hi> Rev. 20.11. And hath not Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf revealed all theſe things in an evident manner: That may ſuffice all Chriſtians, and ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal men of their reallity; and how then ſhould all ſound ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and conſciencious Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, from the conſideration of theſe things, now hinted to them, with many more that might from Gods word be ſet before them to ſuch purpoſe,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102108:12"/>be ſtirred up to love the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as the Apoſtle profeſſed for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, with that great encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to all others, to partake with him of a Crown of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. To long for his ſaid ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, when he cometh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin, having fully ſatisfied for that at his firſt coming; but then onely for ſalvation to his People, to deliver them from all their Enemies, and even the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Creatures with them; from the bondage of corruption, into the glorious liberty of the Sons of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.21. And to have their own bodies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from the Priſon, and the corruption of the Grave, and have powerful grace, as the Angels in Heaven in their condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and even thoſe alſo in the natural Life, ſhall ſerve Chriſt in Holineſs and Righteouſneſs before him, all the days of their life, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.74, 75.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. And that they may love his appearance, and long for it, let them labour continually to be fitted for it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and this rather, becauſe many wayes; the time thereof ſeemeth to be near approaching, not only in regard that moſt of the preceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Predictions are fulfilled, but alſo becauſe we find the computations of years; which the Holy Ghoſt ſeems to ſet down, of the <hi>Jews</hi> great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration, and of the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Churches Enemies, are ſhortly to be compleated, of which two in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and two in the Book of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> appear very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to that purpoſe; which we ſhall endeavour here to ſet down, as ſome of the Grounds and Reaſons of ſuch our Conjecture: From thoſe 4. Computations of the ſaid my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Numbers, formerly more fully explained in our Parallel of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the Book of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> and upon the ruine and deſolation of the <hi>Remane</hi> Monarchy as follows.</p>
                     <p>The firſt is from the 2300. days of years, in <hi>Daniel</hi> 8, 26. by <hi>Palmomi</hi> or the ſecret Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berer, ſeeming to refer to the end of the <hi>Jews</hi> Captivity refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the time of the end, <hi>v.</hi> 17. &amp; to the laſt end of the indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>viz.</hi> of God againſt that cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated People: The like to the ſame purpoſe is alſo obſervable, where <hi>Daniel</hi> declares the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Kingdom ſhall proſper till the ſame time, <hi>viz.</hi> until the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation ſhall be accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for (ſaith he) that that is determined, ſhall be done, <hi>Ch.</hi> 11.36. So again upon the ſame account; <hi>The Sacrifice and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation ſhall ceaſe, for the over ſpreading of Abominations, he ſhall make</hi> Jeruſalem [taken by <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>Veſpatian</hi>] <hi>deſolate, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven until the Conſummation, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102108:13"/>that determined, ſhall be powered out upon the deſolate,</hi> Dan. 9.27. See many other Reaſons upon <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.26. In our Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary of <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſions: This Computation of 2300 years, was from the deſtruction of the Temple by <hi>Nebuchadnezzers</hi> Army, then carrying the <hi>Jews</hi> captive to <hi>Babylon,</hi> to their great Reſtauration at Chriſts appearance, is by Scripture and Chronology thus computed: at <hi>Babylon</hi> 70. years under the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> about 80. years, till <hi>Daniels</hi> 70. weeks, when the Edict went out for building the City <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 3549; when is reckoned by their Kings Reigns, to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 80 years more, and <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> weeks, to the end of the half week; when Chriſt had finiſhed his Sacrifice of himſelf, for our ſins; which was in all 640 years more, and from thence to about that year, which we reckon will be 1700. will ſo be made up 2300. years.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, For the 2335. years, in <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. from the effectual taking away of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, in <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate Emperours time, when not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly many Heathen Idolatries, were encouraged by him, but he alſo in oppoſition to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, allowed the <hi>Jews</hi> out of the publick charge, to Rebuild their Temple for Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; whereupon Hiſtorians Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord that God by miraculous Tokens of his diſpleaſure, by Fire, Tempeſt, Earthquakes, <hi>&amp;c</hi> deſtroyed ſuch as were employed in the ſaid work, and not only burnt up the very Tools they wrought with: But caſt out the very Stones which they had laid for the Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof: Whereupon an Ancient obſerved that then Chriſts words were fulfilled, that one Stone ſhould not be left upon another, which ſhould not be caſt down, which times reckoned by Biſhop <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> to be <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 363. unto which if 1335. of <hi>Daniels</hi> ſaid account be added, it is near about 1700.</p>
                     <p>The two other Numbers in the <hi>Revelation</hi> are firſt the date of the man of ſin, his forty two moneths, or 1260 years, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to begin before 420. when the ten Kings were up at one hour with the Beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.12. to which ſaid 420 years or leſs; if there be added the 20 or 30 years to come, being the remainder of the 6th Vial, they will all together amount to about 1700 at the time of Anti-Chriſts deſtruction.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, As to the <hi>Turks</hi> day and hour, and moneth, and year to deſtroy the third part of man, computed by Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> 396 years, who is the ſecond woe Trumpet, to deſtroy the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102108:13"/>
                        <hi>Roman</hi> Empire in the Eaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.11. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.40. which being added to 1300 or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more, when the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Family, according to Chronolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, obtained the power; it will with the other 396 make up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 1700. All which compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations though by Reaſon of ſome differences, in Chronolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy before Chriſts birth, and ſince (as Biſhop <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) we may not attempt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine day, or hour, or year; yet within a competent Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude; the Spirit of God ſeems in theſe particulars, to give juſt ground of conjecture, that men of the world may be admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed of its fleeting ſtate, to prepare for the great ſhakings and changes, that ſeem ſhortly to draw near therein: By theſe Computations and other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters obſerveable to ſuch pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, from the Book of God: Since the <hi>Jews</hi> Reſtauration is pointed out by the 2 former in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the deſtruction of the Enemies of Chriſt, and his Church in the 2 latter; which the Holy Scripture declares will be the work of Chriſt, at his ſaid great appearance now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching.</p>
                     <p>Whence alſo we made our Conjecture of the moſt literal ſenſe of the Number of the Beaſt, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 13. 666. [as <hi>Belſhazzers</hi> Kingdom was numbred when it ended at his death] though other obſervations of the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 1666. may alſo be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der able to other purpoſes) but if we reckon the appearance of Chriſt, and his Kingdom to be about 1700. according to the the four ſaid computations, at which ſaid appearance of his preſence, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8. The Apoſtle ſaith he will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the man of Sin, then reckon backward for the <hi>Epoc.</hi> of his Number of 1666. (for it is agreed by learned men, that the whole Number of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand is there underſtood to be added) and it will fall out ſo to begin about Chriſts Aſcention, from whence to his deſcending again, will ſo be made up 1666 years, <hi>viz.</hi> about the ſaid time conceived to be the Period, of the ſaid four computations; and from our Saviours birth, by the common account 1700, at the ſaid Beaſts deſtruction; and his Aſcenſion, when Chriſt led Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity captive, ſeems more ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to point out by the ſaid Number, his Viſible conqueſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the remaining Powers of the world that oppoſe him.</p>
                     <p>About which time, not only will probably appear the moſt eminent fulfillings, of Gods moſt antiently revealed mercies, in his powerful, effectual and eminent breaking of the <hi>Serpent [Satans]</hi> head, by taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way or deſtroying, ſuch his Churches Enemies, and tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102108:14"/>down Satan himſelf under the Saints Feet, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> foretold, ſhortly or ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Rom</hi> 16.20. in the order of accompliſhment. Firſt, By his binding, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.2. and after by caſting him (upon the ruine of his laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi>) into the Lake of Fire and Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone for ever, <hi>v.</hi> 18. And then Gods Wiſdom, Power, Mercy, Truth and Faithfulneſs, will gloriouſly appear towards both the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as the ſpiritual Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> by the deſtruction of the Enemies of them both: But more eſpecially then, in the raiſing up the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of <hi>David</hi> in Chriſt his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Seed, and in ſetting up of his ſaid Kingdom; who as we have ſhewed ſhall gloriouſly ſit upon <hi>Davids</hi> Throne, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to the end of the world, in a peaceful and bleſſed Eſtate: And if the word of God did not give Teſtimony, in all the ſaid particulars from the ſaid Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, promiſed Mercies and Covenants; it had been high preſumption ſo to have aſſerted them: But ſince as we have pointed out thus briefly, yet ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry evidently his word doth largly, fully and clearly hold them out; Let men henceforth upon due conſideration of theſe things, take heed of oppoſing and gainſaying theſe evident Truths, which he will ſhortly bring to paſs; and no power of Men or Devils ſhall in the in the leaſt hinder any of them; as Chriſt will manifeſt when the Myſtery of God is finiſhed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10. and it is to be hoped when many ſerious and unprejudiced and judicious Chriſtians, have ſought God by Prayer, and due ſearch of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; from theſe Foundations well pondered by them, that they may be herein ſatisfied, that ſuch a bleſſed reſt and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the preſence of the Lord. remaineth to the People of God; whereby ſuch perſons may evidently diſcern with me, that ſuch pretious Jewels of <hi>Revelation</hi> Myſteries, are high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be valued, and it is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of theſe things, which is the great Reaſon, why many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem them not as they ought: and that this moſt ſacred and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt; by his beloved Servant and Diſciple Saint <hi>John,</hi> (which is the Diamond in the golden Ring of Holy Writ) is not duly prized by them: and particularly in this reſpect, that it affords light and Luſtre to all parts of Holy Script. without which men are not like other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe rightly to diſcern the ſame; concerning the matters here ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to them, as we by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence find more and more, to the Glory and Praiſe of that true Light, who lightneth every man that comes into the World, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102108:14"/>to that proportion he is pleaſed, to diſpence the ſame, unto them.</p>
                     <p>And thus much of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative Preface and Compriſal, both of our ſaid former work and ſubſtance of the divine My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries contained therein, with what further diſcoveries God hath been graciouſly pleaſed to offer unto the preſent world, by the hand of ſo weak and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy an inſtrument by the help of the ſaid laſt Key, of moſt ancient propheſie, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.21, 22. (as before ſaid) &amp; to precede our intended Treatiſe on <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5. Of the firſt bodily Reſurrection of the Saints.</p>
                     <p>The cheif improvement we ſhall by Gods aſſiſtance, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour here to make of what hath been ſaid, briefly is, for infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Chriſtians of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great uſefulneſs, and manifold excellencies of all ſuch ancient, revealed and promiſed Mercies and Covenants, made to and with the ſaid fore Fathers and Saints, that have their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and moſt eminent fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, from the guidance of this ſaid divine Key, and other parts of Gods word; yet remaining to be gloriouſly accompliſhed by Chriſt himſelf, in the world to come, or 1000 years of his Reigh with his Saints; There is an Heavenly Treaſure of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs contained in them; for all ſuch Saints at the firſt bleſſed reſurrection to be given to them thereupon; ſo that if their ſaid Promiſes and Covenants, be not by men extended to that ſaid ſtate, they exceedingly narrow the Mercy and Grace of God therein, and as much as in them is, deprive all ſuch Saints of their right then in them: And this may further appear by touching a litle upon the diverſe uſefulneſs, and manifold excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies of the ſame.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, They are moſt ancient, for they are all virtually contained in that moſt antient one, <hi>Ge.</hi> 3.15. which was not in the beginning (as Chriſt, the word was) but in the beginning of mans need of ſuch Goſpel Grace, God ſpeedily revealed it, as the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary of all that followed and all the ſaid branches that ſprang out of that Root, are by the word of God manifeſt, to be of the ſame nature, having a tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and that cheifly to thoſe ſaid laſt times.</p>
                     <p>No ſooner had Satan at the fall marred Gods work of Creation, but upon the tryal of all the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, the moſt glorious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration proceeds from Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt of reſtoring loſt man, and the whole Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God in the Iſſue, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ways ſince by Gods word is evident, which by Chriſt and the holy Spirit are in all times ſince, carrying on to the end, a work that is every way won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102108:15"/>that the Son of God ſhould pay the Ranſome in mans Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by dying for ſin, who was perfectly Righteous, not to free man and the Creation from ruine onely, but to redeem both it and him to himſelf; yea to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore both into a better ſtate, to make him both ſurely and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly bleſſed, in a way and ſtate unconceivable and unutterable; for Chriſt the Womans Seed is not a Privative only, but a poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Saviour, nor a partial, but every way a perfect Saviour, and this ſhort comprehenſive Goſpel contains all in it by Chriſt, to be obtained for his Saints for ever: Away with falſe Oracles and Fictions of vain Heathens, of their anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, here is only true anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and the beſt antiquity to be found; and all the others iſſuing from this if <hi>a parte ante</hi> they be not ſo ancient, yet <hi>a parte poſt</hi> they ſhall be as laſting (as in their particulars we ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from Gods word) but yet without this divine Key, we had not known where to fix them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> conſider them particularly with reference thereunto, as we have given Scripture Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and as we ſhall, by Divine aſſiſtance, further manifeſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The ſubduing of the laſt great Enemies, the Saints injoying of the happineſs of Chriſts <hi>Davi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical</hi> Kingdom, and of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> State, have all their infallible Grounds from ſome or more, of the ſaid Foundations, as was particularly made to appear, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that they were all as well as the firſt, freely and graciouſly given, did appear by occaſions that God uſually took to make them known, upon ſome ſailing or tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of his Servants or both, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. They are all uniform, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering fitly one to another in all ſuch ways God was pleaſed to manifeſt his preſent or future Grace to all that were concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in them, or ſhould be, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. Moſt true as proceeding from the God of truth, Satan if he ſpeak truth, it is not truth from him, becauſe he purpoſeth thereby to deceive, but it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for truth it ſelf to lye or deceive.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. They are alſo moſt wiſe, tending directly to the beſt end, and that in the ſureſt and moſt prevalent powerful way and means, that cannot fail.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Moſt certain, as coming from the unchangable God, and therfore neither the beſt of men nor the meaneſt of Saints, are not conſumed, becauſe by ſuch ways of Grace ſaved by him that is unchangeable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">6. Moſt comfortable, becauſe they contain the conſolations of God, which are not ſmali; yea the greateſt for all ſaid intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that ſuch ſinners are capable of for good.</p>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:102108:15"/>
                     <p n="7">7. Theſe antient Entails of all the ſaid Saints are very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful and pleaſant, eſpecially being not only upon good, but upon the beſt Securities that can be. I conceive none, upon due conſideration, will be ſo bold as to ſay directly any of them is not the Word of God, nor that Chriſt by this Key hath not laid open the precious excellencies of them, if any wilfully turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their eyes or ears: upon them will that deficience re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main: the higher the points of Wiſdom, the Children of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom are exerciſed in, the more delight they ſhall find in them; the ſecret of the Lord is with ſuch as he will ſhew his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant unto; of which, theſe are a very great and excellent part: our Saviour gives his Key eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for that end as knowing their fitneſs for it. I can ſay much of the delight of them by experience, though men often ſlight them and me for them <hi>[At mihi plaudo Domi]</hi> upon a much better account than it was ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; the Teſtimony of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and true Witneſs Sealed by his Spirit anſwers all objections, their mention or meditation is cordial, in them is Chriſt and all his benefits, not only as he is ſet forth, as to his firſt coming to lay the foundation of all fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture good, as he became the Seed of the Woman, as ſet forth to the old world, and was of the Seed of Man, as of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaack, Jacob,</hi> &amp; <hi>David,</hi> in the new world for conſolation to mankind, but ſpecially made known of what Tribe namly of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> at what time to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t when the Scepter was departed from it, in what place at <hi>Bethelem,</hi> of what perſon, of a pure Virgin of the lineage of <hi>David,</hi> which with other things in his Birth, Life and Death he fulfilled: But if we improve the intent of theſe promiſed antient Mercies, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting his ſecond coming, and all concurrent Texts concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> the holy Scriptures in ſuch reſpects much more abound. It is true, the glorious Promiſes reſpecting all theſe at Chriſts ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, hath much miſled the <hi>Jews,</hi> over-looking the humility of the firſt: and it was well if ſome Chriſtians were not a farther ſtumbling-block to them in over looking the great Promiſes at Chriſts ſecond coming, and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what reſpects the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> Chriſt became a light to lighten the <hi>Gentiles</hi> upon the <hi>Jews</hi> rejecting of him at his firſt coming: but he will at his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond be the glory of his people <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be ſaved: the ſaid time is coming a pace that great will be the day of <hi>Jezreel,</hi> ſhe muſt lengthen her cords, and ſtrengthen her ſtakes: It is a ſnare of Satan to make men by dim-ſighted Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102108:16"/>to pore ſo much upon im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probabilities as to over look ſuch large ſecurity given by God to his antient people, who are and will appear ſhortly to be beloved for their Fathers ſakes, God will make them the wonder of his mercie, in a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful way and manner (as is very probable) it is ſad, mens prayers of late concur in that no more with Gods promiſes, which ſpiritual allegorizing will not anſwer in their true intent and literal meaning; yet the beſt and moſt excellent ſpiritual ſence is carried on as the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods antient peoples en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments his Covenant is when he takes away their ſin, and to them chiefly is promiſed to put his Law into their hearts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with many more of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wherein we <hi>Gentiles</hi> have ſome part; but it is but a ſmall part in compariſon of them to whom they chiefly belong. God will not fail them in one of his Promiſes, and they are many and great, and proper to them in the firſt place and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree; the Childrens hearts will effectually be turned to the Fathers, and generally too: though miſtakes and prejudices with the currents of times carry many a contrary way: but there is enough in Gods Promiſes to that purpoſe to anſwer all, let our faith be exerciſed in them, and our prayer will not then be wanting for them; a joyful and pleaſant thing it is to know ſuch a confluence of mercy to <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> is approaching when they ſhall both rejoyce to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.43. and that when Chriſts days will be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed in the world he ſhall ſo abundantly ſee his ſeed, and the will of the Lord ſhall proſper in his hand, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Theſe ſaid promiſed mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies ſo laid open to all his living or raiſed Saints, are of exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great and manifold uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for the preſent, and for fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture times, they are of a very comprehenſive nature, intenſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and extenſively if rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood and applyed: in or unto any times, places or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition for true Chriſtians; they are aboundant in bleſſings, as with <hi>Iſrael</hi> at his death, he had diſtinct bleſſings for all his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity: let but a believing ſoul conſider how much comfort it can draw out now by faith and prayer from them, upon Chriſts opening of them one by one as their virtue hath been derived to all Saints paſt, and may be to all now, and as certainly will be to all Saints hereafter: for they contain, upon that account, flowing ſtreams of mercy, if by our Veſſels of Faith, and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of grace, we will through Chriſt go to thoſe waters of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, the Womans promiſed Seed is breaking the Serpents
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:102108:16"/>head continually, the Children of the Promiſe, circumciſed, and uncircumciſed, are travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Promiſed Land, and <hi>New Jeruſalem. Davids</hi> ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and faithful Race ſhall have of <hi>Davids</hi> ſure mercies in his Kingdom under, and with Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.3. There is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent comfort in them all by faith, as well as ſure bleſſedneſs here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after in fruition: but I muſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly point out theſe things at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> others may be added upon due meditation of theſe, and the like.</p>
                     <p>Many other improvements might here be made of theſe things: As,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. To convince of many Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and Miſapprehenſions of many men, but this hath been done by my ſelf in many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects already, and likewiſe by others as we have particularly ſhewed in our Treatiſe on <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. as <hi>pag.</hi> 19. of the <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Goſpel</hi> is to be ſeen.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. This ſhould admoniſh Chriſtians to manifeſt, as there is great reaſon to do, a ſober and pious acknowledgment of ſuch Divine Truth and Grace herein laid open for their great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage if duly pondered, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by them.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. To ſtir them up to thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs for any degrees of ſuch Divine Diſcoveries in theſe ſaid reſpects tendered to them, that ſuch a ſtate upon ſuch ſure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations is by the goodneſs of God, and the wonderful wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Jeſus Chriſt imparted to them, wherein all ſorts of his Saints then living or raiſed will be ſo much concerned, as alſo in our following Tract of the firſt bleſſed Reſurrection: we doubt not more fully to manifeſt to Chriſtians Conſciences by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Aſſiſtance.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. To diligent Study and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of the greatneſs of theſe mercies, and of every believing ſouls great concernment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. To excite them from all ſuch conſiderations of ſo great mercies ſhortly approaching in Chriſts ſaid Kingdom to be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained unto; to labour more and more to be fitted for the ſame by exerciſe of a true faith from Gods own aſſureance, and of all Godly obedience in the due exerciſe of every grace both towards God and Men: which is alſo in good part done at the concluſions of all our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Practical pieces on Subjects of like nature, as on <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.20. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.17. and is farther intended, if God permit, on that enſuing, on <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5. In doing of which, although we are reſtrained at preſent from much enlarging therein, yet when Foundations thereof are once well laid, as to Doctrinal Truths; the other may much be ſupplyed by Chriſtian Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:102108:17"/>Admonition and Confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon all fitting opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. To which good purpoſes, the ſaid unworthy Pen-man hereof, hereby declares his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs upon any ſuitable and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable occaſions, to be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto ſubſervient.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>W. S.</signed> 
                        <dateline>
                           <date>
                              <hi>October.</hi> 30. <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1673.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="errata">
                  <head>ERRATA.</head>
                  <p>Title page read <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. p. 4. r. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.7. p. 13. col. 2. r. <hi>Ruine</hi> not <hi>Reign.</hi> and 4 lines after r. <hi>Covenaneed</hi> not <hi>Contented.</hi> and 4 lines after that, r. <hi>Intereſſed</hi> not <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſed</hi> twice. p. 14. col. 1. r. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Uſher. l. 40 r. <hi>Charter</hi> not <hi>Character.</hi> in col. 2. l. 26. r. <hi>unto the Saints</hi> not <hi>until the Saines.</hi> p. 15. col. 1. r. <hi>their future.</hi> p. 18. col. 1. r. <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.11.</p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:102108:17"/>
                  <head>ΕΧΑΝΑΣΤΑΣΙΣ OR The Riſing out of the Maſs of Dead Bodies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>REV. 20.5.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>This is the Firſt Reſurrection.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>WE having by the good hand of God been di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to premiſe divers things preparative by way of Preface, tending to manifeſt the firſt bleſſed Reſurrection of the Juſt, or the Saints Bodily Reſurrection to be here, that which in this Text is by Chriſt Jeſus himſelf, entituled with this diſtinguiſhing Note from all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, namely, of the <hi>Firſt Reſurrection:</hi> that is, properly ſo called and ſo punctually and exactly decyphered here by him: which may theſe four ways following, by his Divine Aſſiſtance be made to appear to all ſerious unprejudiced and underſtanding Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. From the words of the Text, compared with other expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our Saviour in the Goſpel to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. From the Context, and occaſion of theſe words.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. From the Arguments and Reaſons agreeable to both the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. From other portions of Scripture ſpeaking to the ſame effect, both in Old and New Teſtament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>First,</hi> From the words of the Text <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, where the Particle <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> this is Demonſtrative: We may know what it means by putting the queſtion <hi>What is it?</hi> and it will be reſolved by what Chriſt was manifeſting by his Servant <hi>John</hi> for the uſe of his Church, by a ſpecial Revelation of Gods Divine way of graee concerning his ſecret Counſels and Purpoſes in their order to be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:102108:18"/>according to the book with ſeven Seals delivered to himſelf, that Lamb with ſeven horns, and ſeven eyes, denoting his perfect Power and Wiſdom, to fulfil the ſame, <hi>ch.</hi> 5. in their due order of accompliſhment for the time to come to the end of this book: namely, the things that ſhall be hereafter, for we ſpeak only here of the third head of <hi>Johns</hi> Writings, <hi>ch.</hi> 1.19. to wit, ſuch as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan above 1600 years paſt, and now appear to be almoſt fulfilled to a very little ſpace to the end of <hi>ch.</hi> 19. But the 20th <hi>ch.</hi> with the two following <hi>ch.</hi> are (as we have many ways ſufficiently proved) and doubt not, by the ſame Divine Aſſiſtance, farther to manifeſt, that they are the ſame Holy mans Writings of that moſt excellent part of the ſame Divine <hi>Revelation</hi> for the time to come reſpecting the happy eſtate of that world, that the Children of the Reſurrection, namely, of this firſt Reſurrection, ſhall be counted worthy to obtain, as our Saviour himſelf Divinely taught, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.35, 36. and in this Revelation he teacheth by his Servant <hi>John,</hi> what that World and Reſur. are, and in what order they ſhould have their being; and it is obſervable, that as there is in the Text a remarkable emphaſis in the <hi>Greek</hi> by the emphatical Article, there doubled, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that Reſurrection, even that firſt Reſurrection. So our Saviours expreſſions in <hi>Luke</hi> 20. of the ſame matter, are ſuitable to this Text, with its dependency: both of that World then to begin, called the World to come, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. and alſo of the ſame Reſurrection, and of the Saints themſelves, and of their being counted worthy of that World, ſetting them all four down; 1. By way of Doctrine, and then again makes the ſame thing known by Revelation to his Servant <hi>John</hi> in reſpect of the time and order of fulfilling in this <hi>ch.</hi> which he had before taught and made known by way of Doctrine while he lived on earth.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Saith he, the Children of that World, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> to this preſent world, where the Children of it are Married, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but not ſo in the other, where the Children of the Reſurrection ſhall be; which here alſo he teacheth ſhall be, when he deſtroys Antichriſt, the Beaſt and falſe Prophet, and binds the Devil for 1000 years, <hi>ch.</hi> 19, &amp; 20. that is that World which will then begin.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It is the ſame Reſurrection ſpoken of here emphatically (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven that) which our Saviour expreſſeth there by <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a Riſing from amongſt ſuch dead bodies as then ſhall be left behind, being the ſame the Apoſtle ſtrived to attain, which he calls <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.11. a Riſing out of the heap of the Dead (of which
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:102108:18"/>more afterwards) and ſpeaks of it as a peculiar thing belonging to ſuch as riſe out of ſuch heaps (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſaith the Apoſtle of ſuch Saints before dead) by the genitive poſſeſſive, as if the Holy Ghoſt would inform us further, it is the Reſurrection only of ſuch dead Perſons to whom an <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> properly belongs, <hi>viz.</hi> a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing out of the heaps of the dead left behind.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Of the Saints themſelves that are to Riſe then, they are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ways illuſtrated there by Chriſt, 1. by what they are reckoned or counted worthy of aforehand. 2. By what they are ſtiled by our Saviour in two expreſſions: For the former, the word is very remarkable, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, they are ſuch as are counted worthy of that World: the word is a decompound, denoting them to be counted worthy, as being Enrolled in antient Record for it, <hi>viz.</hi> in the Lambs Book of Life; and that they are conſequently to obtain that World as upon Record for it: the words ſeem very for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible in their decyphering of the Saints bleſſed eſtate then by them to be obtained; ſo here, bleſſed and holy are they that have part, <hi>&amp;c. v.</hi> 6. Again, our Saviour there gave them a twofold excellent ſtile, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the Children of Gods and the Children of the Reſurrection; ſo here they are the Spouſe the Lambs wife, being the Children of God, <hi>ch.</hi> 19. &amp; 21. and this bleſſed Reſurrection we ſpeak of, is proper only to the Saints, thoſe bleſſed Perſons then.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Chriſt ſets forth a twofold excellency of that eſtate of the Saints, they are immortal, they can die no more: ſo here, on ſuch the ſecond death ſhall have no power: yea <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> they are like the Angels of God in Heaven; not only privatively, that they need not outward worldly helps to ſuſtain them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or not liable to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, but as here, bleſſed and holy, as the Angels of God in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: and thus Chriſt by his ſpirit guided the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> to ſet forth a practical Comment in this Divine Revelation of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Heavenly Doctrine, <hi>Luke</hi> 20. ſo agreeable is all Divine Truth in what the Holy Spirit ſpeaks any way of the ſame thing.</p>
                  <p>To like purpoſe when our Saviour ſpeaks of this firſt Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in the Text, he expreſſeth it by theſe words, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.29. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, they ſhall come forth to the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of life; they ſhall come out from the reſt of the dead, they ſhall come into the Reſurrection of life, which is alſo called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the Reſurrection of the Juſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.14. that is, theirs, properly and peculiarly belonging to them, as before: they are the Synonomous Expreſſions of the Holy Ghoſt, ſo exact is all Divine
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:102108:19"/>Truth delivered by him, if we conſider it aright, as we ſee all theſe expreſſions ſuit admirably with the text in its expreſſions &amp; depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency. Now come we to the thing decyphered out by Chriſt; 1. It is called a Reſurrection. 2. The Firſt Reſurrection. 3. Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively and Emphatically ſet down by this Reſurrection: we have ſhewed it to be properly the bodily Reſurrection, which is only properly ſo called in Scripture: Regeneration (as ſome would have it) is improperly ſo taken; only by a Metaphor, neither is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, in that Text of <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.28. to be underſtood of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration; but as learned <hi>Beza</hi> notes in five Copies, it is diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed in the Original from the preceding words [you that have followed me] denoting that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, there was the <hi>New Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſis,</hi> or Chriſts making all things <hi>New</hi> then, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5. when he the Son of Man ſits upon his Throne, that the Diſciples that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him ſhall then ſit upon twelve Thrones, judging the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> or as it is remarkably explained, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.29, 30. ye are they that have continued with me in my tentations, I appoint unto you a Kingdom, as my Father hath appointed unto me <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet if it could have been proved to be meant of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, yet ſo it is a Reſurrection, only Metaphorical, not Proper, which is only bodily at that firſt, and alſo is peculiar to the Saints at that time only.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It is called the firſt Reſurrection in oppoſition to the other, to diſtinguiſh it from that following, for the reſt of the dead 1000 years after being both to be raiſed bodily in their due order and time, both properly ſo called, and to be actually performed by Chriſt in their appointed times to raiſe both ſorts: firſt the ſaid Saints bodies at the firſt, and the bodies of the reſt of the dead 1000 years after: <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as died in the ſaid 1000 years, and all the wicked at the laſt Trump.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Now for farther reſolution what the Demonſtrative Article <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> points out to us; that as we before noted in revealing the order of that matter to be fulfilled, he ſhews here that unto the ruin of the Beaſt and falſe Prophet ſucceeds the Riſing of ſuffering Saints; for Chriſt and his Word, in that New World, as he explains <hi>ch.</hi> 21, 5. when in that <hi>Jeruſalem State</hi> he makes all things New; they ſhall Riſe to Reign with Chriſt in his <hi>Davidical</hi> Kingdom, which hath long been Entailed upon him, as we ſhewed in our <hi>Systeme:</hi> and he went, upon his Aſcention, to Heaven to receive it; and at his Return ſhall poſſeſs it, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14. and wherein the ſaid Saints ſhall Reign with him the ſaid 1000 years: and this is exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:102108:19"/>ſet forth to be contemporary with Satans binding the ſaid 1000 years; and the times of both are ſo interwoven and linked toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make the ſaid Revelation of both more evident: and yet he Reveals farther, <hi>v.</hi> 3. that Satan muſt after the 1000 years be looſed again for a little Seaſon, who in the ſame order will be looſed, as <hi>v.</hi> 7, 8, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> Now in reference to the Saints, St. <hi>John</hi> ſaw Thrones, and they ſate upon them, for to them the Army of Heaven, <hi>ch.</hi> 19. in white, the relative expreſſion evidently relates; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the ſouls of them that were beheaded, which were twice de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in <hi>ch.</hi> 19.1. the As Bride or Wife of the Lamb, <hi>v.</hi> 7.2. As of the Armies in Heaven in white Linnen, white and clean, after ſet forth by the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> Inhabitants, metonimically, <hi>ch.</hi> 21.9. which are thoſe that ſate on the Thrones: the ſame Thrones in <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. which he ſaw ſet becauſe of the great words the Horne ſpake <hi>v.</hi> 11. which were pitched or ſet, as the <hi>Caldee</hi> word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſignifies, or lifted up, as <hi>Arias Montanus</hi> renders it, till the Beaſt was ſlain, and his body given to the burning flame, <hi>v.</hi> 9, 11. and for whom were the Thrones ſet, but for the Saints at the time Chriſt came in the Clouds of Heaven, and received his univerſal King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom over all Nations under the whole Heaven, often mentioned in the Goſpel; and <hi>v.</hi> 18. the Saints took the Kingdom then and poſſeſſed it: and again <hi>v.</hi> 22. Judgment, that is, <hi>Poteſtas judicandi,</hi> the power of Judging was given to the Saints: of the ſame our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour tells his Diſciples they ſhall ſit on Thrones judging the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> which is the ſame time and thing revealed in this place; but here two things farther are explained by our Saviour then were ſeen there by <hi>Dan.</hi> Firſt the ſuffering, but then raiſed Sts. ſhall then have the ſaid Kingdom &amp; power. 2. That they ſhall have it with Chriſt 1000 years: theſe are his farther Revelations here of theſe things; namely, upon the deſtruction of the Beaſt: the Saints that ſuffered under him are raiſed bodily, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and power of judging is given to them, and they reign with Chriſt in his Davi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical Kingdom 1000 years, and if our Syſteme of Promiſed Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies be conſidered well with its Scripture grounds, none of this will ſeem ſtrange, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And though ſome make a ſtir upon that the Souls were ſaid to live, we there ſhewed in Scripture, Ideom ſouls were put for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>Gen.</hi> 40.20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.10. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.19. beſides, how they were repreſented to the Holy Man in Viſion; as ſouls in taking their bodies is alſo conſiderable, for ſuch expreſſions at that time, a like deſcription he had <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.14. where they are ſaid to be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rayed
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:102108:20"/>in white Robes: ſo <hi>ch.</hi> 6.11. and farther ſaith Mr. <hi>Mede, Animae in ſacris literis non tantum perſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, ſed cadavera denotant:</hi> Souls in Scripture are not only put for Perſons, but for dead bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: So <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.21. Ye ſhall make no cuttings in your fleſh for the dead, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> the ſame word ordinarily ſignifies the ſoul, but fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here tranſlated for the dead: the like <hi>ch.</hi> 21.1. none of <hi>Aarons</hi> ſons muſt be defiled for the dead among his people the; word uſed for the ſoul, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> but here for a dead body.</p>
                  <p>But above all, we may from the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Souls, here take notice of the exact agreement of the expreſſions of the Holy Ghoſt here, and in <hi>ch.</hi> 6.9, 10. of the ſame perſons, firſt of thoſe that had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered before under the Dragon, called ſouls here, and others that were after to ſuffer under the Beaſt, there ſtiled, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, their fellow ſervants and Brethren: and here ſpeaking of them both as rewarded, the firſt he ſtiles ſouls, for they we ſeperated ſouls then, when there they were ſaid to cry to God under the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar [as being before ſacrificed] for Vengeance: where by the way, let us take notice how that ſuited to <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Propheſie, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.41. <hi>I will render Vengeance,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>v.</hi> 42. from the beginning, of Revenges upon the Enemie, <hi>viz.</hi> [Antichriſt] [here deſtroyed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11. to the end] who before hindred the joyful Union of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as in the very next words follows, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.43. and the beginning of revenges ſeems to be the doubling double un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Babylon</hi> her cup of wrath before, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.6. as alſo <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaw in his Viſion, <hi>ch.</hi> 7. and ſo ſuch antient Propheſie will be fulfilled, and the ſame cry of the Martyrs will blood be particularly anſwered from under the Altar, which are the ſame ſouls which <hi>John</hi> here ſaw in Viſion ſo rewarded as to live to reign with Chriſt the ſaid 1000 years, when the body of the Beaſt, as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaks, was given to the burning flame: and to theſe ſaid ſouls, the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatical expreſſions <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, thoſe ſouls of thoſe men (before) beheaded have particular reference; but then the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaks as diſtinctly of the other: by the cauſe of their ſuffering, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c. and thoſe that worſhipped not the Beaſt, nor his Image, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the maſculine gender being their fellow ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and Brethren afterwards then to be killed: and theſe alſo are here in the ſame manner rewarded, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19. <hi>Thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded thy Servants the Prophets, and thy Saints,</hi> &amp;c. and all ſhortly to be fulfilled at Chriſts appearance: And by theſe things we may again obſerve the ſpecial Divine Excellency, and exact ſuitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs both of the words and things contained in this ſacred book.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:102108:20"/>And now in this juncture of time, it is a thing very deſirable for many good reaſons, as much conducing to the honour of Chriſt, and the benefit of the Bride his Church, for which end this Love-letter was ſent by him almoſt 1600 years paſt, to prepare for that approaching Marriage, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. &amp; 21. I ſay therefore it is hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth very deſirable that more than ordinary endeavours ſhould be uſed in, and encouragement given to thoſe Studies by all real Friends of Chriſtian Religion, who may now expect much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn from Chriſt thereupon: And I confidently believe that every degree of obſtruction unjuſtly caſt in the way thereof (upon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſeeming good pretence) will by himſelf be reckoned, when he comes, as an acting for Antichriſt, and againſt himſelf, and by how much the greater degrees the worſe: and if young Students now begin early to apply their Studies thereunto, they may likely find by the aſſiſtance of the Spirit and Grace of Chriſt (I ſpeak from Experience) a better foundation laid for their future Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, than from many others formerly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now when he had thus decyphered the ſaid Saints, or Souls, by their ſuffering before, and their living and reigning then with Chriſt; he ſpeaks of the others dead that lived not again till the 1000 years were ended, both being ſo diſtinguiſhed the former ſuffered, and lived, and reigned with Chriſt, but the other had no part therein: but of the former only that had part in all theſe he ſpeaks in the words of my Text, <hi>This is the firſt Reſurrection, viz.</hi> bodily, ſo long, namely, 1000 years before the other dead ſhall riſe again bodily, which is alſo called the time of the dead to be judged with reward: and is the ſame time in that Parallel text, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19. and that thou haſt rewarded thy Servants the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and thy Saints, and all that fear thy name both ſmall and great, and all theſe at the ſame time when the laſt Vial was pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Aire of the Beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. when the Prince of the power of the aire is to be dejected from his Rule at the Beaſts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and he himſelf to be ſo ſecurely bound, and ſhut up, and ſealed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then the Saints roſe bodily and reigned with Chriſt: this is the time, order, cauſe and end of their riſing then 1000 years before the reſt of the dead; to whom only that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or riſing out of the heap of the dead doth properly belong: and alſo our Saviours <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> a riſing out of the ſtate of ſuch dead left behind, ſpeaks the ſame thing: that the Saints riſe 1000 years before the reſt of the dead, which is this firſt Reſurrection.</p>
                  <p>And that the ſaid time of 1000 years is not taken indefinitely
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:102108:21"/>but abſolutely for it ſelf, 1000 year is acknowledged by the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, even among ſuch as would underſtand them by way of Antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation in the moſt unfit times of Satans prevalency; as <hi>Paraus</hi> and others, which I doubt not but a clear laying down of the Truth will here ſufficiently reſolve: and ſuch men alſo grant, that that whole number of 1000 years is always uſed for it ſelf in Scripture, and not otherwiſe. But our bleſſed Saviour hath ſo exactly laid that down in this Revelation, ſo as he hath taken away all ground to pretend otherwiſe; both in laying down the ſaid 1000 years ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, and relatively in regard of Satans binding, and the Saints reigning, and in ſeveral reſpects what was before, what in the time, and what after the ſaid 1000 years: ſo that no Parallel paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in holy Scripture, or other Writings I believe can be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; and again ſo ofren repeated both abſolutely what that time was, namely <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> three times 1000 years, and as often rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, thoſe, thoſe, thoſe 1000 years, in reference both to Saints and Satan: and ſhall vain men preſume to pervert this ſence of Chriſt which he hath ſo faſtened upon them, yea I may ſay, Rivited into them all along, and ſo by all circumſtances, Divinely &amp; gloriouſly illuſtrated in this moſt excellent part of his Revelation more plainly and clearly laid down then all the reſt (as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> obſerves) wherein is contained the ſure table of the beſt times of his Church in the world, and her Sabbatiſm of reſt to come in it, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.9. and thus much from the firſt conſideration of the Text with its dependancy.</p>
                  <p>In the next place the Saints bodily Reſurrection will appear to be the ſaid firſt Reſurrection from diverſe conſiderable paſſages obſervable from the Context, of which we gave divers hints long a go in our Appendix after the <hi>Irenio.</hi> page 100, 101, 102.</p>
                  <p>And the firſt from the <hi>Antitheſis</hi> or oppoſing the living of theſe to the not living of the reſt of the dead till 1000 years after; ſo that look how theſe lived now, the other muſt not live again ſo, till that ſaid time take it both ways, the others live not bodily till then, therefore theſe live bodily now, the others ſhall not live ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually then therefore theſe live not ſpiritually now for they are oppoſed as the one living, the other not living again: <hi>oppoſita non ſunt poſſunt ſimul eſſe vera.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. In what reſpect the Saints were ſaid to be dead, being ſuch as were beheaded, in the ſame reſpect here they are ſaid to live, but they were dead only in reſpect of their bodies; therefore they lived here onely in reſpect of their Bodies: Again, their Souls
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:102108:21"/>were not at all dead ſince they ſuffered; therefore as to them, they are not ſaid to live at that time when Satan was bound.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They were to live, as ſhould be ſuitable to Chriſts being the firſt Fruits of the Saints Reſurrection, at his coming again; but he was ſo by his Bodily Reſurrection; therefore they, as the whole Vintage, riſe bodily at his ſaid coming, ſuitable to the firſt Fruits of the ſame kind, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.23. Above 1600 years after (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) and then (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) cometh the end which our Saviour hath revealed, ſhall be above 1000 years, after his ſaid ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Saints are then to live as will be ſuitable to Chriſts per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Reign, to behold his Glory, and to behold the Viſion of him, as the object of their Sence, (then) as <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. He wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led that they ſhould be with him, to behold his Glory, which the Father hath given him, which many ways appears by Scripture, muſt neceſſarily be then in his ſaid Kingdom, where they ſhall Reign with Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Chriſt alſo gave a <hi>preludium</hi> or foreſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing example, of the firſt Reſurrection of the Saints, at his own Reſurrection, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. by the Reſurrection of many dead, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks to that effect, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.14. That as God raiſed up the Lord, he would ſo raiſe them and preſent them together: But nothing of raiſing any wicked man till the laſt Trumpet.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> But is not this Reſurrection meant of Regeneration, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch are ſaid to be bleſſed, that have part in the firſt Reſurrect. <hi>&amp;c. Anſwer,</hi> Some perſons at the firſt view, are apt to conceit ſo of it, not conſidering the drift of our Saviour in this <hi>Revelation,</hi> nor the Order of it: Beſides all the incongruity of it, to what hath been ſaid already, and as for the bleſſedneſs here aſſigned to it, it much better proves this to be the ſaid bodily Reſurrection of the Saints, when they obtain together a greater and much more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent bleſſedneſs, then any regenerate Saints have in this life: all Tears are then wiped away from their Eyes for ever, and their grace perfected, and Souls and Bodies united in a bleſſed and holy State, <hi>v.</hi> 6. though not in ſuch outward glory (probably) as they ſhall have at the general rapture, yet will have then bleſſed ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Bodies, ſuitable to ſuch a middle State as Chriſts Body was in after he roſe again till he aſcended, and it may be very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous that as Chriſts body was in ſuch a ſtate wherein he appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and diſappeared to his Diſciples and others, before his was glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified; ſo all theſe Saints ſhould firſt riſe in ſuch a ſtate, to be the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:102108:22"/>more uſeful to living Saints (then) before the ſaid Rapture at the laſt Trump: Such alſo were the Saints Bodies, ſeen in the Holy City, <hi>Math.</hi> 27. And ſhould not there be a ſuitableneſs of the Members to their Head? and will not the Communion of ſuch as walk in the light of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> require the ſame? How did <hi>Moſes</hi>'s glympſe of glory trouble <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, till his Face was vailed: Gods wayes to his Saints will all appear to be full of Wiſdom as well as goodneſs: But this is a condition of a new living, after men were dead or beheaded, and then no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation is to be expected, that muſt be now in this Life or never: And it is alſo of ſuch as were regenerate before they died, elſe they would never have been Martyrs of Jeſus Chriſt: Again, if this living were Regeneration, then all regenerate men muſt be made ſuch in a ſhort compaſs of time, for all Saints till then that have died, ſhall then ſo live again; and if all regenerate men muſt live with Chriſt a 1000 years in Regeneration, what became of ſuch as died before Chriſt took our nature; or when ſince did all ſuch live with Chriſt 1000 years altogether in Regeneration. Again the purpoſe of this living was to be now revealed as a mercy not known before as to time, and many other things reſpecting the firſt ſaid Reſurrection, as we ſhall (God willing) ſhew in many things, but Regeneration was an ancient Doctrine well known, that onely concerned the living but not the dead, the abſurdity of ſuch a pretence is ſo palpable, it would be but ſuperfluous here to write more upon it, or for the Reader to ſpend time in reading o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver again our ſaid hints, or others like with further inlargements.</p>
                  <p>But alſo many Scriptures ſhew a neceſſity of the ſaid Saints ſo liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bodily then; for firſt, Chriſt promiſes to over-comers, that they ſhall rule over the Nations, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.26. Theſe over-comers by Faith are his ſuffering Saints that are dead; therefore they muſt riſe again, whilſt ſuch Nations are to be rul'd over: alſo, ſaith he, they ſhall ſit on his own Throne diſtinct from his Fathers, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. But Chriſt hath none ſuch yet, but he ſhall have at his return from his Fathers right hand, they ſhall therefore then ſit thereon, <hi>The meek like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſhall inherit the Earth, and delight themſelves in abundance of Peace,</hi> Pſal. 37.11. They never did ſo yet, but our Saviour ſaith they ſhall <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.5. therefore ſuch a time and ſtate, for ſuch, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains that they muſt live again, to enjoy theſe and many other like premiſes, in the time of Chriſts Mediatory Kingdom, for they cannot in any other ſtate hereafter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:102108:22"/>
                  <p>Many other particular promiſes reſpecting the ſaid ſtate might here be added: But I proceed to that great conſideration that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains many weighty Arguments and Reaſons in it, namely, that this part of the <hi>Revelation</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt is his own Key (as we have ſufficiently proved in our ſaid Preface) fitted by himſelf to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock that great Cabinet of pretious Jewels, concerning the reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed &amp; promiſed Mercies to the Fore-fathers; cheifly to be performed to themſelves and their ſpiritual Seed at this firſt Reſurrection pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to the Saints, at the beginning of 1000 years, when they ſhall behold all the glorious Grace of Chriſt, (cloſed up till then in a great meaſure, in the Womb of thoſe promiſes) which will then have their perfect birth, and ſpeedy growth; whereupon great <hi>Halelujahs</hi> will be founded out to God the Father, Son and Holy Spirit by themſelves, Angels, men, and all other Creatures then living in the world, in their capacity, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at the glorious reſtitution of all things, and they themſelves and all the reſt enjoy the good of them, together in the ſaid 1000 years: Without which ſtate, I may upon many good grounds aſſert the main parts of theſe great promiſes will never be performed, nor their cheif ends attaine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> want thereof, but God on the one part ſhould looſe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of his Juſtice, Holineſs and Truth deſigned to be then manifeſt, (as by his word appears) in regard of his ſaid predictions, againſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe greateſt laſt Sinners, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan himſelf, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And alſo of his Wiſdom, Mercy, Faithfulneſs and Truth then alſo declared, to be fulfilled towards the Saints, in and about the ſame 1000 years, as by conſidering thoſe particulars before laid down, will eaſily appear to ſuch as are not reſolved to ſhut the light that God hath given them, as men, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſame: For hath God in his word ſo abundantly reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch a time and ſtate, and is there an excellent and ſuitable Harmony in theſe <hi>Revelations,</hi> from the beginning to the end of his word, ſo revealed; and do the moſt antient Promiſes and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants, fitly &amp; ſpecially refer unto the ſaid ſtate and time, and that upon divers great accounts; and hath Chriſt particularly revealed how, in what ways his Saints ſhall be brought to receive the benefits therein, to be enjoyed and be fitted to perform the Service, which thereby they will be engaged unto, as well as to receive the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs therein reſerved for them; and ſhall not theſe things upon ſuch excellent advantages be carried on effectually? What ſhould hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? yea they do all ſtrongly concur to advance their great ends, Gods word gives witneſs as we have ſhewed to all theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:102108:23"/>and not one of them ſhall fail: But Chriſt with his raiſed Saints ſhall Reign the ſaid 1000 years, the bleſſed <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate ſhall be ſet up, all Promiſes and Covenants that have their particular and cheif reference to them, ſhall be in ſuch reſpect ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, Chriſt and his Saints ſhall have their juſt Rights appointed by God in that condition, whoſe good pleaſure it is to give his little little Flock that Kingdom; Truth hath ſaid it, and will not fail, the great God by his holy Spirit hath revealed them unto his Church, and our bleſſed Saviour hath at laſt ſet forth the time and place of their being in the World, in a very excellent and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous manner, which all the ſaid antient Promiſes and Covenants have their ſpecial and cheif reference very evidently unto; and what can be more done but to work upon mens minds and Spirits, due apprehenſions of theſe things, and of the nearneſs of their approach; with true Faith to believe theſe things as revealed in the Goſpel, as well as other parts thereof? That ſo God and Chriſt may have their due praiſe and glory in reſpect thereof, and his faithful Servants may have the happineſs belonging thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. Now as all rational men that are of a ſound mind, when they read the Story of the Creation of the World, how God had made the Fabrick of the World, and all Creatures firſt, will acknowledge there was great divine Wiſdom and Goodneſs, manifeſt in putting man into the poſſeſſion thereof, who was made capable to diſcern and partake thereof, and to diſplay the divine wiſdom and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God therein, whileſt he enjoyed the benefit of the ſame, which ſhould have been his Sabboths work, had he continued in that condition: So when men but of ingenious tempers ſhall come to underſtand that God promiſed ſince mans fall, not onely a deliverance from that ſad condition, by the promiſed Seed of the Woman, and ſhews by degrees how it ſhould be carried on and accompliſhed, and reveals from time to time, from that Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, particular mercies for the advantage and good of all men in the Old and New World; and theſe Mercies and Covenants have ſeveral reſpects to men, preſent and future as in a natural Life or Spiritual Eſtate, and by his holy Spirit inſtructs his Servants more and more rightly to know them, and the Son of God the wiſdom of the Father in a wonderful divinely Myſterious way, ſets them forth, ſo as the divine Excellency falls in with the bleſſed <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi> thereof: What can ingenious Spirits do leſs but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge as theſe manifeſtations of Gods divine grace and goodneſs in diſcloſing of them, and of his Faithfulneſs and Truth in their
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:102108:23"/>gradual actual fulfillings: But how then are beleiving Chriſtians, ingaged alſo by the word to beleive theſe, upon the aforeſaid di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Foundations; and eſpecially ſince they reſpect ſuch a ſtate as Chriſt hath ſet forth, is ſhortly approaching, and all faithful Souls and Perſons are therein greatly concerned; yea Angels, men and all Creatures are intereſſed therein, as holy Scripture therein de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, and how fitly will a Sabbatiſm of reſt, after Chriſts finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the great work of his Reſtitution of all things, and his mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all things new, ſucceed to be celebrated to his glory by his Saints in the World, who by being. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> God and man in one perſon, hath ſo reſtored all, and being the Son of <hi>David</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording the Fleſh, ſhall have the ſure mercies of God, long ſince promiſed to <hi>David,</hi> by the enjoyment of his ſaid <hi>Davidical</hi> Kingdom, many wayes in the word of God ſecured to him, in the ſaid thouſand years, with all the ſaid Saints in the Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of all things; theſe are no ſlight matters, though much over looked by men.</p>
                  <p>We ſhall now a little touch upon the particulars in our ſaid Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteme of Gods Oeconomy, or ordering his houſhold the Church, in regard of his mercies ſo made known, and ſo in the ſaid thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years to be fulfilled for his Saints; firſt in removing or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying all their Enemies, and doing for them all revealed or promiſed good; either firſt as faithful men from <hi>Adam,</hi> or as <hi>Gentiles</hi> from <hi>Japhet,</hi> as <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> as men after Gods own heart, meek and holy, <hi>&amp;c</hi> as <hi>David,</hi> as faithful Servants and the Overcomers of the Lamb Jeſus Chriſt, as Chriſtian Martyrs to Reign with him then, and to enjoy the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, at the beginning of the ſaid State in the eminent break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Serpents Satans head as revealed to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve;</hi> he will when he comes from the right hand of the Father eminently make his foes his foot-ſtool, when he will put down all Rule, all Authority, and Power, that ſtand in oppoſition to him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24. at his ſecond coming; and perfect it after the end of the 1000 years, as we ſhewed: and how will he thereby be gloryfied, and how will his Saints rejoyce at this, as was ſaid at <hi>Babylons</hi> deſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.20. <hi>Rejoyce over her, thou Heaven, and ye holy Apoſtles and Prophets,</hi> &amp;c. So likewiſe much more then, when root and branch and the whole body of the Beaſt will be given to the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning flame, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.11. at the beginning, &amp; alſo when after the end of the ſaid 100 years the laſt <hi>Geg</hi> &amp; <hi>Mogog</hi> ſhall be conſumed by fire
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:102108:24"/>from God out of Heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9. But how much more when the Saints then ſhall clearly diſcern that the Divine promiſed Seed of the Woman hath not only ſubdued the enemies, but by all his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices hath purchaſed and procured ſo great good as will both then be enjoyed by them, and alſo provided for them to all eternity enſuing. And not here to inſiſt on what was ſaid of <hi>Enoch</hi> or his Propheſie, <hi>Jude</hi> 13.14. to encourage men in good in the world by his tranſlation upon his walking with God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or to warn them againſt evil by his foreſhewing the Judgment at the ſaid times to be after manifeſted concurring with the former, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as the ſacred truth informs us.</p>
                  <p>We ſhall in the next place, offer the conſideration of <hi>Noah</hi> a worker of righteouſneſs in a three fold reſpect, 1. as a Type of Chriſt. 2. Of the Covenant of God made with him for the New World. 3. Of his Propheſie. 1. He ſaved his Family in the Ark, as Chriſt doth his Houſehold the Church: and will be his peoples true Ark to ſave them at the partial or total Conſumption of the World by Fire, at the beginning, and after the end of the ſaid 1000 years, of which the Saints will then have bleſſed experience in both reſpects. And 2dly. As the Saints will know that the World according to Gods free Covenant with <hi>Noah, Gen.</hi> 8. &amp; 9. was many thouſand years preſerved till then; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> that the moſt abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant fruitfulneſs of the earth was in wonderful manner according to Gods Word reſerved for that ſtate and time; in the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or ſight whereof all the ſaid Saints will pay their due Tribute of Praiſe and Thankſgiving: wherefore they muſt then live to do it.</p>
                  <p>But 3dly, and more eſpecially, when according to <hi>Noahs</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of <hi>Japhets</hi> Poſterity the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that they ſhould dwell in the Tents of <hi>Shem</hi> (though ſtrangers before ſhould become the people of God) which the Scriptures witneſs they have once ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled already to them (whereof at this day we have cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce and bleſs Gods holy Name for the ſame) ever ſince the <hi>Jews</hi> were rejected: But we, and all Saints hereafter, will have cauſe more abundantly to rejoyce and praiſe his Name in thoſe times to come, upon that account when <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhall both rejoyce together, according to <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Propheſie, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.43. which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> applies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. with other texts (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting the ſame time, and ſtate) pointing out the truth of God therein, for the truth of God (ſaith he) to confirm the promiſes made to the Fathers, <hi>v.</hi> 8. how will the knowledg of that foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:102108:24"/>fitted to the top-ſtone of Gods performance, then affect Gods Saints with joy, and redownd to his own praiſe.</p>
                  <p>And was not <hi>Baalams</hi> Parable clear in many things forenamed, which in part have been fulfilled, as reſpecting the Ships of <hi>Chittim, Dan.</hi> 11.30. and others, namely, ſetting forth the riſe of the laſt Oppreſſor of the <hi>Jews</hi> that ſhould periſh for ever, or go into Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. (as we ſhewed) and other things in the 1000 years which Gods word witneſſeth ſhall then be fulfilled, which the Saints will alſo rejoyce in, and render unto God his due praiſe for them.</p>
                  <p>And what in <hi>Melchiſedeck</hi> was ſhadowed as a type towards faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Abraham</hi> that had the Promiſes, will really and compleatly be fulfilled in Chriſt to faithful <hi>Abraham</hi> and all his ſpiritual Seed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Gods word, to the praiſe of the glory of his grace.</p>
                  <p>But eſpecially to <hi>Abraham</hi> and all his ſpiritual Seed with him, and alſo to <hi>Iſaack,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> according to Gods Promiſes and Covenants made to them and their ſpiritual Seed through their one Divine Seed Chriſt: But the mercy ſeems to be chiefly inveſted in <hi>Abrahams</hi> Covenant in ſeven Gradations, as we ſhewed in our <hi>Key:</hi> who is thereupon (probably) ſtiled the Father of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and Heir of the world, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13. whoſe natural Seed failed in their firſt Covenant, and polluted their reſt in the Typical <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> which therefore caſt them out with a fore Deſtruction, <hi>Mich.</hi> 2.10. But the ſpiritual Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> by that one Divine Seed Chriſt, whoſe day he ſaw by Faith, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8. by Gods undertaking for them the conditions of this New Covenant which then will be manifeſt to the great glory of his ſo wonderful free Grace made known; and the benefit from that Foundation derived to them, as both his faithful Seed, circumciſed and uncircumciſed will evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know and find the happy experience of in the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate (then) both filling their ſouls with joy, and making them break forth into praiſe unto God.</p>
                  <p>But for <hi>Davids</hi> Promiſe and Covenant upon whoſe intereſt the Title of Chriſts Kingdom (then) doth immediately depend, and who muſt enjoy it as the days of Heaven upon earth all the 1000 years, though what he promiſed conditionally as reſpecting <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> Kingdom in his natural Race was forfeited by them upon the fall of whoſe Tabernacle the Interim, or Interruption of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom took place in the four <hi>Gentile</hi> Kingdoms for (probably) 2300 years: yet the ſure mercies of <hi>David,</hi> in Chriſt his Divine ſpiritual Seed, all will be performed for the the meek, faithful, up
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:102108:25"/>right, ſpiritual Children of <hi>David,</hi> who ſhall then have their ſure mercies of <hi>David</hi> alſo, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 55.3. in being then joynt heirs with Chriſt in that bleſſed Kingdom, when they upon that account and foundation ſhall Reign with Chriſt in that ſtate of the New Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and New Earth wherein will then dwell Righteouſneſs to the ſuperabundant glory of God, and happineſs of all thoſe Saints who ſhall have their portion then therein, with the repreſentative living Wights, and 24 Elders to exult as they, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that in other reſpects they have been or ſhall be Kings and Prieſts unto God through the Lambs Blood; but that they then will with them joyntly Reign upon earth: when <hi>Davids</hi> Tabernacle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fallen for the Sin of his natural Seed ſhal, by his Divine one Seed Chriſt be reſtored for himſelf and all his ſpiritual Seed in that ſo bleſſed ſtate and condition to continue the ſaid 1000 years, and after remain to the Saints ſo long as the Sun and Moon ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.36, 37. (though once attempted againſt in vain) and after (probably) be tranſlated into perpetual felicity; and were but the ſpiritual eyes and underſtandings of men exerciſed in theſe things from the grounds of them, ſo Divinely and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly laid down in the Word, and did they but labour by Prayer and due means to acquaint themſelves with the ſame, by degrees I doubt not, but God would really teach in ſome good meaſure, all rightly teachable ſpirits of men by Faith to believe them, and apply them to themſelves, as finding (if they walk uprightly with him) their own peculiar intereſt therein, with all his Saints that then ſhall have their Lots there with them: both to be freed from all enemies, to ſerve him without fear of any, in holyneſs and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs before Chriſt then (if they be in the natural life, and walk in the light of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi>) or if raiſed Saints then ſuch his ſervants will ſerve him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.3. it will be found as well their happineſs as their buſineſs ſo to do: God hath not made ſo great proviſion for the marriage of the Lamb, his only beloved Son, &amp; that the Wedding be without Gueſts; yea, which is more, that the Wedding be without the Bride the Lambs Wife: What a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach would ſome men by ignorance and unbelief caſt upon God the Maſter of the Feaſt, as if his great deſign to honour them who before had honoured him in the World ſhould then be fruſtrate and utterly in vain? which muſt needs be, if thoſe who are only ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of ſuch happineſs for time, and bleſſedneſs in both ſhould not then have it, <hi>viz.</hi> the raiſed Sts. in the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate with thoſe that walk ſhall then in the light thereof (probably) not fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:102108:25"/>then to enjoy the ſame with them, neither could the Saints departed before, be capable thereof, were they not in their ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual bodies prepared for the ſame; and how many ſorts of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments might be drawn from every of the ſaid Foundations parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, let ſerious and judicious Chriſtians conſider: when I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly found from Gods word, what would be before, in, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the 1000 years, I was ſatisfied that ſuch things ſhould be in their due time and order; fulfilled in 36 particulars in the firſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the <hi>Word Written.</hi> But it hath pleaſed God by this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Key, Rev.</hi> 20, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to ſhew me that the chief drift of all his Revealed Promiſes, pitch upon ſuch a ſtate ſo revealed by himſelf, wherein all his Sts. intereſts and concernments concur for the beſt ends reſpecting God, themſelves, &amp; all Creatures in that ſtate, in ſo many and great things, as we have manifeſted from the Word of God, whence I am as it were enforced to do that by Faith in my preſent employment, that I aſſuredly, from the ſame word, know thoſe raiſed Saints, with others, will then do in the fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof; affectionately deſiring to ſet forth Gods ſpecial mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, like the Woman in <hi>Samaria,</hi> for others uſe and benefit alſo.</p>
                  <p>For then the faithful Seed of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> that had no other Promiſe, will ſee and know that the bleſſed Seed of the Woman hath broken the Serpents head, and chiefly eminently at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and fully after the end of the 1000 years.</p>
                  <p>Then alſo ſuch as lived from <hi>Enoch</hi> ſhall know how both Gods acts of Judgment will be carried on: then will all ſaved Saints of <hi>Japhets</hi> Race ſee and acknowledg the grace of the laſt great call of <hi>Gentiles</hi> as well as the firſt: then all Saints from <hi>Noah,</hi> will praiſe God for the Earths preſervation and fruitfulneſs then in ſuch abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, as before promiſed, and then performed: Then they from <hi>Baalams</hi> Prophecyed mercies then to take place, will find great matter of joy and praiſe to God: then they will from <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> his Propheſie know Chriſts hands are ſufficient for him when he is ſo happily come to his people: Then all <hi>Abrahams</hi> faithful Seed, through that one Seed Chriſt ſhall enjoy the Promiſed Land and City in that excellent Renewed State: then ſhall all meek and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right ones, with <hi>David,</hi> poſſeſs all the happineſs of Chriſts <hi>Davidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Kingdom, containing all the reſt.</p>
                  <p>But becauſe ſome, like <hi>Thomas,</hi> though Chriſt was preſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes, had reſolved not to believe; ſo theſe, upon the neer approach of Chriſts ſaid Kingdom, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.28.31. <hi>unleſs he put his fingers in the holes of his wounds;</hi> when the Doctrine of it is
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:102108:26"/>become very evident, will not only not own it, but not with pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence hear of the Doctrine of it; yea, think all ſuch, like the two Diſciples neer <hi>Emaus,</hi> are but idle tales that are ſaid thereof; yea, and ſay ſo too till God ſhall ſhew them their errors, that they may give due praiſe to his holy name in regard thereof: We ſhall a little expoſtulate the caſe, and reaſon with ſuch; that ſo we may convince them of their error, and leave them at leaſt inexcuſable, or rather ſatisfie them therein, if it may be. What, hath God written ſo much in his Word, and in ſo many particulars, as we have heard, all ſo fitly anſwering to each other, and all to no purpoſe, <hi>&amp;c.?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hath God in unſpeakable mercy and goodneſs been laying the ſoundation, and erecting a ſtately Structure, which ſhould be as the Maſter-piece of Chriſts workmanſhip, and almoſt in the 6000 years paſt hath been carrying the ſame on, that his glory in the compleating thereof, may ſhine out eminently before Angels and Men, and all Creatures, wherein that true <hi>Solomons</hi> glory may in due time appear; and that his Saints may upon the diſcovery thereof, firſt by Faith, and after by actual fruition, receive the benefit thereof: and this the better to prepare them (with the glorious Angels) for that perfect and perpetual bleſſedneſs, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meadiately to ſucceed unto it; and all upon ſo many excellent ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, and from ſuch ſtrong foundations thereof? And ſhall it be reckoned no better than Satans three ſaid <hi>Babels,</hi> but worſe? as if it, after ſo long preparation for it by God and Chriſt, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation from the Faith of it in the Saints ſo long ago; it would yet never at all appear in the world? Shall mens unbelief darken the luſtre of ſo great an undertaking of Chriſt? Let God be true, and let all men of ſuch unbelieving hearts be found to be lyars. Did Chriſt pray for ſuch a ſtate, wherein all thoſe that God had given him ſhould be made perfect in one, as the Bride the Lambs Wife, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.19. &amp; 21. and will men go about, now the Marriage day is neer, to forbid the Banes? he willed before he died alſo, that all thoſe which God had given him ſhould behold his glory in his Kingdom, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. given him by his Father; <hi>viz.</hi> his Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Kingdom: and are all Divine Propheſies, of theſe things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as wind with theſe men? But let ſuch beware, leſt as the unbelief of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> cut them ſhort of enjoying the typical <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> ſo leſt it be alſo found that many ſuch ſhall come ſhort of this heavenly City of Gods making through their unbelief: no ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacle like unbelief to Divine Mercies: and according to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:102108:26"/>opinion of ſome Fathers, there will be <hi>mora</hi> in the Reſurrect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion of the juſt, if men knew but competently the excellency and worth of ſuch an eſtate they would take more pains and care to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it; and that early too: they would think every hour, every minute a great loſs, wherein it might be attainable. And then alſo let ſuch take notice that all Ages ftom Chriſts firſt giving of this Revelation, have in ſome degree or other witneſſed to theſe Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines; and Men or Devils could never ſo ſuppreſs it, but it ſtill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe up again; and in theſe laſt days more than ever, now the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of that ſtate approacheth: and I doubt not as Divine Truth will more and more prevaile with many, though (as it is probable) many will reject it, as the Scripture ſeems to foreſhew (as in our 10th Aſſert of our <hi>Key</hi> is obſervable) yet Satans ſeven Vials have not, nor ſhall deſtroy it, <hi>Prod.</hi> pag. 41, 42.</p>
                  <p>It is true indeed, without a ſpetial Faith, like <hi>Abrahams, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids,</hi> or the like, men were not like to ſee it of old, though couched in many Promiſes: neither in the New Teſtament, were men likely without an extraordinary ſpirit to conceive aright of much of theſe Doctrines; nor could ſatisfactory knowledg ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily be had without this Key of Chriſts making, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. &amp; 21. &amp; 22. that ſo fitly opens that (before to us) much locked Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; but thereby it is ſo laid open, that each Jewel may be ſeen and made good uſe of by Faith at preſent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Gods works of grace are moſt beautiful in their times, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And conſider in the Creation, Was not Gods Wiſdom and Goodneſs therein made glorious, at firſt by putting man in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Creatures, being made fit to glorify God in thoſe his former works by keeping a Sabbath immediately thereupon, had he ſtood upright in his eſtate: and will not this great work of Chriſts Reſtitution of all things, wherein Gods Divine Wiſdom, Power, Mercy, Truth and Faithfulneſs will appear much more glorious (as the holy Scriptures teach) which hath been almoſt 6000 years in carrying on, and a yet more perfect work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of his ſaid Saints, <hi>viz.</hi> of their Bodies, alſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.21, 23. with inferiour Creatures, and then living perſons from all ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.74. Likewiſe, that all of them at length may enjoy that Sabatiſm of Reſt remaining to them in ſuch a bleſſed eſtate in that world of Chriſts ſaid Mediatory Kingdom, which he on casth affared his little little Flock they ſhould have of Gods good pleaſure and free gift, with that <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> the City of him the ſaid igreat King, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. which God hath prepared for the Fore-fathers alſo, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10, 16.</p>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:102108:27"/>
                  <p>Now what way ſoever the Revealed, Promiſed or Covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Right and Enjoyments, of the Saints in that ſtate, or upon what account ſoever they ſhall find it, (for many Reaſons may be gr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, they will all clearly know it) whether as the faithful Seed of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> as men through the bleſſed promiſed Seed of the Woman, the great Redeemer of all men: Or as the Seed of <hi>Japhet,</hi> being <hi>Gentiles</hi> by their firſt or 2d. Calls aforeſaid: or as that ſpiritual Seed of <hi>Abrah. Iſaac</hi> or <hi>Jacob,</hi> by that one divine Seed Chriſt to come, as the natural and ſpiritual <hi>Iſrael</hi> alſo, or the ſpiritual <hi>Iſrael</hi> onely, or as any wayes having a Title by and with Chriſt, in his ſaid <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidical</hi> Kingdom; they will upon all thoſe or the like accounts or intereſts, whereby ſuch divine goodneſs is conveyed to them, accordingly, magnifie his name and all together, ſound forth his praiſe for them all, (as Chriſts myſtical Members perfected) rejoycing in the happineſs one of another, and all joyntly exalt Chriſt their divine and glorious Head and Hus band, and both then, and for ever ſound forth Praiſe and Glory to God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Lamb that was ſlain, and to the Holy Spirit for ever and ever; both joyntly, and as upon their ſeveral accounts they are in poſſeſſion of happineſs and glory: It is want of informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and conſequently of the Faith of theſe Truths, that is the Reaſon why many are at preſent no more affected with the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them; the Reaſon whereof appears to be, becauſe God was pleaſed ſo myſteriouſly to lay them down, that unleſs few by a ſpecial Faith foreſaw them, (as we ſaid) that ſew others uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcerned much of them; and though we in the New Teſtament times, might ſee much in thoſe antient promiſes contained, as ſince in Old and New Teſtament hath been further by degrees ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained; yet without this laſt ſaid divine Key, given by Jeſus Chriſt himſelf; we could never have been reſolved and ſatisfied of, or concerning the time and place, and perſons to enjoy them, nor how they ſhould be fitted in ſuch a ſtate to obtain them, with many circumſtances thereunto appertaining; which from this bleſſed laſt <hi>Revelation,</hi> Chriſt hath graciouſly reſolved for his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants preſent comfort and future happineſs in that State, and for ever.</p>
                  <p>And to lead unto the uſe of this ſaid excellent Key, all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer parts of the whole <hi>Revelation,</hi> is made to be ſubſervient through all thoſe ſad ſuffering times, to lead Gods Servants to this trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant ſtate (in good meaſure) then next ſucceeding, as well as to teach the Sufferers before, that God had appointed them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:102108:27"/>but a <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate followed, as in the ſeven Epiſtles, and all parts following as we ſhewed, <hi>Prod. p.</hi> 39.40. and ſo to occaſion us to look unto what God revealed, of the ſtate of his Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by <hi>Daniel</hi> and others, under the four Monarchies; and ſo by looking back to the fall of <hi>Davids</hi> Tabernacle, to conſider what is foretold of the raiſing it up again; and ſo of all the ſaid ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly revealed promiſes, one by one, to obſerve by the guidance of Gods Word and Spirit, what they all related unto, till we came backward to the firſt divinely publiſhed Grace, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. The Foundation and ſhort compriſal of all the reſt, yea of the whole Book of God; from whence as the Spring head, all the other Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volets have flowed in their ſeveral courſes, to empty themſelves into thoſe narrow Seas or Streights of the 1000 years, to paſs in their order and time from thence into the vaſt Ocean of Eternity, (as in our ſaid Reſemblance) and all in that time and manner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by God appointed.</p>
                  <p>Many Arguments may hence from our whole Syſteme be drawn for the Saints ſaid bleſſed firſt Reſurrection of their Bodies, being many wayes their peculiar intereſt, ariſing from many antient intereſts, beſides manifold reſpects unto God himſelf therein: for theſe are no new Devices or Fancies of men, but antient Foundations of Gods own laying, often confirmed, and much by degrees explained, but now by Chriſt irreſiſtably evidenced, ſo as to leave all men inexcuſable, to whom ſuch Truth ſhall be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon tendered; and all that hear it ought to judge themſelves greatly concerned, to inquire rightly and duly into it; that is, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, faithfully, diligently, earneſtly, as being a truth of the Goſpel, but now greater then at other times upon many ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts; and therefore they ought to hear, read, pray, ponder well and conſider with pains and patience, and willingneſs to be informed in theſe things; though they may be good Teachers other wayes: And in ſuch a courſe men may be Gods bleſſing, ſoon ſay as the Neighbours of the woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> ſaid unto her, now we believe theſe things; not becauſe ſuch or ſuch told us of them, but now we find we are taught by Chriſt the ſame Truths, and rejoyce likewiſe in them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But I conceive ſo much hath been ſaid upon this account, in our ſaid Preface prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory, and in this Tract alſo, with divers ſhort intimations and hints, that conſiderate perſons will not think of any of them, without reſpects to the Saints bodily Reſurrection, revealed here by Chriſt in ſo many circumſtances, that an Infidel in Reaſon ſhall hardly
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:102108:28"/>deny? But onely take this along, Chriſts laſt <hi>Revelation</hi> muſt be allowed to be a <hi>Revelation</hi> of ſomething, not ſo known before, or elſe it had been uſeleſs; but it is of ſuch great matters of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment as none elſe could, and is of ſo great moment as became the Son of God, the Lamb that received the Book to open this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Seal to the uttermoſt, no other way otherwiſe to have been known: And therefore let us all give all praiſe due unto the Lamb, and bleſs the Father who gave the ſaid Book to him, and acknowledge the gracious operation of the holy Spirit, who teaches us every degree of Divine wiſdom; and ſo from our ſaid Grounds, Reaſons and Arguments, which have been alſo drawn from Scripture Foundations: We now proceed to our fourth way of proving this firſt Reſurrection, to be the Saints ſaid bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly riſing, which Chriſt will bring with him at his coming in the Clouds of Heaven, to raiſe them in their ſpiritual Bodies, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the happineſs of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate, in the ſaid 1000. years of their Reign with Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But here a great Obſtacle ſeems to lye in our way, for what other Text or Texts of, Scripture, may ſome ſay, teach theſe things? And for <hi>Revelation</hi> Myſteries they are obſcure, and they may ſeem queſtionable, whether they be Argumentative or not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the firſt branch, That there are other Texts of Scripture, in Old and New Teſtament, that ſpeak the ſame things in ſubſtance; though more darkly we ſhall by and by ſhew; and we have before obſerved (and it ought here to be remembred) that the Doctrine of the Reſurrection was long, but darkly delivered: our Saviour therefore proves the Reſurrection by an inference from the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teuch of <hi>Moſes,</hi> againſt the <hi>Sadduces;</hi> being that part of holy Scripture, which that Sect onely owned, and little is found of it in all the old Teſtament, at leaſt that is clear and explicite; in the Goſpel we read of the Reſurrection of the juſt, and as before our Saviour ſpake of the Children of the Reſurrection in that World, but how few have taken notice of what World that was meant? So theſe remained for the moſt part ſtill obſcure; the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul</hi> reveals a myſtery of it, yea many Myſteries (as we hope to manifeſt) the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Iſraelites</hi> civil Reſurrection, that is near to it, and in Scripture adjoyned to it, is likewiſe called a Myſtery and riſing from the dead, for the ſtrangneſs of it <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37. with <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. &amp; <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1, 2, 3. and both are again joyned by our Saviour, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.28, 31. But our Saviour according to his Divine wiſdom, hath given light to thoſe and many other Texts
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:102108:28"/>of that nature; and ſhould we in this cavil with our Mercy, and contend with our moſt Divine Teacher, as if we were wiſer then he, or that Wiſdom it ſelf had erred therein! And indeed it is ſtrange to hear mens perverſe reaſonnings in theſe things, and the like; but we ſhall give other Scriptures that teach the ſame in ſubſtance or the like, after all (as we ſaid) both in Old and New Teſtament: Onely we would ſpeak a word or two to the other branch of the Objection, in the firſt place: That the Book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> is myſterious, and men have been much mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, <hi>&amp;c. Anſ.</hi> It hath been in ſome things a ſecret, long but yet not ſuch as were forbidden to inquire into; yea we are command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to read it and ſearch this, as other Books of the Goſpel, viz. to underſtand it, and it is not as in <hi>Daniels</hi> hints of theſe things, when he was commanded to ſhut them up; but contrary, the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> is commanded to leave them open, and not Seal them, <hi>Chap.</hi> 22. <hi>v.</hi> 10. Yea our Saviour pronounceth a bleſſing to ſuch as read them as they ought, and he hath bleſſed many with very Remarkable Diſcoveries by degrees, (though Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors are injuriouſly Critical againſt them,) inſtead of being thankful to God, and to them, for what they have in ſuch kind diſco vered, and ſtumble more at a Conjecture or eaſie miſtake, then profit by many pretious and uſeful things, ſo tendered to them, all have but what meaſure they receive, to ſuch purpoſe from God, in one reſpect or other, and God hath vouchſafed a ſpecial aſſiſtance in this kind one way or other; even ſometimes by unexpected and unlikely means, and Inſtruments; ſomewhat I could ſay in that kind, but it may not be convenient, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> did not Chriſt ſend his Spirit to lead his into all truth, and <hi>Revelation</hi> Truths are ſome of them, yea and very pretious ones too: Though ſome miſtakenly would perſwade ſome good perſons to the contrary, and Gods Spirit hath not yet laid down that Office, Chriſt promiſed to ſend him for, though we expect no new Foundation Truths, but the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and true Explications of old, and of ſuch antient Foundations eſpecially as we have occaſion now to ſpeak of; for the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is always of ſome (before) obſcure and hidden Scripture Truths, and it is a great advantage (as we before noted in our Preface) to know the ſubject, nature, time and end of ſuch Scripture Truths; ſo in this book revealed, as by this moſt precious Key that reſpects the happy eſtate fore Propheſied for Gods people in the ſaid 1000
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:102108:29"/>years: it is true, it was long in thoſe reſpects, miſtaken by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and ſtrangly miſplaced, but now they are in a great meaſure made evident: it is true alſo, the times of the great Red Dragon, and the Beaſt were for a long time more dark and obſcure, till their fulfillings in many things, have given more light to ſuch things as yet remain unfulfilled; but particularly, as to theſe laſt things the ſaid Key relates unto (as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> well obſerves) the ſpirit of God ſpeaks more clearly of theſe in <hi>ch.</hi> 20. of this <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> than in the times foregoing: and the two laſt <hi>chap.</hi> are in ſome meaſure an explication of the ſame matters, and times, and ſtate of things in the ſaid 1000 years; and that 20th <hi>ch.</hi> is an exact Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſuch times, which if a man once diſcover what things it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates unto, he is in a good way to attain the end thereof; and it being once found to be Chriſts Key of antient revealed Mercies (as Scriptures make evident in many particulars) as I have, and doubt not, by the ſame guidance, to give farther and good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of from Gods Word; which alſo I am well aſſured from Scripture, and ſatisfied, (whatever ſome may think otherwiſe) that for the ſubſtance, it will be approved by Jeſus Chriſt the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and true Witneſs, and our Guide into theſe Truths, by the aſſiſtance of his Holy Spirit; and I ſhall ever reſolve, with humble thankſgiving, to aſcribe the praiſe thereof to his Divine Grace, for ſuch a great mercy to ſuch a poor weak much inwardly and outwardly ſhattered and broken Earthen Veſſel: But as it is his work of Grace by a weak hand, ſo tendered, let none deſpiſe it: God ſtands in need of no mans parts, learning, eſteem, or worldly advantage or intereſt whatſoever farther than he pleaſeth.</p>
                  <p>The ſlighting of this moſt Divine excellent and ſacred Book is much in ſome mens minds and mouths; therefore I thought fit here to ſay thus much to it. Now let us proceed to the Sympho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and agreement of this with other Texts of Scripture, for the <hi>Revelation</hi> (as we noted) is of ſome Divine Truth written be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; yet if we know Chriſt ſpake this of the firſt Reſurrection of the Saints bodily, and ſpake it ſo plainly in a good degree, it is preſumption to ſeek a confirmation of his words; but becauſe it is a Revelation, it is of ſome Scripture before though darkly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, as all the other parts were of <hi>Daniels</hi> ſhort hints ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or ſhut up before, and ſo is this of the ſubſequent Myſteries in <hi>Daniel,</hi> in reſpect of their time (as in part we ſhewed) though much of this firſt Reſurrection, we hope to manifeſt from other Scriptures likewiſe. We will begin with the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi>'s Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:102108:29"/>in that excellent Song, <hi>ch.</hi> 26. who having ſaid of thoſe Lords that had Dominion over the <hi>Jews, viz.</hi> the Heathen Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, <hi>v.</hi> 13, 14. <hi>They are dead, they ſhall not live; they are deceaſed, they ſhall not riſe: viz.</hi> at this firſt Reſurrection, <hi>v.</hi> 19. but he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares there who ſhall live and riſe (then) <hi>thy dead men,</hi> ſaith he, namely Gods Saints, <hi>ſhall live; together with my dead body ſhall they ariſe:</hi> that is, at the ſaid firſt Reſurrection, which our Saviour hath here ſo fully explained: So <hi>David</hi> foreſeeing, by the Spirit of Propheſie, that the Juſt ſhall have Dominion at that time, over ſuch wicked men, in the morning of the Reſur. and day of Judgment; it muſt needs follow as our Saviour explains the ſame; that the juſt muſt neceſſarily firſt riſe to receive that Dominion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.14. and in this <hi>Daniel</hi> concurs alſo, for when the Thrones were ſet or placed, as the words ſignifie (not caſt down, as ours read them) at Chriſts coming, then (as we ſhewed) Judgment, or power of Judging was given to the Saints: it is the ſame time, and the ſame thing which the Apoſtle is trught here by Chriſt here to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, at the end of the <hi>Romane</hi> Monarchie, in this 20th <hi>chapt.</hi> of <hi>Rev.</hi> who expreſsly ſhews that the ſuffering Saints before, then lived to Reign with Chriſt 1000 years: to this tends alſo the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul</hi>'s <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or riſing out of the heap of the dead (then) <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.11. and our Saviours expreſſion of thoſe worthy ones to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that world by <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which we explained before to be a riſing from them that were in a ſtate of dead men in the grave: the ſame Apoſtle hath divers texts tending this way; where he, as being guided by the ſame Spirit of Chriſt, ſpeaks e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently in the ſame ſenſe, both of the times of both Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and other things, as the perſons riſing at both. 1. Conſider 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.21. where he ſhews, as Chriſt was the firſt fruits of his firſt Reſurrection, ſo they muſt riſe at his ſecond coming, before the end; which Chriſt ſhews will be above 1000 years after (as was ſaid) and before he hath put down all Rule, and Authority, and Power, to make way for his own Reign, <hi>v.</hi> 24, 25. and then, <hi>v.</hi> 51, 52. he ſhews that at the laſt Trumpet, the great chang of all Saints ſhall be, which muſt be when all have come into Chriſt in the 1000 years, not before poſſible; for not one member of Chriſt can then be wanting, beſides other Reaſons: ſo of both ſaid comings. At firſt, he brings his Saints with him, that ſlept in Jeſus, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. <hi>ult,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14, 15. but (then) he ſpeaks there of his deſcending from Heaven with a ſhout, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven (as when the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> came from God out of Heaven)
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:102108:30"/>but of three forts then to be caught up to meet him in the Aire, <hi>v.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6 juſt as the Revelation tells us of the Saints raiſed in the <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> ſtate, and of the Nations of them that are ſaved, walking in the light of the ſaid <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> which being mortal, ſome of them die in the 1000 years, as <hi>Eſa.</hi> 65.20. and ſo lie dead till the laſt Trump; ſo here, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14, 15. of the two former, faith he, we that are alive and remain (<hi>viz.</hi> to the coming of the Lord to the laſt Judgment) ſo diſtinguiſhing both the living and the raſed Saints remaining from the dead, and, ſaith he, the dead then in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt, that is, before the wicked (as the raiſed Saints alſo did before in the 1000 years) and ſo again in the former text, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. concerning the living Saints, <hi>then,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>we ſhall not all ſleep,</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> by dying before a natural death) for ſome will be found alive at the laſt Trump which he ſpeaks of; but of ſuch, and the raiſed Saints (ſaith he) we ſhall all be changed, and from both ſorts he diſtinguiſheth a third alſo; namely, ſuch as are dead in Chriſt, at that time the Trumpet ſounds, which he ſaith ſhall then be raiſed incorruptible, when both the other ſorts ſhall be changed alſo in a moment, <hi>v.</hi> 51, 52. ſo agreeably the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God ſpeaketh in all places to his own Oracles; and in the <hi>Revelation</hi> Chriſt gives us the beſt explication of all ſuch Myſteries, for in the 1000 years the raiſed Saints, and they ſaved in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural life will be of one Communion: all to be changed, and all ſaid to live and remain till the the laſt Trump; but ſuch as ſleep, or are dead (then) are in both places diſtinguiſhed from both the other, and in both Texts called the dead; in one the dead in Chriſt then, to diſtinguiſh them from all the wicked then dead, yet both ſaid to be the reſt of the dead that roſe not till the 1000 years were ended, <hi>ch.</hi> 20.5. Now to prevent miſtaking, the Apoſtle reſolved the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> 2 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2.2, 3. that the coming of the Lord was not at hand in thoſe ages; for the great falling away, and reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Man of Sin was to be firſt, and Chriſt would deſtroy him with the appearance of his preſence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is not yet done: but he was guided by the ſame ſpirit of Truth in theſe Texts, to ſpeak according to theſe Revelation Diſcoveries (who alſo at his rapture into the third Heaven heard unſpeakable words, of which theſe might be ſome) and I believe it was not poſſible to reſolve the riddles in them without Chriſts Revelation given for many ſuch purpoſes; and here is one coming with all his Saints, which he brings with him: this <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. &amp; 21. ſhews to be at the beginning of the 1000 years; and there is another after 1000 years, when
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:102108:30"/>all the Saints are come into the Church, and when all ſhall be rapt up in the twinckling of an eye to meet Chriſt in they aire, which the Apoſtle calls a coming as well as a deſcending (which we have not till now obſerved) we that live and remain to the come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>viz.</hi> to the laſt Judgment; ſo three ſorts ſhall then be rapt or caught to meet Chriſt that laſt time in the aire; yea, and (ſaith he) we ſhall ever be with the Lord; which it is evident will be after the end of the 1000 years, for when Satan was looſed, they were not with him perſonally preſent. Two ſorts are diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the dead Saints at the time of that rapture in both Texts: of thoſe in that to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> (ſaith he) we ſhall not all ſleep: ſome Saints then will be mortal, but not all dead, but we ſhall all, even we all, <hi>viz.</hi> all Saints raiſed before, as well as thoſe in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural life ſhall then be changed: ſo in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> we that are alive and remain, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, we that ſo live, and we that are left for that long continuance: both the two Articles <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and the original word ſeem to ſpeak the like difference of two ſorts of Saints (beſides the dead Saints then) and both theſe Texts are cleared by Chriſts Revelation, that tells us of the ſpirits of juſt men coming with him, as the <hi>New Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> down from Heaven, after ſaid to be the Lambs Wife, and theſe lived having then their ſpiritual bodies from Chriſt; and alſo the Nations of them that are ſaved are then alſo ſaid to walk in the light of that <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> from whoſe happy Communion, they will have much guidance and conſolation in that ſtate: and both theſe are by Chriſt alſo differenced from the reſt of the dead Saints that lived not till the 1000 years were ended, <hi>ch.</hi> 20.5. that then are ſaid to riſe firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> at the laſt Trump and Rapture. Now if men would produce thouſands of Expoſitors of anothers mind, I muſt only in duty humbly Anſwer, I have Chriſts Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in the caſe (as of <hi>Daniels</hi> hints before) from this Divine Revelation, and otherwiſe I believe no man had ever been able fully and truly to have opened theſe Texts, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, by reaſon of ſuch <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> contained in them, hard to be underſtood. Let all men therefore learn to praiſe God for this bleſſed Divine Book of the <hi>Revelation;</hi> and learn to have its Explications in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great Veneration; for had it not been uſeful and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, it had never been ſo wonderfully adorned with ſo many glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous excellencies, which I believe the Saints in that world to come will acknowledge, to the honour and praiſe of Jeſus Chriſt, whoſe that ſacred Book is entitled to be, <hi>viz.</hi> the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:102108:31"/>
                  <p>Now if men were not prepoſſeſſed with other groundleſs noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the General Reſurrection, and General Judgment without reſpect unto Chriſts Revelation, and other expreſſions of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in many reſpects agreeing therewith; theſe things were ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and familiar to ſuch as were tolerably verſed in the way and ſtile of that ſacred Book: but it is hard to remove long ſettled miſopinions of men upon ſome eaſie miſtakes, as in this caſe the Scripture often ſpeaks of them together without explication: but then we muſt grant the Spirit of God and Chriſt himſelf may, when and how, and by whom he pleaſes, make particular expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations in any reſpects, and it is the uſual manner in this Divine Book, firſt to hint generals, and after particularly to explain them: Chriſt will at the firſt act of Judgment, Judg quick and dead, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. <hi>viz.</hi> the wicked quick (as was ſaid) by remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them out of the world, and then with a Judgment of reward to his Servants the Prophets, and his Saints, and all that fear his name, both ſmall and great: as likewiſe at the latter act he will conſume the laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog, ch.</hi> 20.9, 10. as well as rap up the Saints at the laſt Trump, and raiſe the wicked then out of the Earth and Sea to be judged: the Saints to be pronounced then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly bleſſed; the other upon Tryal to be declared curſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Devil will then alſo be caſt into the Fiery Lake, though he was only bound, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the 1000 years. Oh that Chriſtians would humbly and diligently ſearch theſe Scriptures, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to pray themſelves into the right apprehenſions of theſe things; then they might better expect Gods Spirit would lead them into ſuch fecret things of God, which he will ſo reveal un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his faithful Servants, which otherwiſe (happly) they may not be reſolved of till the Appearance of Jeſus Chriſt, which then his raiſed Saints will find true. Which courſe, if they would take, their Language and Expreſſions would not be ſo antiſcriptural; nor their Explications of many Texts ſo hererodox to Chriſts Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of theſe, and ſome other matters, as ſometimes they are; and ſo diſorderly of Chriſts being King, Prieſt, and Prophet (which firſt in due order is laſt.) And there is more weight in theſe things, (however any may ſlight them) than men uſually (that have not learned otherwiſe from ſacred Scripture) are (happly) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of, whence many expoſitions are put upon ſome Texts, which I aſſuredly know, Chriſt Jeſus will not allow of, beſides their holding themſelves ſo more engaged againſt the Truth: But to paſs from this fourth way of proof of this firſt bodily Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:102108:31"/>of the Saints, by ſo many Scriptures ſpeaking to the ſame purpoſe, divers ways, with this Text and Context, whereby our Saviour here gives light and ſtrength to them all: who is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that Doctor <hi>irrefragabilis</hi> that need not ſpeak <hi>ex Cathedra</hi> (as they ſay) That great deluder of theſe latter days muſt do) or elſe he may err: But Chriſts <hi>Revelations</hi> in all ſuch kinds, are Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Reſolutions, that Chriſtians ought not only, not to gain ſay, but to reſt in, as their ultimate Determinations in the Caſe; though any, or many men ſhould not own them. And thus much for the proof of the point in hand; namely, That this ſaid Firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, is the Bodily Reſurrection of the ſuffering Saints here ſpoken of. And ſo we hope we have ſufficiently manifeſted the ſame to the Conſciences of ſerious and judicious Chriſtians: firſt from the Text, with its dependancie, and as the matter of the ſaid Divine Truth is explained Doctrinally by Chriſt himſelf, and here again ſet forth by his own Divine Revelation, in the order, time, and way of the execution of the ſame; and that by variety of expreſſions in ſeveral places to this very purpoſe, fully agreeing with the Apoſtles <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or riſing out of the heap (as was ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before) wherein the curious exactneſs of the Spirit of God is very remarkable (if rightly conſidered.)</p>
                  <p>Secondly, From the context, by divers Reaſons therein obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, manifeſting this particular <hi>Revelation,</hi> to be the Explication of <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſion <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.9, 10, 13, 14. Of the Judgement ſet to deſtroy the Beaſt, and to give his Body to the burning Flame at Chriſts coming, in the Clouds of Heaven, and his receiving his univerſal Kingdom over all Nations, under the whole Heavens; when he brings with him all his Saints that ſlept in him before, and and raiſeth them in their order bodily to Reign with him; which we thirdly prove two wayes: Firſt poſitively to be a bodily Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection from ſeveral Scriptures and Reaſons; and Secondly, on the Negative part, ſhewed it could not be meant of a ſpiritual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, ſetting forth the many abſurdities of ſuch a pretenſe: whereunto we added divers particular branches in our Syſteme of Gods Oeconomy, in ordering his Houſhold the Church from the beginning, in regard of thoſe antiently revealed and promiſed Mercies and Covenants to the Fathers, remaining cheifly to be (altogether) fulfilled in that ſtate of his ſaid <hi>Davidical</hi> Kingdom, in the 1000 years Reign with his Saints, and the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate the ſame time; which contain that ineſtimable Treaſure of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:102108:32"/>Grace, laid up therein of old for them, which now by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Divine Key is laid open for them for the preſent, to be uſed by Faith for their great conſolation, and whereby they ſhall alſo by the due improvement thereof: aſſuredly hereafter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largedly receive the Frution of the ſame, without which Divine Key (though the ſaid promiſes in the matter of them were ſure) yet there could not have been any ſatisfactory account given, by Angels or men, unleſs from ſome other ſuch ſpecial <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> when, or how, or where, or to whom; or how long with all ſuch circumſtances by Chriſt here decyphered thoſe ſaid reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and promiſed mercies ſhould be ſo performed to the Saints, but by this Key they are all excellently and divinely reſolved here by the Spirit of Chriſt, in his ſetting forth the times of the Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all things; when he makes all things new; <hi>Chap.</hi> 21.5. alſo ſpoken of by all the Holy Prophets ſince the World began, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19, 20, 21. Which will then be manifeſt to be Gods and Chriſts moſt glorious work, whileſt the WOrld ſhall continue, and the greateſt matter of Glory and Praiſe, to the Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty by Angels and men, and even inferiour Creatures (in their capacity) to be rendered to God the Father, to the Lamb that was ſlain, and to the Holy Spirit for ever and ever. And Fourthly, We have by ſundry Texts in Old and New Teſtament, ſet forth a wonderful accord and agreement of them, with this ſaid <hi>Revelation,</hi> which gives light to them all, and which could not otherwiſe have been known as was ſaid by Angels or Men.</p>
                  <p>And now I hope as Creation Atheiſts (as we may fitly call them) are generally exploded by all ſober and prudent perſons, who have unreaſonably fancied that Atoms, ſo fell in one with another to make up all things at firſt in the world: So allpious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians will more and more judge them, in ſome fort to be counted Creature-Redemption-Infidels at that time, or denyers of the Reſtitution of all things, that ſhould prophanely aſſert after ſo abundant evidence; that thoſe and all parts of Holy Scripture, reſpecting theſe Truths, fell onely in by the Fancies of the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of them in all parts thereof; &amp; that Chriſts opening thusall ſuch divine Myſteries, is but a mere Chymera and Phantaſtical Fiction: Of which dangerous Error, let all Slighters and Oppoſers of theſe divine Myſteries, beware of being found guilty at Chriſts appearance, now near approaching; for it is ſtrange in this Caſe,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:102108:32"/>to conſider what a bold licentiouſneſs of ſpeaking, ſome men have dared to venture upon even to amazement, now in ſuch times of Light, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Some ſuch Objections we have already anſwered, which fell in our way, and ſhould here anſwer many more, if many had not in our former parcels been anſwered before, and alſo by many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of late times, as we ſhewed particularly in the everlaſting Goſpel, on <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>pag.</hi> 19. is to be ſeen.</p>
                  <p>But one thing we ſhall here by way of prevention, reſolve by Divine affiſtance: Leaſt ſome ſubtil Queſtioniſt, rather to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct theſe Doctrines, then to diſprove them, ſhould demand of us in the Caſe, what ſpecial words of direction have we, for ſuch uſe of the ſaid Key; whereupon ſuch weight and ſtreſſe is laid?</p>
                  <p>We might briefly anſwer, the whole ſtreſs is not laid thereon; for before we had ſo well obſerved, and conſidered the uſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, by the order of accompliſhment of matters in the Book of <hi>Revalation</hi> which is of exceeding great uſe with the three others, we touched in our Preface, <hi>viz.</hi> the Subject, Nature and Scope of the Book: I ſay we had obſerved thirty ſix particulars before, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting thoſe times and things; but ſince upon the exactneſs of that <hi>Chap.</hi> reſpecting ſuch a change in the World, relating to the ancient Prophets; whereby all circumſtances are ſo ſet forth, and the ſacred Scriptures before had brought things to ſuch an height of ſuitableneſs, by ſearching through Gods goodneſs, we found that which we hope we ſhall never loſe again; that the 20. <hi>Chap.</hi> of <hi>Rev.</hi> &amp;c. is the great Key of moſt ancient Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie: And as the whole Scripture is the intereſt of all and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Saint, and what ever benefit or comfort is therein already re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, or hereafter ſhall be revealed, belongs to them all as ſuch: So more eſpecially thoſe Scripture Foundations, which concern ſo great a Joynt intereſt of all ſuch ſaid Saints together, are therefore more highly to be regarded, ſuch as thoſe are, which this Key evidently (upon Warrant from the word, as in good meaſure we have ſhewed) ſo evidently relates unto: If a Father give his only beloved Son all his Eſtate, and Houſe and Goods, and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures contained therein; though the Heir in his Nonage knew little of his Fathers poſſeſſions, yet when he is pleaſed to ſhew him ſome of his moſt pretious Jewels, though he ſtill reſerves them; yet the Son knows thoſe particularly ſhall be his; but yet
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:102108:33"/>when the Father ſets down a time of ſure enjoyment of them if the Fathers ſecurity be good) the Son onely waites for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time: Now all Gods adopted Children, (though but adopted by him with Chriſt to be his Sons) are both Heirs and Joynt-Heirs with Chriſt in his <hi>Davidical</hi> Kingdom; yea then with him will be Heirs of all things, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.7. All having there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in one and the ſame intereſt, of which Chriſt hath ſet a time for the enjoyment, and which will not fail them; And let ſuch a Queſtioniſt know, that when God hath once laid the Foundation of ſuch antient pretious mercies, the gradual <hi>Revelation</hi> of them is onely according to his own good pleaſure, and as in his infinite wiſdom and mercy to his People he ſees good: It was ſo in his firſt laying the great Corner Stone in his Houſe; Jeſus Chriſt at his firſt coming it hath been ſo in reſpect of all his Offices, and all his Benefits held forth by the Goſpel: But moſt of all in thoſe matters, reſpecting both the Myſteries of his Spiritual Kingdom, till Chriſts 2d coming; and alſo thoſe Myſtiries of his viſible glorious <hi>Davidical</hi> Kingdom; with all the excellencies of that ſtate, (both of which are the Contents of this Book) and in all Gods three chief Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nologers, <hi>Moſes, Daniel,</hi> and the beloved <hi>John,</hi> their Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles are both of large extent of time, (as in <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. of our <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic.</hi> is manifeſt) and myſterious; and to be conſidered as ſuch: But above all the Divine Excellencies of this Book, which is the <hi>Revelation</hi> of both the other Chronicles as we have ſhewed) are many ways wonderful; yet full of Divine ſweetneſs to ſuch of his, as Chriſt is pleaſed to open ſuch Treaſures unto, ſhortly from hence to be enjoyed by them; but yet more particulary as to this Divine Key, we are now ſpeaking of, it is made moſt fit to open the Lock, which may largely appear by the Work in it, and the Wards fitted for it: if we conſider them particularly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="key">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:102108:33"/>
                  <head>The mutual ſuitableneſs of them both evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by <hi>[The Picture of the Divine Key]</hi> here enſuing.</head>
                  <div type="prognostications">
                     <head>1. <hi>In Predictions.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. IF we reſpect the Enemies, or their Removal, Ruine and Judgment, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. and when, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110. 1. and <hi>Enoch</hi>'s Viſion of their Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Jud.</hi> 13.14. both in the ſaid firſt and ſecond acts of Judgment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. If we have reſpect to the Spiritual Seed of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve;</hi> or the Spiritual Seed of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Promiſed Seed of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 53. for whom a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe is to be procured by Chriſt, and reſtored to them at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of all things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. If we look at <hi>Noahs</hi> Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for the Earths Preſervation and Fruitfulneſs.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. If we reſpect <hi>Shems</hi> Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing derived to his Spiritual Race <hi>Abraham, Iſaack</hi> and <hi>Jacob, &amp;c.</hi> with all the Repeated and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged Promiſes of <hi>Canaan</hi> to their Spiritual Seed Chriſt,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:102108:34"/>to inherit the ſame through that one Divine Seed Chriſt of their Lineage after to come accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Fleſh.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Or to ſuch of <hi>Ahrahams, Iſaacks</hi> and <hi>Jacobs</hi> Poſterity, to be then in the natural Life, to whom many great Promiſes are then to be performed: and to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> likewiſe of <hi>Japhets</hi> Race, then, at their ſecond Call to be United in one Fold with that people of God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.43.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Or look upon it as the time of the Reſtitution of all things, as the end of Chriſts undertaking in the world, <hi>viz.</hi> according to his Promiſe of the New Heavens and New Earth, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 65.17, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> by the free gift of God, poſſeſſed all things for himſelf and his Seed if he had ſtood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="7">7. If as a Scepter or Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on foretold by <hi>Balaam, &amp;c.</hi> or of a Kingdom promiſed to the Son of <hi>David.</hi> for ever, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. of which there is very much in Scripture, and will then be a comprehenſive mercy for all ſorts of Saints then.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. If it be enquired how all thoſe Mercies ſhould be fulfilled in that ſtate at once to all ſorts
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:102108:34"/>of Saints in all times both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed and living, and upon what accounts to <hi>Jews, Iſraelites</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> then, who it ſeems ſhould all have their ſeveral conditions then to be enjoyed by them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="revelations">
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:102108:33"/>
                     <head>2. <hi>In Revelations.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. THis Chriſt hath mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11. to the end, in taking of the Beaſt, and falſe Prophet; and <hi>ch.</hi> 20.1, 2. in binding Satan, and in conſuming the laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gog</hi> by Fire from Heaven: and laſtly by caſting the Devil into the Lake of Fire for ever, <hi>v.</hi> 8, 9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. This is anſwered by the raiſed Saints eating of the Tree of Life in the middeſt of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe of God, <hi>ch.</hi> 2.7. which is alſo ſaid to grow in the middeſt of the ſtreet of the City, <hi>ch.</hi> 22.2.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. It is anſwered with the 12 maner of Fruits growing upon the ſame Tree in each Month, with Leaves for the healing of the Nations then, <hi>ch.</hi> 22.2.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. That is anſwered in this Key of Chriſts, by the <hi>New Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> ſtate, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. as the City prepared for the Fore-Fathers, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10, 16. whoſe Maker and Builder is God: and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:102108:34"/>for all the Saints to be raiſed then bodily, <hi>v.</hi> 40.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. They are all compriſed in Chriſts ſaid Key under the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of them that are ſaved, ſhall walk in the light of the ſaid <hi>New Jeruſalem, ch.</hi> 21.24. being ſuch as are in the natural Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">6. It is anſwered by him that ſits upon the Throne, <hi>ch.</hi> 21.5. who ſaith, Behold I make all things New at that time; and ſo the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> who hath a threefold right, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2, 3. is now appointed by God to be the Heir of all things, who will at the Reſtitution of all things alſo make all his ſaid ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Seed or Overcomers by him and with himſelf to inherit all things, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.7.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. That is to be in Chriſts Kingdom, or Reign with his Saints the 1000 years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4, 6. which is of large conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration when the Kingdoms of the world are become the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of our God, and of his Chriſt, <hi>ch.</hi> 11.15.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Chriſt hath reſolved all thoſe in the raiſing of his Saints which he brings with him, to raiſe their
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:102108:34"/>bodies in their order, <hi>ch.</hi> 20.4. when he will reward his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants the Prophets, and his Saints, and all that fear his Name both ſmall and great; whereby <hi>Daniels</hi> darker Viſion of the ſame is enlightned: and by a ſtrange, yet promiſed, both Civil and Spiritual Reſurrection of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> Ezek. 37. Dan. 12.1, 2, 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> Rom. 11. when the <hi>Gentiles</hi> of <hi>Japhets</hi> Race ſhall have their ſecond moſt full and large Call, with performance of great Promiſes to them alſo.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="discussion">
                     <p>And is not there wonderful Divine Wiſdom obſervable in ſuch a Contrivance, and wonderful Goodneſs in giving ſuch an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Key to his Church, ſo Divinely fitted to open thoſe ſo anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Propheſies and Promiſes? And will not much more wonderful Wiſdom, Mercy, Truth and Faithfulneſs, with all other Gods Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies ſhine out to the Admiration of all thoſe Saints at that time in the ſaid State, to their heightning then to a like wonderful Praiſe of the Divine Grace, with Angels, Men, and all other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10, <hi>to the end?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> and all Saints ſince them ſhall be preſent (then) at once, to ſee all their Intereſts, and well grounded Expectations (then) made good; and how the order of Times, and of all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, which have been ſuitably ordered and carried on (to which purpoſe, a Scripture Harmony might largely and profitably be written upon the account of this Key in all the particulars, from the beginning to the end of the Bible: whereby the Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Goodneſs (with other Excellencies) might appear wonderful to a believing Soul (in any good meaſure enlightned in ſuch Divine Miſteries:) Yea, if men would but rightly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, and not unworthily pervert their very Reaſon in ſuch things, they might diſcern much more than uſually they do; and if they were but as forward to imbrace what Evidences are ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, upon due conſideration of them; as they are ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to find ſtumbling-blocks in their own way, or caſt them in the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:102108:35"/>way of others, there would ſoon be more conſent to, and enquiry after theſe divine Truths, than oppoſition and reſiſtance of them: The Book given by the Father had ſeven Seals, and the Lamb is wiſe and powerful enough, to execute them in their due order, and ſo he hath done almoſt in all of them already; and what now remains may in a good degree appear to ſuch as give their minds to, &amp; duly uſe the means appointed for the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them: But if others will not, and therefore are judged by Chriſt not worthy, ſo to be taught, becauſe (as the unbeleiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Jews</hi> formerly) ſo they now alſo ſhut their Eyes, and turn away from ſuch light of Truth, the fault will then be their own: And it is obſerveable Chriſts firſt revealing, and his Spirits teaching of theſe things, is in a different way from many other divine Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines: Yea, Chriſt queſtioneth whether he ſhall find faith of theſe things, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.18. upon Earth when he comes (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his Spirit three times (as we noted) confirmed the truth of them,) <hi>chap.</hi> 19. and 21, 22. and yet of all the matters in that divine Book, no part ſo evident and clear (as was ſaid) none ſo exact and diſtinct in all reſpects of order, time, place, perſons, continuance, with all uſeful circumſtances as this ſaid 20th. <hi>chap.</hi> which hath many ſtamps of Divine Excellency ſet upon it, all very uſeful for the perſons concerned; for the opening of this great myſtery of God by the help of the ſaid Key, being rightly uſed by them, in ſome, it hath pleaſed the divine Majeſty, according to his infinite wiſdom and grace reavealed, thus by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees to ſet forth by Chriſt himſelf, the great concerns of himſelf and his Saints, the Lambs Wife; then to be in ſuch excellent Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him, as then will appear to them, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.3. And let all ſuch critical Perſons againſt theſe Truths conſider, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 25.9, 14. <hi>The meek he will teach his way, and his ſecret is with ſuch,</hi> &amp;c. and the work of Faith muſt be his own in every branch of Divine truth, tendered to any from his written word: Such as all theſe matters are, (though ſomewhat myſteriouſly ſet down) we have I conceive ſpoken ſufficiently to this purpoſe before; I ſhall therefore here adde no more.</p>
                     <p>Now for Application, We ſhall onely endeavour to give ſome breif hints thereof, referring their inlargements to future op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, if God be pleaſed to afford it, for I cannot ſpeak larg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Preſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:102108:35"/>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Inform.</hi> This may inform all Preachers of the Goſpel, and all wiſe and faithful Chriſtians, that deſire to be well and ſurely guided in theſe great things of God, reſpecting the ſaid firſt Reſurrection, of what concernment it is; to labour well to underſtand: Firſt, the curious work of this Key, given by Jeſus Chriſt, ſince he aſcended unto the Father: And Secondly, the right Uſe and Improvement of it. The curious work in it, is that it is Divinely fitted for all ancient Propheſie, and indeed for all Propheſie reſpecting the general good of Gods faithful Servants, throughout all the Bible, and of all times throughout the being of the World; all ſetting forth the neceſſity of the Saints ſaid Reſurrection; ſo revealed by our Saviour, as we ſhewed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the excellent Improvement and Uſe thereof, is to ſhew their ſpecial and peculiar intereſt, as well as the general, in all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed promiſed Mercies and Covenants, in the whole Book of God, <hi>viz.</hi> How, or under what capacity any ſuch ſpecial Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, is derived to them, and made effectual to their Souls in ſuch or ſuch a Diſpenſation of Grace to them particularly; which hath not efficatiouſly reached to many others, at leaſt, as yet; but in Charity and thankfulneſs, to endeavour truely that it may do ſo alſo, if it may be; and according to their underſtanding well the curious work of the ſaid Key, and the due improvement there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: All judicious Chriſtians may find from thence, an excellent ſure guidance; I ſay again, an excellent ſure guidance by divine aſſiſtance, to judge of the true intent and meaning of all Prophetick Scripture; all hangs upon that one Hindge of ſuch ſaid breaking the <hi>Serpent</hi> [Satan] head, <hi>viz.</hi> both his head of Craft and Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and all drive to the ſame end of Reſtauration, of men and Creatures in the World; as in the ſeveral branches of ſuch revealed Mercies, may appear, if they be rightly conſidered; and all to be accompliſhed by the ſaid promiſed Seed, within the time of his Mediatorſhip: Before thoſe things ſhall be enjoyed, that Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear heard, nor entered into the Heart of man to conceive; which will be in the higheſt Heavens after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: Whereas theſe mercies in the interim will be much of another nature; whileſt Chriſt is redeeming and reſtoring Men and other Creatures, from the bondage of Corruption, unto that glorious liberty of the Sons of God: And though there be many particular and ſpecial Propheſies many times, yet they are in their drift and ſubſerviency, to be reduced thereunto; and therefore the allegorizing of any ſorts of Propheſies, that have a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:102108:36"/>tendencie to any branch of ſuch reavealed ancient Promiſes and Covenants, muſt needs be erroneous upon whatſoever fair pretenſes, ſuch ſenſe or ſenſes are put upon them, by any man or men whatſoever. And therefore if we look unto what God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in general to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> and for their Spiritual off-Spring, through Chriſt that ſaid Divine Seed of the Woman, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 4000 years after to come in the Fleſh: Both in reſpect of the evil to be removed and the good to be obtained, anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thoſe divers times and divers ways after declared Mercies, acording to the good pleaſure of God to the fore Fathers: Or conſider aright the Covenant which God made with <hi>Noah,</hi> that Type of Chriſt for the preſervation of the renewed Earth, as the Stage whereupon God would act in all future Mercies, to be known and performed in their due time and order, to the end of the World; and thereupon the Mercies then to his people were ſaid to be as the Waters of <hi>Noah</hi> unto God himſelf, that was, ſure and infallible; and by that Covenant, both all Creatures with men have their uſual preſervation and Proviſion, by Seed time and Harveſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and their greateſt fruitfulneſs, is eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially reſerved for thoſe laſt times, when the Serpents head ſhall be broken, both eminently at Chriſts coming from the right hand of the Father, at the begining, or when his ſhall ſully deſtroy all his Churches Enemies with death the laſt, after the ſaid thouſand years: Or conſider the bleſſings of <hi>Shem</hi> and his Race to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and thence eſpecially to all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the twelve Tribes, and ſo in Chriſts lineage and forward; or the Predictions of the Calls of <hi>Japhets</hi> poſterity, the <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſince by holy Scripture explained and applied; Or as <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> both united under that one King Chriſt Jeſus, which is that Son of <hi>David,</hi> that ſhall ſit on <hi>Davids</hi> Throne, ſo long as the Sun and Moon ſhall endure, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Davids</hi> ſure mercies promiſed, reſpecting his ſaid King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and all other Saints intereſt therein through Chriſt; (for to them alſo belongs the ſure Mercies of <hi>David, Eſa.</hi> 55.3.) whereby they are alſo ſecured for Eternity; for ſuch ſhall not be hurt by the ſecond death, as riſe then to Reign with Chriſt in that Kingdom, which onely will continue to the finiſhing of his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatorſhip, but then is by him to be given up to the Father, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. And is that that muſt be during the Worlds continuance, as appears by our fifteen <hi>Reaſons</hi> in the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> pag. 9, 10. when under him the ſaid Saints glorious King, Head and Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, who prayed in that ſence before his death, that they ſhould
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:102108:36"/>be ſo made perfect in one as his Bride or myſtical Body, and willed they ſhould behold his glory then, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.21, 23, 24. when there will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> very gracious and happy performance of all ſuch promiſed mercies, in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> to the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of the Perſons or Creatures, that are to be ſo blened, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved or reſtored. So that they attend to this Iſſue, that Chriſt may be manifeſt in the world before all ſorts of Creatures, to be as perfect, yea a much more perfect, yea an infinitely more perfect Reſtorer, and Redeemer than the Devil was or could be a deſſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and deſtroyer: as all thoſe ſaid predictions in their ſeveral times and kinds, with their ſubſequent Scripture Confirmations and explication ſufficiently reſtifie: being all opened by and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated unto this Divine Key of the Son of God the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the Father: by whom the worlds were made, <hi>viz.</hi> the Old World, the New world, and the World to come ſhall be, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. with <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5. who hath, and doth, and will till then uphold all things by his Divine Power, as well as he hath Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us by his Blood, who ſhall then accordingly inherit all things, anſwerably to this his ſaid threefold right aſſigned by the Father unto him in his ſaid Kingdom; and by him to his ſuffering Saints, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.7. in the time of his ſaid Mediatorſhip, or of his <hi>Davi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical</hi> Kindom, and ſaid <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate; upon which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts the ſaid Saints the Lambs Wife ſhall then with him enjoy the ſame in their capacity; and the inferiour Chreatures then alſo be reſtored to the glorious liberty of the Sons of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.21, 23. all bowing the knee, and paying their Homage to him as Lord, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9, 10.</p>
                     <p>And for the large meaſure of Divine Grace, which will abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly then be poured out upon thoſe in the natural life, who ſhall then walk in the light of that <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> when God will Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe the hearts of that his antient people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> eſpecially, as <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. to <hi>v.</hi> 11. particularly reſpecting the ſame time, as many other Scriptures do, for that is the Foundation of all their outward bleſſings promiſed to them (eſpecially in thoſe times) for unto Godlineſs are the Promiſes of that world to come made, ſo much more than to this, in regard in that ſtate greater Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of much larger meaſure of Divine Grace, are made in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for thoſe times more generally: ſo that it is a mere blinding of the Truth for any to ſay they conceive (that is, only by gueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing) that a more ſpiritual Church ſtate will be, and yet not yield the outward viſible glory in the ſaid time belonging thereto:
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:102108:37"/>for in reference to the fulfilling of all outward Promiſes, not only to the ſaid Saints, but unto Chriſt himſelf as ſuch a viſible (then) glorious King of thoſe raiſed Saints, will thoſe large <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ward mercies be given together with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> large endowments of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> in the natural Life: and the holy Scriptures thall not be broken in any of theſe things: but Chriſt will then moſt certainly raiſe the ſaid Saints; and they as the Wife of him the Lamb ſhall then Reign with him, or as the members of that then his viſible Body, whereof he will then be their viſible glorious Head; that is, viſible to themſelves: and when alſo the then converted <hi>Jews</hi> firſt and eſpecially, with all <hi>Iſrael</hi> that then ſhall be ſaved, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. to whom alſo the great fulneſs of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> is after to come in, who being united into one fold with them, ſhall inherit all the ſaid declared and promiſed Mercies, yea and inferiour Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures then obtain their libertie aforeſaid, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that the drift of all ſuch Promiſed Mercies reſpecting the ſaid Spiritual Seed of all times before, ſhews the neceſſity of ſuch a Reſurrection of the Saints in the time of Chriſts Mediatorſhip, and the accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Divine Key unto them, many ways illuſtrates the glory of God, and that ſaid happy eſtate of the Raiſed Saints, fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelves (with Angels) for a moſt bleſſed Eternity, when Chriſts final Judgment is ended: and ſuch as would deny ſuch a ſtate preceding the ſame, muſt blot out much in all parts of holy Scripture, beſides the divinely uſeful accommodation of this Key of Chriſt Jeſus, ſo fitted for all ſuch antient Propheſie, with all the ſubſequent carrying on the ſame deſign of God for theſe ſaid happy times in the world; of which much may be groundedly ſaid under every branch of the ſame, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet all along anſwering fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the ſaid neceſſary (revealed by Chriſt Jeſus) firſt bodily Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Saints.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Inform.</hi> Since the ſaid firſt bleſſed Reſurrection of the Saints, is to Reign with Chriſt, and partake of the <hi>New Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> State in that World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This may inform all men of theſe three things, <hi>viz.</hi> Of the Antiquity, and Excellency, and Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs appertaining, or to the Doctrine to the ſaid Kingdom and <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate. Firſt, For the Antiquity thereof, it is contained in Gods firſt Declaration, as afterwards explained; expreſſed in <hi>Baalams</hi> Parable, but abundantly typified in <hi>Davids</hi> and <hi>Solomons</hi> Kingdoms; confirmed and explained by <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Prophets and Pſalms, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as in our <hi>Iren. chap.</hi> 5.6, 7, 8. And the Doctrine of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> was alſo contained in that firſt ſaid publicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:102108:37"/>but particularly manifeſt to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> ſince explained largely in the Prophets and Pſalms, and is that City the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith is prepared for the Forefathers, whoſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and Builder is God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10.16. whoſe great Priviledges have all along the <hi>Revelations</hi> been the ſuffering Saints encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The Doctrine is excellent, of a Divine and Heavenly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency; whereof <hi>Davids</hi> and <hi>Solomons</hi> Kingdom were but ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes: And the old <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was but a Type of the holy, great and beloved <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſhortly to be in the World; as it is glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly diſcribed, both by the Prophets and Pſalms likewiſe; but cheifly by our Saviour, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. and his Kingly Office is many wayes the moſt glorious part of Chriſts Mediatorſhip, ſee the Treatiſe on <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That the Doctrine of them contains much bleſſedneſs and comfort in it, is manifeſt from the time, and occaſion of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and ſetting up of both, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the time is when Chriſt comes and brings his reward with him, and all his Saints alſo to be then rewarded by him, as he promiſed to ſuch as come to him, to ſuch as believe in him, and ſpiritually eat his Fleſh, and drink his Blood, four times over, <hi>John</hi> 6. <hi>viz.</hi> That he will raiſe them up at the laſt day, which is at the ſaid Reſurrection of of the Saints, to be brought into the ſame State and Kingdom, and the large and great promiſes made to the ſame are big with variety of bleſſings, in the Old Teſtament; but in all this excellent Book of <hi>Revelations,</hi> all ſorts of Sufferers in their times, have their conſolations and encouragements from ſomething, reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that State and Kingdom, as in <hi>Prod. pag.</hi> 39, 40, 41. may particularly be ſeen, and then at the ſaid Reſurrection they will have the Dominion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.14. and rule over the Nations as was ſaid, yea then ſaith the <hi>Pſalm</hi> 149 (Conſider the whole <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi>) ſhall the Saints execute the judgement written, <hi>viz.</hi> by <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 33.40, 41. For there will never be ſuch a time or occaſion again to do it, as at the <hi>Armageddon</hi> Battel when Chriſt will wound that Head of many Countries, from the beginning of the Revenges upon that Enemy, [Antichriſt] when God whets his glittering Sword, and makes it drunk with Blood, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I do but touch upon theſe things, much more is ſaid on <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. in the <hi>Everlaſting Goſpel.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Inform.</hi> Men may likewiſe hence be informed of the exceeding great benefit, of this moſt excellent Key of all antient
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:102108:38"/>Propheſie from <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. and 21. and 22. Which the whole Book before doth cheifly make the way for; indeed it is a great mercy to Gods Church, both formerly and of late in all the ſaid times of Chriſts overcomers, of Dragon and Beaſt, that they have been encouraged therein from ſuch <hi>Revelations;</hi> of what they ſhould ſuffer was ordered by his Sovereign hand; ſo though wicked Men and Devils were the Inſtruments, yet they did ſuffer under them, according to the good will and pleaſure of Almighty God, and by the ſtrength of his Grace carrying them through all their Tryals; and they found what helps and ſupports he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for them, both preſent then, and what is promiſed for the time to come, in the Epiſtles to the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and all Sufferers after in order to theſe very times, as in the large paper in our <hi>Prodr. pag.</hi> 39, 40, 41. may be ſeen: But the benefit of this ſaid Divine Key in the laſt part, is incomparably advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and comfortable, in ſhewing from the beginning what Fonn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, of ſuch wonderful anciently revealed and promiſed mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, God hath ſo Divinely couched in them, for all Generations before and in the 1000 years, or <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate; (together) in the World wherein everlaſting happineſs, will not onely be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered upon, and ſecured to all Saints: (for none ſuch ſhall be hurt by the ſecond death) but by that State they will upon many ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages be fitted, more for Eternal happineſs, and more to glorifie God in the enjoyment of it, for evermore! Upon the abundant diſcovery (then) to be made of ſuch wonderful wayes, of Gods revealed, formerly, and then fully performed Grace in all branches thereof; which the ſaid Key leads Chriſts Servants to, by Faith till the time come of the fruition of the ſame, for the Spouſe of Chriſt, the Lambs Wife, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.9. In whatſoever times before of the Church, they have lived, they will then drink afreſh and unſpeakably, more fully the Waters of conſolation, by formerly revealed or promiſed goodneſs, in any meaſure or manner derived ro them, in their ſeveral Ages in the World, when they ſhall all together drink thereof; as the new Wine prepared for Chriſts ſaid Kingdom, in that world to come. Firſt, For thoſe of the Spiritual Seed of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> which (it is probable) knew little of any other Foundation of Faith, that the old world had; and it is to be hoped, that though all <hi>Cains</hi> curſed Seed pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in the Flood at laſt when their wickedneſs was grown to the height; yet that ſome of them by ſome ſpecial weyes of mercie, manifeſt to them before, might be ſaved by the Application of the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:102108:38"/>vertue of Gods firſt publiſhed and declared grace in Chriſt the Seed of the Woman, (through whom good <hi>Abels</hi> offering was firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) and that fundamental <hi>Revelation</hi> leads us to look fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent, ultimate and perfect deliverance from all Enemies in Chriſts ſaid Kingdom, and the enjoyment of all good, reſerved for the raiſed Saints in that ſtate.</p>
                     <p>And for all ſuch as lived after <hi>Noahs</hi> time, when the ſaid old World periſhed for their great provocations, they had (as we may ſay) a new ſtring to their Bow, by Gods bleſſing of <hi>Shem</hi> for the preſent and for the future, the Prediction of the mercy of <hi>Japhets</hi> poſterity in the calls of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> afterwards more particularly made known, as was ſhewed as another Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit Pipe conveying alſo Gods Grace unto them: Alſo ſuch as had received yet more ſpecial mercy, from the Covenant to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and his ſpiritual Seed, by that one Divine Seed Chriſt to come, by that new conveyance of ſuch Gods Grace to them, had ſtill thereby a ſtronger Title thereunto, and alſo as <hi>Iſaacs</hi> and <hi>Jacobs</hi> faithful Poſterity, as a new intayle of the ſaid mercy, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards from the renewed manifeſtation of Gods ſure mercies to <hi>David,</hi> in reſpect of his Kingdom, which Chriſt ſhall as ſurely poſſeſs with his raiſed Saints in the thouſand years; (amongſt which it is probable will be found, many that came in as Proſelytes, under all the ſaid Diſpenſations of Grace) till the time of the publick mercy of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> firſt came in, after Chriſt was come in our Fleſh; according to all the former ſpecial <hi>Revelations</hi> and <hi>Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations</hi> of the ſame, for about 4000 years before; and according to all ſuch ſeveral conveyances of Gods mercy to them, in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times they lived, (which in the 1000 years (it is probable) the Saints will largely know,) they will ſuitably glorifie the ſame Grace, Faithfulneſs and Truth of God in the 1000 years, and be filled with rejoycing therein, in greater meaſure and manner than we can conceive, when they ſhall rejoyce together as happy Members of the ſame myſtical bodie, whereof Chriſt is the Head, and as the Lambs Wife, at thoſe Divine Nuptials then to be celebrated, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.7. being the Inhabitants from that time of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> whoſe Maker and Builder is God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.9. &amp; <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10. and the wiſdom and goodneſs of God will many ways appear glorious to all ſorts, of ſuch Chriſts Subjects, in his ſaid Kingdom; when not onely the raiſed Saints will ſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly know the revealed Foundations, of their thenceforth perpetual happineſs; but the living Saints of all Nations that then
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:102108:39"/>ſhall be ſaved, and will walk in the light of the ſaid <hi>New Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> ſhall be aſſuredly ſatisfied in the ſecurity of all their preſent and future enjoyments, and in their meaſure add their halelujahs to the raiſed Saints with Angels and all other Creatures likewiſe in their Capacities, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at that time of the happy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of all things, and that ample revelation of all things in reſpect of Myſteries, Creatures and Providences paſt, when knowledg ſhall abound in the earth, as the waters cover the Sea, in all that is really good for either of them to know; and whereby they may more be engaged to ſing forth the praiſes of the Lamb, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as is ſet before us in the ſaid glimps of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which will be a School of Inſtruction for Angels and Saints more excellently to glorifie God the Father, the Lamb that was ſlain and the Holy Spirit to all eternity; and enlarge the happineſs of both ſorts of ſuch gloried Creatures accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly for ever: and though this excellent Love-letter of Chriſt to his Spouſe the Church in this his Divine Key, ſeems to ſome to be cloſe foulded up, and in Charracters, that none but his Spouſe ſhall comfortably read; yet in due time and manner, he hath, and doth teach his Beloved rightly to read in this world for her Faith and Conſolation in ſome good meaſure, and fitly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen it more and more fully for her in the fruition of that bleſſed ſtate and condition in that world to come: of which, much more from Scripture might he added.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Inform.</hi> Hence may all Saints be informed what will be then their <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> work and employment when they ſhall be raiſed at this firſt Reſurrection, they will be much in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, in, and for the work or Creation, <hi>Rev.</hi> 4 and eſpecially be exerciſed in ſetting forth the Praiſe of Chriſt the Lamb many ways, in a joynt and ſucceſſive Quire of multitudes of Saints with Angels, and all other Creatures then in their Capacity, as <hi>Rev</hi> 5.1. where is, I ſay, a glymps of that glorious ſtate repreſented us, <hi>v.</hi> 10. <hi>to the end.</hi> and they will be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry helpful to all thoſe Nations of them that are ſaved then, which ſhall walk in the light of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> to inſtruct them in what ſhall be uſeful for them to know, or do, to comfort and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them therein, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as revealed by Chriſts Spirit and grace unto them; as one of the Elders comforted the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> (when he wept) that <hi>the Lyon of the Tribe of Judah had prevailed to open the Sealed Book,</hi> Rev. 5.5. Then will be a bleſſed Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints much above what is poſſible in our preſent ſtate
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:102108:39"/>of things upon many advantages: there will be greater Grace ſhed forth, greater diſcoveries made, greater opportunities, heightned Charity, hinderances removed, powerful and uſeful helps afforded and made effectual, great delight in doing good to or for the ſaid living Saints in one Sheep fold then; undiſturbed peace, and ſecurity in well doing, and in enjoying all ſorts of bleſſings uſeful for both ſorts of Chriſts ſaid Subjects in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom promiſed, or that ſhall conduce thereunto, as God ſhall ſee good, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And hence we ſhould now labour to act in conformity to the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate, as we deſire our ſhare therein, the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant made with Gods ſpiritual <hi>Iſrael</hi> then will be fufilled in the higheſt degree the Sons of Men that of are capable receiving: Yea, and it ſeems probable, grace will then be derived lineally to them, their Seed, and Seeds Seed for ever, as we have ſhewed in <hi>p.</hi> 13, 14. of our <hi>Foundations of Faith:</hi> which will be proper to that ſtate; therefore ſuitable means will be then by God provided for them and bleſſed by him accordingly when her watchmen ſhall never hold their peace day nor night: and when not only raiſed Saints and Angels will be neer aſſiſtants upon all good opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ready to do any good office for them, when all evil Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are removed; as other places of this Divine Book do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, as <hi>ch.</hi> 7. another Elder informs the Apoſtle of the white Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Palm bearers; and <hi>ch.</hi> 14.6. Angels or Meſſengers warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Church, and threatned the Enemies: ſo <hi>ch.</hi> 17.6, 7. ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcovers that Whore and Beaſt, and ſhews their deſtruction; and laſtly, another Angel ſhews the Apoſtle all theſe glorious matters of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate, and confirms them to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and true, three times over, when the Apoſtle ſeemed ſo to be rapt with Admiration, that he would have worſhipped the Angel, if he had not reſtrained him, <hi>ch.</hi> 19.10. &amp; 22.8, 9. yea, and Chriſt himſelf will be the light of that City, in whoſe light they ſhall ſee light, immediately, or mediately, and why are things ſo decypher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this moſt Divine Book but to make them known to his Church: and it is all according to the Prophets, if rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, and applyed, as <hi>Eſa.</hi> 60. in <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. and other places as largly might be declared to divers purpoſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="5">5. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi> This may alſo inform Chriſtians why Satan hath ſo long been ſo eagerly bent from age to age againſt theſe Doctrines of the <hi>Davidical</hi> Kingd: of Chriſt, and the <hi>New Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> ſtate the ſaid 1000 years, which will be the great priviledge of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:102108:40"/>all the faithful, joyntly being made then perfect in one, when they ſhall behold Chriſts glory there, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24 for it is obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that ever ſince thoſe ſeven Vials were revealed to be poured out upon the Kingdom, Earth, Seas, Rivers, and Throne of the Beaſt, and laſtly upon the Prince of the power of the Air too, <hi>ch.</hi> 16. he hath ſpitefully ſought to pour out his ſeven Vials upon this Doctrine of Chriſts ſaid Kingdom, as we ſhewed particularly, <hi>p.</hi> 41. &amp; 42. of our <hi>Prodr.</hi> for indeed the coming of that Kingdom will not only end his for 1000 years, but when he ſhall attempt to reſtore it again, all his Vaſſals ſhall be utterly caſheered from the earth, and himſelf in the end caſt into the lake of Fire and Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone: but that is not all, for his malice is moſt againſt it upon this account, that the Wiſdom and Goodneſs of Chriſt is manifeſt by this Divine Key, framed and given by himſelf to his beloved Spouſe, and fitted by him (in due time) to open this Cabinet of ſo precious Jewels, which were formerly ſo locked up in ſuch antiently revealed Promiſes and Covenants; for that without it the Church of Chriſt could not have been reſolved ſufficiently when, or where, or by what means, or how long ſhe ſhould ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the wonderful benefits therein contained: but this moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Key is ſo fitted for her uſe, that by the due improvement thereof, the Church cannot chooſe but ſee her great Treaſure therein reſerved for her againſt the marriage of the Lamb now coming on: the fore-ſight whereof, provoked him formerly to great wrath againſt the Womans Seed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.12, 17. when he entered upon his laſt deſign of the two fold Beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. but how will this Doctrine enrage him the more, that ſhews his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms ruine to draw ſo neer; hence, in theſe latter times, he ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth up all ſorts to plead againſt it with many groundleſs preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and many of them contrary to others, not only by ignorant, and mean, but by ſome great and learned too; and which is more ſad, not only by enemies, and bad men, but ſometimes by friends; in the main, and good men, upon intereſt or error, and one diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage or other, as in <hi>Aſſert.</hi> 10. of our <hi>Key:</hi> and yet ſo good news was never made known to mankind ſince the fall to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained whilſt the world continues, as this will be (ſaving only the particular Salvation of every believing ſoul) I ſay, as this, which all ſuch Saints ſhall together enjoy at the ſaid ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt to Salvation, when our Saviour bids them <hi>lift up their heads, for their Redemption draweth nigh,</hi> Luke 21.28. yea, <hi>and this Kingdom of God</hi> alſo <hi>is</hi> then <hi>nigh at hand,</hi> v. 31. when he will ſend
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:102108:40"/>his Angel with a great ſound of a Trumpet to gather his Elect from the four winds into his Kingdom, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.31. This doth bring the Devil into an envious Hell of Torment, otherwiſe, long before his time, and will plague him with deadly dumps all the time of his long impriſonment the 1000 years in the bottomleſs pit; that like diſcontented <hi>Judas,</hi> or melancholy <hi>Saul,</hi> he would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſparately make an end of himſelf if it were poſſible: it is not to be doubted but the Preaching of theſe Doctrines upon many conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations will ſting him to the heart; and therefore wherever it is like to prevail, he will buſily beſtir himſelf by all means he can to hinder it: and we ſhall not need to wonder at it for the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons before ſaid, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="6">6. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Inform.</hi> This ſhould diſcover the exceeding greatneſs of the folly of all carnal, ſelf-ſeeking, fleſh-pleaſing unregenerate perſons in the world, who place all their happineſs in the things of this preſent liſe, and have no expectations of Good for Eternity: indeed in reſpect of what concerns the body, which they only, or chiefly look at, it muſt lie, like the beaſts, in the duſt above 1000 years to come; but if they depart the world in that condition, their Souls will immediately thereupon feel the horrour of Gods indignation, with miſery unconceivable; but if they would wiſely provide for the body, which they chiefly ſeem to regard, they ſhould lobour to get into a capacity of the bleſſed <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate, with all the ſaid Saints that will produce a ſpeedy return, for the time draws neer of the happineſs of the whole man, Soul and Body: preſent or ſpeedy poſſeſſion is a great motive in earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purchaſes; but much better is this, and that for a long enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of 1000 years with Chriſt and his Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be perfected in Eternity: ordinarily mens hopes for body and ſoul together is not till the laſt Trumpet; but Chriſt, that is thebeſt Teacher hath evidently ſhewed the Bodies of all that ſleep in him, when he comes at the firſt Reſurrection, will in their order be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with their Souls for that happy ſtate 1000 years before: if worldly men were ſure the preſent ſtate of things would continue but half 1000 years, how would they be encouraged to lay out for Purchaſes for that time? but when there ſeems to be good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that men may not groundedly hope it may continue the twentieth part of 500 years, how wary have they cauſe to be in laying out their Treaſure in ſuch a ſhaking, tottering, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding World: unto which the ſaid <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> will ſuddenly ſucceed in that world to come whereof we ſpeak: If men be born
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:102108:41"/>again by ſound Regeneration ſpiritually, then they ſhall riſe from the dead with the Saints bodily, a thouſand years before the reſt of the dead, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5. which is like to prove a ſpeedy poſſeſſion incomparably above all worldly enjoyments in the beſt way they can be had here; as we ſhowed before in many particulars: but by the way which bad men love, purſue, or by Gods long ſufference enjoy the world; it were better not to have had a being in this world, than ſo to have had it without Repentance, for the abuſe of what they have had therein; for all that ſuch perſons find in it is the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, the pride of life (the matter of their preſent ſin) and the cauſe of their future miſery; and now this world of it ſelf is moſt vaniſhing, ſtanding upon its laſt leggs (as we ſay) and though that deluding old Harlot, like <hi>Jeſabel</hi> or old, a little before her death, paints her ſelf to hide her wrink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led face, and gaſtly countenance; and adorns her ſelf in gorgeous Attire, yet is ſhe for very age ready to give up the ghoſt, and leave all her Paramors, like old Myſtery <hi>Babylon</hi> the Mother of Harlots, to make them crye out there, Alas alas, alas alas, when all is loſt and deſtroyed, <hi>ch.</hi> 18. Oh then for a Saints part in the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate, for ſo excellent, long, ſecured happineſs which will end in eternal bleſſedneſs; what would ſuch men give for it if it could be then had, and they had withal to purchaſe it? If men would befriend their bodies; what good policie would it prove to get them befriended there, and take adviſe ſpeedily in that caſe; when God begins to ſhake not the earth only, but the Heavens alſo: the Scripture tells us (that he that ought to be) the deſire of all Nations is about to come, and are there not great ſhakings of both at this preſent time? &amp; it ſeems from Script very probable that that next great ſhaking fit of the world is not far off, deſcribed, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 2.17. <hi>to the end,</hi> with <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. will ſhake moſt impenitent unreformed ſinners from off the worlds ſtage into the bottomleſs pit, to bear their Maſter company whoſe ſervants ſo they are, for that ſhaking Earthquake will be ſuch as never was, mighty an Earthquake and ſo great, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.18. and ſuch a time of Trouble as men never ſaw, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. I point out theſe things only, I cannot now preſs them ſaving by my Prayers, that God would ſet them home for good, that poor ſinners may now at laſt be plucked like ſire brands out of the fire. And let all ſorts conſider now they uſe the world at preſent (though they abuſe it not as ſome ſenſual bruitiſh perſons, wallowing in groſly notorious courſes of licenciouſneſs, hardning and priding themſelves in
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:102108:41"/>their groſs impieties) yet what do they with their enjoyments? all that men have in the beſt way are Talents that God will have account of; how will the great tryal be when Chriſt ſhall Judg at laſt; <hi>in as much as ye have not done it to the leaſt of my Diſciples, you have not done it unto me,</hi> Mat. 25. <hi>go therefore ye curſed,</hi> &amp;c. If men would take off every yoak, and comfort the diſtreſſed, feed the hungry, cloath the naked, if leſs was ſpent in vanity, more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on deſigns to promote works of piety and charity, men would make better accounts than it is to be feared moſt rich and great men will then do; who, if they pervert not their power and wealth to hinder good, and promote evil, yet will be condemned an guilty in Chriſts day: for not hindering evil, and not promoting good, every Commandment of God hath a poſitive ſcope: but otherwiſe, let ſuch look to have all pride and hautineſs of men in honour, in wealth, in any worldly abundance to be humbled, and then driven from their Places and Poſſeſſions, or periſh with them; when their perpetueties here will utterly end, their world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honour will vaniſh ſo far as they have not honored. God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, their great and coſtly buildings will tumble down upon their heads, or otherwiſe be deſtroyed or burnt up, and then they ſhall leave all their Treaſure buried for ever in the worlds ſudden ruines, and neither they nor theirs have any good of thoſe things that they would not ſuffer others to have good of before, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 2.17, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and then will be no time to do it when thoſe things ſhall be no longer theirs, nor any left to confer them upon within their reach; and yet muſt unavoidably be called to an account for them, and condemned, without early reformation: and our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our tells he comes as a thief in the night, and his coming will be as a ſnare upon the whole earth: but what then will become of thoſe that by Rapine, or Violence have increaſed in wealth; that have abuſed their Power, and Authority, to Oppreſs, and Perſecute? the plenty of Gods Creatures to conſume them in riot and exceſs in many ſorts of ſinful vanities, the heavier load will hereby lie upon them, that they are not only privitively evil, but poſſitively alſo: make to your ſelves then friends (ſinners) as Chriſt your Judg formerly commanded of the unrighteous Mammon, whilſt ye have time; but if ye will not quickly do it, Chriſt himſelf will provide for his meek ones, who ſhall then inherit the earth, and delight themſelves in abundance of peace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Inform.</hi> Hence all Chriſtians may be inſtructed that many comfortable Doctrines may be drawn from the ſaid Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:102108:42"/>of ſuch conſolations to be enjoyed in the ſame <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate to come, at the neer approaching Reſurrection, to anſwer the preſent wants of them in many particular caſes now; what, are they here perſonally troubled and moleſted? then they ſhall have, yea delight themſelves in the abundance of peace; they ſhall (ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>) have reſt with us when the Lord ſhall be revealed from Heaven with his mighty Angels, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7. whilſt thoſe that troubled them ſhall have Tribulation rendered to them: Chriſts Church now militant will begin from the entrance of that ſtate to be more and more Tryumphant: If they want the good company of ſuch as excelled in vertue, but are now taken out of the world, they will ſhortly meet with them again with great advantage, perfected both in Soul and Body at the ſaid firſt Reſurrection of the Saints bodily: if they would have more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward grace, or outward ſupply; both will rightly be ſupplied in the Saints Reign with Chriſt the 1000 years on earth: (ſtumble not at that expreſſion, I have it from Jeſus Chriſt, however Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan barks at it.) Would you get much honour, achieve great things? this honour have all Chriſts Saints, as ye heard, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149. <hi>the last,</hi> Thus you ſee by the help of this excellent Rey, the rich Cabinet is opened, that you may take out the Jewels one by one for your uſe: The ſtudy of theſe Doctrines to rightly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Souls, concerning theſe things, will be to them a School of Pleaſure, ſeconded with exceeding great Rejoycing: Chriſtians, I ſpeak it by experience, I wiſh you all partakers thereof with me, or that I might be helpful to inlarge your meaſure.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Inform.</hi> Let all true Chriſtians know, that the ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and promoting of theſe Truths will provean excellent and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent means to beat down <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the Kingdom of Satan; it is therefore no marvel that Satans brood and Babels brats are enemies thereunto upon any occaſions; it muſt be expected it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares the ruine of both ſpeedily; <hi>Babylon</hi> the great is fallen, is fallen almoſt in the order of accompliſhment, and God (ſaith the Apoſtle) ſhall tread down Satan under your feet ſhortly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.20. and now his time of being bound is nigh at hand: it will much diſturb both of them to hear much of that news; and it wil put much cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in Chriſts Champeons to fit them to fight Chriſts Battles, under his own banner againſt his and their own enemies.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Inform.</hi> Hence take notice what an enforcing neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is now incumbent upon all Profeſſors of Religion, eſpecially in an higher degree than ordinary, to take care they fully anſwer the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:102108:42"/>ſame, and eſpecially to avoid the practical conſutation thereof in their converſation: let them not be ſeeming Saints, but real Saints here; or elſe they will not be amongſt the raiſed Saints at Chriſts appearearance: they muſt paſs through the firſt Reſurrection ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual (only proper to the Saints here) before they can have any poſſibility of any part of that firſt Reſurection bodily, of the Saints hereafter: if they be not firſt here regenerate with them, it is moſt certain they will not then be raiſed from the dead with them: look to the catalogue of ſuch as will be ſhut out of the bleſſed and holy ſociety, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.7. &amp; 22.15. namely, the fearful, the unbelieving, the abominable, and Murderers, and Whoremongers, and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerers, and Idolaters, and all Lyars ſhall not only have no part of the Saints inheriting of all things, but ſhall be caſt into the lake of Fire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and again, without, <hi>viz.</hi> the Holy City, are Doggs, and Sorcerers, and Whoremongers, and Murtherers, and Idolaters, and whoſoever loveth and maketh a a ly, though theſe laſt lyars ſeem more eſpecially to reſpect Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters and the promoters thereof, who have a lye in their right hand, yet the other ſpeaking of all lyars, includes all hollow de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful, falſe hearted Hypocrites, that will pretend much love to God, Chriſt, and his Saints, but have no true love for them as ſuch, unleſs they are carried on by ſome ſelf reſpect or other, and all ſorts that reſt in a form of Godlineſs, either by a ſeeming high profeſſion only, or the low practiſe of ſuperſtition, two dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ways of lying in the world in theſe evil days, whilſt they both deny the power thereof: they both in their kinds hinder much good, and promote much evil, towards God and Men: God, his Religion, his Name is diſhonoured by them both; their brethren are deluded, or ſeduced, or ſcandalized by them; theſe do God much diſſervice, but are the moſt uſeful ſervants of Satan; and eſpecially the higher pitch of Devotion they pretend to, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſcandal they are to true Religion: and how much better might it be for themſelves and others, that they appeared only to be what they are, than to ſeem to be what, indeed, they are not; whereby they will be excluded out of the Holy City, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Much Doctrinal information may be had, if men ſeriouſly ponder theſe Truths, which we ſhall not here farther at preſent ſet down, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>We ſhould proceed to a word of Terrour againſt all obſtinate, impenitent, ignorant and hardned ſinners; And alſo to a word of Conſolation to poor, humble, diſpiſed, faithful Chriſtians of all ranks, but theſe we have done in others of our Practical Parcels,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:102108:43"/>upon other Texts of like nature: We ſhall now add a word of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition to all Chriſtians briefly. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Adm.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let therefore all ſorts of Chriſtians, into whoſe hands the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers may be delivered, and unto whoſe ears theſe Doctrines may have acceſs, be hence admoniſhed to make uſe of the ſhort time remaining now to them in this decripit ſading world, to labour the more ſpeedily and earneſtly, now to demean themſelves, as wiſe Virgins, to provide to have Oyl in their Cruſe, and to have their Lamps burning: and carefully watch for the Bridegrooms com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: we have our Saviours own enforcement here of now to be improved in its proper ſeaſon about the ſixth Vial, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I come as a thief in the darkſome night, of moſt ſinners ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and happly in the time of the night alſo; and in the time men are leaſt aware of; as <hi>Sodoms</hi> flames ſuddenly kindled by the fire of filthy prevailing Luſts: then bleſſed is he, ſaith Chriſt, that watcheth, and keepeth his Garments leaſt he walk naked, and they ſee his ſhame; for ſuch as have not on them the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Garments of Juſtification, and Sanctification <hi>(for the Kings Daughter is all glorious within)</hi> yet together with a ſuitable holy Converſation, they will when the Bridegroom comes, be aſhamed before Angels and Men: [and now we may obſerve the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Froggs are croaking in Kings Palaces, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] otherwiſe they will not be admitted unto the happy marriage of the Lamb, neer approaching: Wherefore Chriſtians, now or never, ye muſt believe as Chriſtians, act as Chriſtians, love as Chriſtians, ſeek peace as Chriſtians, ſuffer as Chriſtians, pray as Chriſtians, rejoyce as Chriſtians, let your whole Converſations towards God and Man be ordered as becometh Chriſtians; and then with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Bride, ſay, come; and let him that heareth, ſay, come; and let him that is a thirſt, come; and whoſoever will not linger, and be loſt, let him now, whilſt it is called to day, take the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of life freely, <hi>chap.</hi> 22.17. For he that teſtifieth theſe things, ſaith, ſurely I come quickly: It is <hi>Verbum Diei in die ſuo,</hi> a word in its due ſeaſon; for it appears to be in its due order of accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment, and the Links of the Revelatian Chain have been paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by above 1600 years, the laſt Link draws neer, to which Chriſts Kingdom will immediately ſucceed: Come in poor Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, get an intereſt therein and then you will be ſafe: I pitty you all that prize it not; I pray God give you enlightned under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, and ſanctified affections now the world is vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with all her Vanities together: ſuppoſe it ſhould continue
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:102108:43"/>twenty or thirty years longer, yet how ſoon may you die in your ſins, or be cut off in Gods wrathful diſpleaſure in a moment, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you be ſecret ſinners, though nothing is ſecret to, or hid from Gods all ſeeing eye, or open ſinners, to him all things are naked and open with whom you have to do; or if you be great ſinners, none are ſo great but the leaſt ſtroak of his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure will ſhatter them in pieces; or ſmall ſinners (though none that is not a Saint can be a ſmall ſinner in the ſight of God, though (comparatively) in the ſight of men he may: and ſuch as have committed great ſins, upon their Faith and Repentance may be pardoned as ſoon as the leaſt: But you that are great ſinners, and would fain think your ſelves out of Gods reach, and upon world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advantages ſeem to bid defiance unto God, ſaying (as they) let him haſten his work that we may ſee it: or you that think with the Fool in the Goſpel, you have enough for many years; or you have great Intereſts, great Alliances, great Relations, great Honour, Wealth, Authority, power to execute your will and pleaſure, and what not: if you came well by them, then there is more reaſon you ſhould ſerve God, and honour him with them the more; they are all Talents, and you muſt be accountable for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one of them; have you fed, clothed, viſited Chriſt in his Diſciples; if not, go ye curſed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. but if you came ill by them, and uſe them contrary to his will, the greater Vengeance hangs over your head for that reaſon, without Repentance: Yet to conclude, there is yet a time of Grace and Mercy to be had for you (great ſinners) if you will improve it aright, before it be quite paſt; be wiſe therefore at laſt, now, now, now, whilſt it is called to day; be not hardned any longer by the deceitfulneſs of Sin; then may your Souls ſafely, and comfortably joyn with Chriſts Spouſe in her hearty <hi>Amen</hi> for the Bridgrooms com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſaying with her alſo, <hi>verſe</hi> 20. <hi>even ſo, Come Lord Jeſus, Come quickly.</hi> Amen.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Laſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> Laſtly, for Exhortation to Thankfulneſs, to all that ſhall have part in this ſaid bleſſed Reſurrection of the juſt upon this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular account, &amp; now more eſpecially in theſe times; That Chriſt Jeſus hath not only given this excellent Divine Key to his Church, opening the many great benefits of thoſe ancient mercies, reſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be accompliſhed in the ſaid thouſand years; and alſo ſo fitly agreeing with the Doctrine of the ſaid bleſſed Reſurrection of the Saints, with all the concomitants thereof: But now in theſe times is ſo graciouſly pleaſed to diſcover and vouchſafe unto us
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:102108:44"/>the comfortable Uſe and Benefit thereof, by Faith upon ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Divine antient moſt ſure Foundations, as thoſe before ſet down, and alſo by holy Scriptures ſo explained and carried on to thoſe intents in the ſaid times, and that the ſaid bleſſed Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſhould be the inlet to all former Saints, to thoſe happy enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments then for their Souls and Bodies in ſuch a bleſſed Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, many wayes as the ſaid Saints ſhall then attain unto: The abundant ſtrong evidence whereof is not only ſufficient, if duly weighed to ſtop the Mouths of gainſayers, but to convince all ſoundly rational men, that Gods great Proviſion for the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the Bride and the Lamb, at the time ſo by his word de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and publiſhed, will not be in vain and loſt; for God is not like men to change or be deceived in, or fruſtrated of his end: But what Thankfulneſs in theſe reſpects, do all ſuch true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans owe to the great God and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, that from all ſuch ſaid Foundations, he hath wrought Faith in their Souls to foreſee with faithful <hi>Abraham,</hi> Chriſts day to come by Faith and receive ſuch comfort in ſo happy news of ſuch manifold ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching mercy; wherein they have ſuch particular intereſt and concernment; and all this ſo ſtrongly founded upon evidences throughout the whole Scripture; ſo clearly explained by Chriſt, and by the Holy Spirit to be words faithful and true three times over; and delivered for their uſe by his Servant <hi>John:</hi> Beſides the many renewed particular promiſes, ſince ſet down with ſundry explications of them, both in Old and New Teſtament, which do evidently lead us to the uſe and benefit of this ſaid divine Key, ſo given by Chriſt Jeſus to his Church for ſuch excellent purpoſes: how ſhould the approaching reign of Chriſt with his ſaid Sts. in the world in that time of the new Heavens and new Earth, fill ſuch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiving Chriſtians Souls with praiſe &amp; thanksgiving? when a double advantage will redound unto them, firſt that the great laſt Enemies of Chriſt and his Church, will be removed and taken away, that ſo long have obſtructed her joy and peace, but that the Church of Chriſt ſhall alſo enjoy the end of her hope, from all the ſaid Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, and promiſed Mercies, then to be performed in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſtate to be upon the ſaid bleſſed firſt Reſurrection of the ſaid Saints.</p>
                     <p>And what ſtronger evidence than from that firſt moſt large comprehenſive Foundation, given by God himſelf, <hi>Gen,</hi> 3.15. which about 3000 years after, had ſuch a particular explication of Chriſts carrying on the ſame upon his Aſcention after his actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:102108:44"/>laying the Foundation of his Churches Redemption, by his ſufferings at his firſt coming, which ſhould ſo eminently be carried on by making his Foes his Footſtool, at his ſecond; when he ſhall come from the right hand of the Father, to judge the quick and the dead, at the ſame time of his appearance and Kingdom, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that antient divine Oracle, ſo often repeated, illuſtrated and explained in the New Teſtament. <hi>The Lord ſaid unto my Lord ſit thou on my right Hand, till I make thy Foes thy Footstool,</hi> Pſal. 110.1. <hi>viz.</hi> at that ſaid time as many Scriptures teach, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. alſo conſider <hi>Ezek.</hi> 38. and 39. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.45. of the <hi>Turk,</hi> with many others, both reſpecting the ruine of <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Turk</hi> the firſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> before the ſaid thouſand years, and for the ruine of the laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> after the ſaid thouſand years; Our bleſſed Saviour hath moſt orderly, exactly, and ſtrongly confirmed the ſame in thoſe many circumſtances thereof, in the following part of this <hi>Chapter:</hi> when the laſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy death will be deſtroyed, and the Devil caſt into the Firy Lake; and I hope no Conſcientious knowing Chriſtian of any rank will dare to deny or gainſay any particular, in this great Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo explained, carried on and applied all along in the word of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of which much more is ſaid in our <hi>Everlaſting Goſpel,</hi> on <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.</p>
                     <p>And <hi>Enochs</hi> Viſion of the firſt Act of Chriſts Judgement, <hi>Jude</hi> 14. alſo confirms the ſame as it is explained by <hi>Daniel</hi> 7.7, 8, 9. when the Judgement is ſaid to be ſet and the Books opened to give the body of the Beaſt to the burning flame; which will be at the beginning of the ſaid thouſand years, as alſo <hi>Gogs</hi> [the <hi>Turks</hi>] de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 38. and 39. before the ſetting up of the <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi> chap. 40. to the end of that Book, with the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way others that do offend then, <hi>Mat.</hi> 73.41. when alſo he will judge the Saints with reward, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19. ſo judging both the quick and dead then, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. and likewiſe <hi>Revelations</hi> 20.7, 8, &amp;c. is contained Chriſts laſt proceeding in his Judgement after the 1000 years, againſt the laſt <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> as by Chriſts <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation</hi> is here explained, to judge thoſe quick, and then the dead, when their Judgement is ſaid again to be ſet, and the books opened: firſt by declaring the abſolution of the Saints written in the book of Life, and pronouncing againſt all the wicked, a Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of condemnation to eternal death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:102108:45"/>
                     <p>Of the firſt Act of Judgement, alſo <hi>Balaam</hi> ſpeaks <hi>Numbers</hi> 24. when the <hi>Romane</hi> Kingdom ſhould periſh for ever, explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed again by our Saviour, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17.8. when in the laſt Head it ſhould go into predition: whereby an utter end will be put to the four mettle Kingdoms or the <hi>Gentiles</hi> Dominion, and ſo this Propheſie paſſeth in the ſame courſe with the former, as another Confirmation of the ſame Truth: How Chriſt will eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the beginning, and fully at the end of the ſaid thouſand years break the Serpents [Satans] Head, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And theſe are ſtrong and clear evidences from Gods Word, of Chriſts taking away the Enemies of himſelf and his Church in thoſe times; and that ſtate of things ſhortly coming on: to theſe we might add the Type of <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſubduing the five Kings, and reſcuing <hi>Lot:</hi> And of <hi>Davids</hi> overcoming all his Enemies at laſt, and leaving his Kingdom to <hi>Solomon</hi> his Son in a peaceable condition, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and as the Enemies deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will be a great matter of the Saints Praiſe and Rejoycing at their firſt ſaid bleſſed Reſurrection; ſo will alſo their enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the happy Viſion of Chriſts Glory in his <hi>Davidical</hi> Kingdom then be given to them; as <hi>John</hi> 17.24. with the happy communion with him, and one with another; and their inheriting all the promiſed Mercies of that time, and ſtate of the <hi>New Jeruſalem, Revel.</hi> 21. and 22. by the Divine promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Seed of the Woman, who ſhall then prolong his days in the world, and abundantly ſee his own Spiritual Seed; ſo that he will therein be ſatisfied when the will of the Lord ſhall proſper in his hand, as foretold, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 53. namely, when all Saints are come in at the general Rapture, and change of them all, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.51, 52.</p>
                     <p>And that the earth might continue to be the ſtage for all ſuch actings of God in the world, God upon his ſmelling a ſweet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour from <hi>Noahs</hi> offering through Chriſt to come, makes a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with him after the Flood for all Creatures, to that happy time; and that then there ſhould be the greateſt fruitfulneſs in it, his word is clear: and as in <hi>Noah,</hi> as a Type, was ſignified how Chriſt would be the ſafe Ark of his Church, in the beginning, and after the end of the ſaid 1000 years; and alſo by his Propheſie of the <hi>Gentiles, Japhets</hi> Poſterities, mercies at their foreſaid firſt and ſecond Call and Fulneſs, which laſt will be performed in the ſaid 1000 years, when <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhall both rejoyce together,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:102108:45"/>when all thoſe many Promiſes concerning that ſtate of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> happineſs in the whole book of God will take their full effect.</p>
                     <p>And as ſurely by vertue of Gods Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſhall all his ſpiritual ſeed through that his own divine ſeed Chriſt, then enjoy the many Promiſes ſtill remaining in Old and New Teſtament to be made good to them in the natural life (then) whether circumciſed or uncircumciſed and ſuch raiſed Saints then that are intereſſed therein, will alſo enjoy by the ſame Covenant that happy New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate in that City prepared for them then, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10, 16. and alſo all the ſpiritual ſeed of <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> with them in all the priviledges and benefits belonging to the ſame, which the ſaid Saints ſhall then be rayſed to inherit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as the ſpiritual ſeed of <hi>Abraham;</hi> and I doubt not but the greateſt part of the Promiſes in Old and New Teſtament made to God's people as the ſpiritual ſeed of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> both circumciſed and uncircumciſed, will chiefly have their fulfilling in that ſtate and time wherein all ſuch their natural race will have the greateſt ſhare, and ſuch promiſes as are made to all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or to <hi>Ephraim,</hi> or <hi>Joſeph</hi> joyntly with <hi>Judah</hi> do eſpecially refer unto (though not only unto them) of which if duly conſidered a large volume might profitably be written.</p>
                     <p>And if laſtly we look to that laſt ſure foundation of <hi>Davids</hi> ſure mercies, concerning his Throne and Kingdom, which Chriſt the Son of <hi>David</hi> ſhould enjoy as the dayes of heaven upon earth, or as long as the Sun and Moon ſhall endure, (though <hi>Davids</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural race had forfeited their intereſt before, <hi>Mic.</hi> 2.10.) yet God laid ſure foundations for the other, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.8, 9. to the end, and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89. with multitudes of Scripture evidences to the ſame purpoſe, and all Believers, as <hi>Eſay</hi> ſhews, ſhall alſo have their part in the ſame ſure mercies of <hi>David,</hi> Chap. 55.3. appertaining then to that time and ſtate, and very many other Promiſes were made to that end likewiſe: And the intereſt of Chriſts ſaid Davidical Kingdom ſeen by <hi>Daniel</hi> a long time paſt in Viſion to be at the end of the fourth Kingdom, <hi>chap.</hi> 7.13, 14. which at this time Chriſt continues in heaven to receive, and then to return, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.17. it is that that contains in it eminently all the other ſaid mercies to all ſuffering Saints that muſt then reign with Chriſt the ſaid thouſand years, and joyntly enjoy all the happineſs thereof, and thence forth and for ever whatſoever things God hath provided for them, which eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (though the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:102108:46"/>things of this ſtate may moſtly be both heard and ſten, as decy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phered by Gods Word:) Concerning which I conceive ſufficient hath of late been ſaid, by us and others, both to ſatisfie all ſerious judicious and well principled Chriſtians that know how to value Divine Authority without reſpect to men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to convince many others, and what greater arguments could be uſed for ſtrength and clearneſs to confirm ſuch a long ſealed or concealed truth, I know not: if Gods Spirit ſhall at any time ſet them home upon their ſouls and conſciences, which he is only able to do, <hi>viz.</hi> to work faith thereof, as in all other Divine (eſpecially myſtical parts of) Doctrines, that ſo they with all true Chriſtians, both now by faith aforehand, and then by fruition of the ſame, may be better inabled thereby to render all honour, thankſgiving and praiſe, both now and then, due unto the great God and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, upon all thoſe manifold and great Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture foundations and engagements upon account whereof Chriſt will then be ſo admired of all his ſaid Saints, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. How glorious will Chriſt appear (then) in his wonderful, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, ſuddain Converſion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and Uniting of the two Sticks of <hi>Ephraim</hi> and <hi>Judah, Ezekiel</hi> 37. which were as iſcattered drie Bones before compared there, and <hi>Romans</hi> 11. to a Reſurrection from the Dead: Shall not they have then the chief Dominion? Will not God then give Nations for them? Shall they not then lengthen their Cords and ſtrengthen their Stakes? Will they not be Gods Battle-Bow and Ax to cut down Enemies, who ſhall then be as Aſhes under the ſoals of their feet? and all People be deſtroyed that will not ſerve or be ſubject to the Holy <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> then? Many and great will be the Priviledges of that antient Inheritance of God, then ſaved by the Lord, when he takes away their Sin, and circumciſes their Hearts, as antiently <hi>Moſes</hi> foretold of that time, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.1. to 11. it would requne a large Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume to ſet forth the many great and excellent priviledges of that People of God at the ſame time, and as our faith of that Mercy ſhould enlarge our thankſgiving and praiſe, ſo by both ſhould Chriſtians be ſtirred up to earneſt Prayer for them for the haſtning of their Mercy: the neglect of which is a great error and ſcandal too, in theſe our dayes, and the great neglect thereof cannot be anſwered to God or man, when Scripture Promiſes of the manifold inlarged mercies and goodneſs of God
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:102108:46"/>reſerved for that now abject obſtinate people at preſent, yet will, e're long, be thoſe that will meet with the moſt miraculous and wonderful, many wayes inlarged and illuſtrated free grace of God in Chriſt that ever was ſhewed to any people in the world, of which all the Prophets, and divers Texts in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment declare great things ſhall be accompliſhed, and the Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving and Prayers of all faithful Chriſtians ought, what in them is, to haſten them: It is Gods way to bring on his revealed and promiſed Mercies, though he needs none ſuch helps to mind or move him, yet he will ſo own both his Saints Graces, his own Ordinance, and gracious Promiſes: And the like may be ſaid of all other the aforeſaid great mercies then to be fulfilled, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which very much might here be added inſtead, whereof I only now add my Prayer to what hath been ſaid already. The Lord God give his bleſſing to what according to his revealed Truth hath of theſe Divine Myſteries herein been delivered, for the glory of his own holy Name, and the real good, edification and comfort of all faithful Chriſtians, <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>This uſeful Treatiſe for all Chriſtians, ſetting forth the Marriage of the Lamb with his Bride,</hi> Rev. 19.7. <hi>ſhortly to be Celebrated, may be had at the</hi> Turks Head <hi>over againſt the</hi> Royal Exchange: <hi>or at the</hi> Herne <hi>in</hi> Pauls Church-yard.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="errata">
                  <head>ERRATA.</head>
                  <p>Page 22. col. 1. line 26. dele <hi>more.</hi> p. 24. c. 2. r. <hi>ſatisfied</hi> not <hi>fulfilled.</hi> and after r. <hi>men are</hi> not <hi>means.</hi> p. 28. c. 1. l. 9. r. <hi>mercy</hi> not <hi>merit.</hi> and l. 10. r. <hi>ſad</hi> not <hi>ſaid.</hi> p. 33. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. p. 35. r. <hi>to them of the Armie.</hi> p. 36. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. p. 47. l. 39. <hi>to believe</hi> joyn <hi>unleſs he put his fingers,</hi> &amp;c. p. 53. r. <hi>as we are</hi> not <hi>as were.</hi> p. 63. l. ult. dele <hi>Chriſt.</hi> p. 69. r. <hi>all tend</hi> not <hi>attend.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
